<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Atheism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/atheism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Atheism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 10:11:17 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/atheism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ontology of Jain authors: Ramayana</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontology-of-jain-authors-ramayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 10:11:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontology-of-jain-authors-ramayana/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am not sure what the discussions are about. Here are some of the problems that have surfaced.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do (did) people in India believe that Ramayana is (was) a narration of &amp;lsquo;what really happened&amp;rsquo;? Even without specifying the &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;where&amp;rsquo;, the answer is obvious: some (did) do; some (did) do not; some are agnostic. The question, however, is: What is the question about? What problem is it meant to solve? Does the answer I give solve any problem? If it does not, that shows that this is not the issue at stake. So, what is the issue then?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Can we talk about truth in Fiction? (The example of Holmes.) Yes, we can and do so very regularly, not only in common parlance but also in literary studies. However, the issues are: how should we understand this way of talking (there is controversy about it) and why is this relevant to Ramayana?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Did some Indians begin a discussion about the existence of Ramasethu and the temple of Rama in Ayodhya (of today) only relatively recently? Yes, I think so. I do not know of any discussion that occurred on this issue, say, a thousand years ago. Again, what is the problem?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Did Indians have no notion of the &amp;rsquo;truth of Ramayana&amp;rsquo; before their contact with non-heathen cultures? This is an ill-formed question, as far as I am concerned, because it is unclear what counts as an answer. Equally, it is unclear what the question is about: (a) is it about the Indian notions of &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo;? (b) is it about the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; of historiography? (c) Is it about the relation between &amp;lsquo;belief about the truth of historiography&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;rsquo;truth of historiography&amp;rsquo; independent of people&amp;rsquo;s beliefs about its truth?&#xA;These are merely some of the questions that have surfaced. May I request that we resume the threads with clear problem statements so that we can make some headway?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;II&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belief vs Faith</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 23:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) It appears to me that in these discussions, a very vital issue (if we want to talk about Judaism, Christianity and Islam, and their &amp;lsquo;problems&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;, etc) is not being recognized. and that is this: religious &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; are not accorded their place, and are talked about as though they are merely a subset of the class of &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) &amp;lsquo;Being a believer&amp;rsquo; (I will confine myself to Christianity for the sake of brevity) does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean assenting to the proposition that &amp;lsquo;God exists&amp;rsquo;. For, if this is what it would mean, then the Devil himself is the first believer: after all, he does accept it as true that God exists. (The Devil is not an atheist, mind you.) He knows that God exists: after all, he rebelled against him! As the new testament Bible puts it: &amp;ldquo;thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the devils also believe, and tremble.&amp;rdquo; (James 2: 26)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atheism: a secularized theism—Jakob de Roover</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 01:25:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1: Atheism is a phenomenon that came into being in the western culture at around the time of the so-called Enlightenment. The West claims that it liberated itself from the dogmas of the Christian religion in this Enlightenment, and those who call themselves atheists mean by this that they belong to the enlightened people who &amp;ldquo;have escaped from the dogmatic illusions of religion.&amp;rdquo; Now, as it has always done, Christian Europe simply identified its own history with human history in general, and it claimed that all cultures had so far been under the ignorant spell of religion, but that they could now be liberated by the Enlightened West. This claim needs two separate premises: (a) That all cultures have religion (b) That atheism was a new and rational system of beliefs that could liberate people from all cultures from this illusion of religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
