<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tradition on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/tradition/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tradition on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/tradition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Questioning the axioms</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are three ideas in the West about Law that are taken as axioms. The first: all societies are founded on Law; if they are not, they ought to be. The second is that Law teaches and educates a people. Third is their corollary: only thus do a people become a Nation. As far as I know, none has shown their empirical truth or proved that they are logically necessary. But their truth-value is undisputed. When they ruled India, the British followed these axioms: they tried to educate us through Law, interfered in our festivals and social practices and the State tried to educate a barbaric people by enacting  ‘just’ laws. Romulus gave Law and made a group into a people; Moses gave Law and made a people into a Nation; Mohammed gave Law and transformed multiple nations into a caliphate; Manu acquires the exalted status of a Law-giver for the ‘Hindus’. These ideas are not dated, apparently. Today, they enjoy the same privilege they had during the colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ad hoc explanations: why do puja to cows?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2011 03:03:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we provide explanations, we should also look at their contrastive nature: why do puja to cows and not to buffalos? The problem in this case, however, is this: the explanation one gives about a tradition (you will soon see that one of the problems is to identify the explanandum itself) must also incorporate this contrast. Someone like Kanch Ilaiah has answered this question thus: the puja to cows and not to the buffalos expresses racism (that is at the origin of the caste system) because cows are white and buffaloes are always dark. In other words, you cannot simply ask for a contrastive explanation without incorporating it in a &amp;lsquo;bigger&amp;rsquo; explanation that explains the explanandum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translations or Travesty of Traditions? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:51:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one sense, the title of the piece captures the nature of the tasks facing the contemporary generation, whether in India or in the Diaspora. This generation, unlike many from mine, is confident and self-assured; perhaps, it is proud too about the strength of its culture and traditions. Rightly so. However, personal convictions about the value of our traditions and culture do not automatically guarantee the truth of such convictions. Not only that. It is also the case that the history of India, and that of the entire humankind, requires of us that we are able to say and show what is valuable and what is not in our traditions. This history is the history of colonialism, subservience, and is further weighed down by the scientific, technological, economic and the military weight of the western culture. Today, we need more than a mere practice and a further continuation of our traditions; we need also to examine them honestly and critically in order that we may transmit what we found valuable in them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Follow Our Forefathers: The Nature of Tradition –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:25:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading this contribution and all the others (&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;) I hope to write, we need to keep the context in mind. The context is this: many intellectuals, both in India and among the NRIs elsewhere, appear bent on transforming our multiple traditions into a single &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. The problem does not lie in the transformation of variety and diversity into a unity. Rather, it lies in trying to fit our traditions into the straightjacket of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. While calling ourselves &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; might be a convenient way of talking, the danger lies in going further and trying to develop &amp;lsquo;doctrines&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;theologies&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;catechisms&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Ten Commandments&amp;rsquo; so that those around us in the West could recognize us as followers of a religion called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. (These reflections are also applicable to &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Jainism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Saivism&amp;rsquo; and all such entities.) In the course of my future contributions, I will look at some of the compulsions that force us to manufacture &amp;lsquo;Hinduism as a religion&amp;rsquo;. In this piece, I want to focus on the nature of traditions. What is a tradition? What differentiates religions from traditions? The second question will remain implicit until the end. By that time, we should have a better understanding of what it means to speak of a tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is tradition akin to following moral obligations?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 04:45:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditions are inherited practices, which mean two things: they are both transmitted and learnt. The learning occurs through imitation, following instructions, through stories and so on. Consequently, traditions &amp;lsquo;change&amp;rsquo; (i.e. undergo modifications) even as they are being transmitted and learnt. This makes traditions flexible and adaptive.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human practices conserve, that is, we do not go around inventing new practices every day. In this sense, traditions are essentially conserving in their nature. This is one of the reasons why we see &amp;lsquo;being traditional&amp;rsquo; as `being conservative&amp;rsquo; as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do practices need rational justifications?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-practices-need-a-rational-justification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 22:57:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-practices-need-a-rational-justification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If we understand the word &amp;rsquo;tradition&amp;rsquo; to mean &amp;lsquo;a set of practices&amp;rsquo;, then the question is this: why continue a set of practices? When someone &amp;lsquo;justifies&amp;rsquo; (I will soon explain why I use scare quotes for this) this by referring to the existence of a set of practices, what exactly is the person doing?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One way of looking at it is to say that the person &amp;lsquo;justifies&amp;rsquo; his actions and understand justification to mean providing a logically derived conclusion from a set of premises. The validity of the reasoning would constitute the justification in this context. Quite obviously, because we are speaking of logical justification, we are inclined to formulate the premises, test the derivation and look at the truth value of the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
