<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Symbolism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/symbolism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Symbolism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:36:30 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/symbolism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interpretations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:36:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are multiple kinds of interpretation. For instance, there is interpretation of symbols in a domain like Physics: μ (in elementary optics) is &amp;ldquo;interpreted&amp;rdquo; as the refraction index of a substance. We use a more or less analogous notion of &amp;ldquo;interpretation&amp;rdquo; in Chemistry, Mathematics and so on. In logic, we speak of &amp;ldquo;interpretation of variables&amp;rdquo; like &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;, etc. Here, it means that the letters stand-in for arbitrary sentences with truth-values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why study the Western culture?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two substantial questions have been raised in response to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/&#34;&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;: (a) why do we need to study and understand the Western culture in order to access our own traditions? (b) Is it my claim that Buddha and Shankara (for example) are irrelevant to us? One other sort of &amp;lsquo;objection&amp;rsquo; too has surfaced, albeit disguised as a characterization of what I have said: (c) is not my position itself illustrative of &amp;lsquo;Eurocentrism&amp;rsquo;? These issues are intertwined.  Hopefully, addressing them together will lend some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of NRIs and their symbolic interpretations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:34:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vyasa&amp;rsquo;s argument (to the extent we can speak of an argument in this context) is quite subtle: When Urvasi comes to Arjuna at the behest of his father, and when she is possessed by desire, and when the Apsaras choose freely and unconfined, then (a) one cannot reject her; (b) and with the argument that she is a superior to him. If you split this conjunction and cast in normative terms, it says something like this: (a) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when one&amp;rsquo;s father indicates that a son should sleep with a woman; (b) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when the woman is sexually attracted to oneself; (c) Rejection of a woman, whoever she might be, is not permitted when she chooses freely and without confines. Because such a rejection is triply prohibited (or forbidden), Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s argument that he &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the parent of his race (which has only one prohibition) possesses less value. So, Urvasi is justified in her curse of Arjuna. In other words, if we read this fragment of Mahabharata in normative terms, Arjuna was wrong in not having an incestuous relationship with one of his great-great-grandparents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1&amp;rsquo;. While one could argue that one &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the &amp;lsquo;superiors&amp;rsquo;, Urvasi suggests that because she has chosen freely, this argument is void. On top of saying why Arjuna is wrong to reject sleeping with her, she also comes up with two other reasons why he could sleep with her: (a) Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s ancestors have done so and without committing any &amp;lsquo;sin&amp;rsquo;; therefore, it is &amp;lsquo;permissible&amp;rsquo; that he does the same; (b)  it is a morally good thing to emulate one&amp;rsquo;s ancestors and therefore Arjuna &amp;lsquo;ought to&amp;rsquo; sleep with her.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indian culture’s attitude toward sex vs. Christian Morality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/indian-cultures-attitude-toward-sex-vs-christian-morality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:14:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/indian-cultures-attitude-toward-sex-vs-christian-morality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with the assumption that our stories about Indra and the Gandharvas are just that: stories, authored by human beings, without truth-content. (That is to say, they are neither true nor false.) When human beings write stories, their imagination is (partially) constrained by their societies, cultures and the times they live in. None quite knows how exactly the latter constrain human imagination even though the extant theories about myths try to explicate this relation: some see in them a mirroring of society, some see in them a disguised historiography or sociology, some see in them a personification of virtues, and so on. Because this issue is not settled yet, I shall presuppose the truth of none of the theories about myths that dot the landscape. However, I take the &amp;lsquo;constraint&amp;rsquo; I spoke about to incorporate the following minimal claim: the myths suggest that some attitudes fall within the limits (or transgress them, as the case may be) of the cultures whose myths they are. Under this assumption, let me isolate some of the attitudes that come to the fore if we look at our stories about apsaras.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victorian morality of NRI and middle class Hindus: Prostitution, Adultery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 05:53:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The Indian traditions did not have the same attitude as Christianity towards prostitution or adultery. And the Indians of yesteryears were not defenders of the Victorian (and Christian) morality. Of course, I approvingly said that the &amp;ldquo;Indians are not prudes&amp;rdquo; but this approval has to do with the thrust of Indian thought, as I have understood it: the impossibility of prohibiting or making obligatory some or another action universally. (This is my formulation, of course.) I do believe that the Indians recognized the impossibility of abolishing prostitution (which is why it is called &amp;ldquo;the oldest profession&amp;rdquo;). Instead, therefore, of banning and condemning prostitution (and subsequently turn a blind eye towards its existence), Indian thinkers suggested that we treat the prostitutes humanely. I have never been to a prostitute nor will I ever go to one; but that does not mean that I want to ignore their existence and treat them as non-humans. Nor am I willing to call all those who visit prostitutes as criminals and perverts. I know of too many lonely men and women who have found human warmth and personal comfort in the arms and companionship of prostitutes to consider them as perverts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are stories symbols?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-stories-symbols/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 03:11:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-stories-symbols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Here is one way of looking at what stories are. They are symbols. What are they symbols of? Well, they could symbolize acts; they could also be symbolically interpreted as justifications of such acts. Under this construal, a story requires an interpretation: one has to interpret the story as a symbol of either an act or as its symbolic justification. (The same applies to looking at stories as symbols of values. The stories, for instance, could be seen to symbolize virtues. Stories could also symbolize passions, feelings, natural forces&amp;hellip;) Then, stories are mostly, if not always, symbols of something or another. When you look at the issue this way, it is almost akin to saying that stories are &amp;ldquo;evidences&amp;rdquo; of sorts: some story or another provides &amp;ldquo;evidence&amp;rdquo; about the presence of &amp;ldquo;something else&amp;rdquo;. (Let us leave aside the issue of what it means to talk of a symbol in all these contexts or what &amp;ldquo;evidence&amp;rdquo; means here. Both terms can be understood in a vague sense for our purposes.) In another language, we can say that all stories are signs. These signs must be turned into signifiers (this requires an act of interpretation) by showing or suggesting that they signify &amp;ldquo;something else&amp;rdquo; (called the signified).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linga, Puja, Symbolism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/linga-puja-symbolism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 20:24:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/linga-puja-symbolism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbolic interpretation of lingam from a netizen&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;In ancient India, there was a fertility cult; our ancestors &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that it was a fertility cult; Lingam was a symbol for the phallus then; it continues to be one even when many millions are ignorant of this now; and that the Modern Indians&amp;rsquo; attitude to sex is inhibiting because of which they do not see the symbolism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To keep the contrast between us stark, here is what I say: Lingam is not a symbol of anything or anybody. Lingam is &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; Shiva&amp;rsquo;s puja is done (as against, say, how we do puja to Vishnu) by the Indians. You tell me that this &lt;em&gt;factual claim&lt;/em&gt; is wrong and that by saying what I have just said, I project my present to &amp;rsquo;explain&amp;rsquo; the past. Very well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
