<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Buddha on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/buddha/</link><description>Recent content in Buddha on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 23:10:29 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/buddha/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Humility is a despicable vice</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/humility-is-a-vice/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 23:10:29 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/humility-is-a-vice/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity (to some extent Judaism), presented an idea, unknown to the world in which it grew, namely the Pagan world of Rome. The idea was that human beings are creatures of God and that they belonged to His domain. He was the dominus or the Lord of the domain. As a result, human beings should not be arrogant, but must be humble instead. (As the ‘Book of Job’ in the Old Testament makes it clear, there is a very heavy price to be paid for arrogance.) Here, it belonged to the opposite spectrum in Ancient thought, which saw arrogance as a moral virtue and humility as a despicable vice. Protestant Christianity, especially Luther and Calvin, very forcefully propagated this idea: Man was a sinner, worse than the lowest worm, because of which God’s Grace becomes unfathomable and ungraspable.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Alleged conflict between 'Buddhism' and 'Brahmanism'</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/alleged-conflict-between-buddhism-and-brahmanism/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 22:54:35 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/alleged-conflict-between-buddhism-and-brahmanism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If the ‘I’ cannot be individuated or described, then there is no possible distinction between the ‘I’ and ‘the Brahman’. They are different names for ‘self-awareness’ which pick out the differential access that individuals have to ‘self-awareness’. Hence, the curious distinction that some Indian traditions make. On the one hand, the ‘I’ is alleged to be identical with the ‘Brahman’; on the other, the same traditions distinguish between ‘Atmagyaana’ and ‘Brahmagyaana’. These two ‘gyanaas’ can be two types of knowledge, if, on one reading, they are knowledge about two different objects, namely ‘atman’ and ‘Brahman’. If, however, they are identical, there could be only one knowledge. Second, even that is not possible. We can only have knowledge of something, if that something exists. If Atman or Brahman exist in this Universe, they are also subject to the processes that occur here. One such is decay and disintegration. Therefore, if we think this problem through, there is only one conclusion possible (if we assume that all Indians have not always been imbeciles): the gyaana is about the processes of accessing the real. It is not and cannot be about the real.
This means that the debate within the Indian traditions is not and could not have been about the nature of ‘atman’ or ‘Brahman’. Thus, the idea that is propagated as ‘the’ truth about the alleged conflict between the dvaita and the advaita is spurious and false. There was clearly debates and conflicts. But these cannot be about the nature of the real.
The same is true about the alleged conflict between ‘Buddhism’ and ‘Brahmanism’. Atman and Anatman are not conflicting doctrines about the real at all; they could not be. It is logically impossible that this was the debate between representatives of these traditions, unless we assume that Indians are congenitally incapable of thinking logically,. Those who sell this story, whether in India or abroad, the western savants and their Indian slaves, are the truly perfect imbeciles, which they actually think that Indians are. These idiots are our professors and many guru’s in India and elsewhere.
Thus, we see that Ambedkar and the Ambedkarites (in India and elsewhere today) are total slaves of their western masters. To ‘convert’ from ‘Hinduism’ to ‘Buddhism’, as though they are conflicting religions, is to simply ape the western cretins who have been selling this story for nearly 200 years. Of course, the Ambedkarites do that because their fame and fortune depends on slavery. They would rather be slaves of cretins than live free as thinking human beings. The western ‘thinkers’ in the US fete them because they love the adulation and adoration they get from these Indians. And, as is the case with Pollock, they are “friends with benefits” with Indians:  getting millions of dollars from idiots like Narayan Murthy and receiving national awards from the Indian government.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Indian heathens' misunderstanding of meaning(purpose) of life</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-heathens-misunderstanding-of-meaning-andor-purpose-of-life/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 05:17:29 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-heathens-misunderstanding-of-meaning-andor-purpose-of-life/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sanskrit word (that I know) that comes closest to the Greek &amp;rsquo;telos&amp;rsquo; is &amp;lsquo;Sankalpa&amp;rsquo;. It means &amp;rsquo;to mentally determine&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;formulation of an end&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;desirous of (an end)&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;anticipation (of an end)&amp;rsquo; etc. It also means &amp;lsquo;Buddhi&amp;rsquo; in some contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the primary properties of religion is that it &lt;em&gt;generates&lt;/em&gt; questions about &amp;ldquo;the meaning and purpose of life&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;meaning and purpose of existence&amp;rdquo; and such like, both at an individual level and at the level of a culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding Buddha and Colonial Consciousness</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-buddha-and-colonial-consciousness/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 19:42:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-buddha-and-colonial-consciousness/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How do we understand the idea that an enlightened person has no wants?&amp;rdquo; Before we understand what the idea says, it would be good to find out what it does not say. Understanding this would also allow us to appreciate the depth and extent of colonial consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the way the Buddha was portrayed in the middle-class text books you studied (that is also how he was more or less portrayed during my period), it appears as though he &lt;em&gt;gave up&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;renounce&lt;/em&gt; all his desires. In other words, he became an &amp;lsquo;ascetic&amp;rsquo; man. Yet strangely enough, if we read about the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s road to enlightenment, we find something else: he did take to and practice asceticism, but, he says, it did not help him to get enlightened! That is, even though some people do practice asceticism and can get enlightened (after all, every path can lead to enlightenment), this was not the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s way. The Buddha, then, did not become enlightened by &amp;lsquo;giving up&amp;rsquo; his desires. Almost in a similar vein, Purandara Dasa also says in his &amp;ldquo;Eenu Maadidareenu Bhava Hingadu&amp;rdquo; that &amp;ldquo;punishing his body&amp;rdquo; did not help him.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>