<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Translation on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/translation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Translation on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 10:41:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/translation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Western intellectuals are not idiots</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/western-intellectuals-are-not-idiots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 10:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/western-intellectuals-are-not-idiots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He says: &amp;ldquo;Doniger translates &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;. Apparently, Indians should not criticize that because we know neither what the English word &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; means nor do we know what &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; means because neither English nor Sanskrit is our mother tongue.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;First of all I do not say or imply that Indians &lt;em&gt;should not criticize&lt;/em&gt; the translation. I merely point out that (a) there is indeterminacy in translation across two languages and &lt;em&gt;therefore&lt;/em&gt; (b) we can only make &amp;lsquo;qualitative&amp;rsquo; criticisms. That is to say, one must suggest &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the word &amp;ldquo;Dharma&amp;rdquo; should be translated in all those different contexts that Doniger translates it as &amp;ldquo;Religion&amp;rdquo;. Otherwise, the criticism (&amp;ldquo;that it is not an &amp;lsquo;accurate&amp;rsquo; translation&amp;rdquo;) is bogus.&#xA;Secondly, I did not say nor imply that we&lt;em&gt;do not know&lt;/em&gt; the meaning of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo;. That is, I did not claim that these two words are just as intelligible to us as the words &amp;lsquo;pif-paf&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;paf-paf&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He further says: &amp;ldquo;We may have the word dharma in Hindi but it may mean something different in Sanskrit. Besides, both these words are ambiguous &amp;ndash;another reason we can&amp;rsquo;t criticize the translation since we don&amp;rsquo;t know all the shades of meaning of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; nor of &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo;. Similarly when &amp;ldquo;brahmin&amp;rdquo; is translated as &amp;ldquo;priest.&amp;rdquo;  Of course Doniger could have translated &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;perversion&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;brahmin&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;idiot&amp;rdquo; and since we don&amp;rsquo;t know what &amp;ldquo;perversion&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;idiot&amp;rdquo; mean either, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t really criticize that as well.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Again, I did not claim nor did I imply that we must know &amp;ldquo;all shades of meaning&amp;rdquo; (whatever that means in the present context) in order to translate. Nor does it follow from anything I have said that one could then use &lt;em&gt;any word&lt;/em&gt; in one language to translate &lt;em&gt;any word&lt;/em&gt; from another language.&#xA;That there is indeterminacy of meaning in translation does not entail that one denies that words have meanings, surely. Words occur in a language and a language has rules, conventions, dictionaries, and such like. It has a syntax, semantics and pragmatics of communication. Who has denied this? Quine has not; nor have I.&#xA;It is the linguistic convention to translate &amp;lsquo;dharma&amp;rsquo; as religion and &amp;lsquo;brahmin&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;priest&amp;rsquo;. One cannot fulminate against this centuries-old practice unless one comes up with alternatives and shows why the alternative is &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; than the centuries-old practice. Until such stage is reached, wisdom counsels us to keep quiet. To reach such a stage, &lt;strong&gt;it is not Sanskrit or English that one should study&lt;/strong&gt; but the relevant phenomena in the world to build a theory about the phenomenon in question.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The subsequent paragraph simply repeats the same misunderstanding without understanding &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/&#34;&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, to understand my post and react to that, the presupposition is that one has read what linguists and philosophers of language have written about meaning and use. If one has not done this work, and has merely some vague common-sense ideas about translation, then one should have the minimal humility to keep quiet and not attack Doniger&amp;rsquo;s translation.&#xA;This, then, is the &amp;ldquo;point of my argument&amp;rdquo;. Do not think that western intellectuals are idiots and imbeciles. Being an Indian and a native speaker of some Indian language does not give you some marvelous ability to criticize the western intellectuals based on your common-sense ideas about the world. People like Wendy have put in years of serious effort to learn languages and theories and if one wants to take them on, one must make sure that one is their intellectual match. And that requires years (if not decades) of dedicated work. That is the &amp;ldquo;point of my argument&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spirituality = Adhyatma?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/spirituality-adhyatma/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 18:46:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/spirituality-adhyatma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One could justifiably see spirituality (the Jewish, Christian and Islamic) as ‘Adhyatma’ if one focusses on the psychological transformations that a human being undergoes in the process of moving from the mundane life to a ‘spiritual’ one. You would be closer to the notion of ‘Adhyatma’ if you can also additionally guide such a process. Such guidance requires, of course, that there is some deep understanding of such transformative processes and their mechanisms.&#xA;Yet, I would be hesitant to suggest that ‘spirituality’ translates ‘adhyatma’ or the other way round. From among the many reasons, I pick three:&#xA;(a) because the weight of the word ‘spirituality’ is drawn from Christianity, i.e., the kind of transformative force on a human being that we have in mind is the work of the ‘holy spirit’, it would be inappropriate to translate ‘adhyatma’ as ‘spirituality’;&#xA;(b) it is difficult to characterize the changes in human beings that we are talking about by using this word in Islam and Judaism as well. There is no ‘holy spirit’ in these two religions that does the work of the Trinitarian holy spirit;&#xA;(c) since a ‘spiritual’ person is the result of the workings of the holy spirit, in the context of Adhyatma which insists that transformations are the results of human phenomena working on human beings, the use of this word would be inappropriate. Both the Christian and the Adhyatmic use militates against such a translation.&#xA;In short, no, we should not translate ‘spirituality’ as ‘adhyatma’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truth, belief, intentionality, eudaimonia, ought</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:15:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to respond to three of your points Claus. First you are not talking only about the Greeks and the Romans because all the problems arising with respect to the phenomena of non-Western societies and culture are/were equally the problems in the frameworks of different varieties of culture. You not only talk about the Greeks and the Romans, you gave examples about the French and the English as well.&#xA;The second point is: you talk about the fact that people face the same problem in Europe of today when they talk about the Greeks and the Romans. You are absolutely right. But that confirms my point, namely, that the Greeks and the Romans had no religion. They were Pagan cultures and this is exactly the problem with India. The Christian culture doesn’t understand Greek — the whole of Heidegger’s philosophy is an example of that. He says we cannot think Greek. And his whole attempt to speak about what thinking is, what truth is, etc. — is an attempt to rescue the Greek language from what he called the Christianization of Latin. I am aware that contemporary European languages and modern Europe do have problems with the Greeks and Romans. But just because of the fact that Ancient Greece and Rome are located in the Western hemisphere does not make them part of Western culture. In an earlier publication, I showed that neither Greece nor Rome were cradles of Western civilization. Western Civilization is Christian Civilization, although you might not agree with that. Greece and Rome do not belong to it. That is why we Indians can understand them. Let me give you a small example — One of the most fundamental notions of Aristotle is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, which gets translated with great difficulty as ‘well-being’, ‘feeling good’, ‘happiness’ and so on. It is a very difficult word to translate. This is not merely a translation problem because I have had discussions with Greek scholars. Aristotle asks: what is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;? It is very difficult to achieve of course but he says once you have it you cannot lose it. I told a Greek Specialist once ‘you know nothing about Greek language’, He responded: ‘how dare you say that’! So, I said: ‘here is a simple thing, forget the translation of &lt;em&gt;eudaimoni&lt;/em&gt;a, give me one example of a human  property which once you possess, you do not lose.’ I said: ‘I do not have to understand Greek to understand what &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; means.’ And of course to this day, no Greek scholar could help me in giving one example of one human property which if once you possess you do not lose&amp;ndash;this is a fundamental property of &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;. For the Indians here is my answer. &lt;em&gt;Eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;aananda.&lt;/em&gt; Once you have &lt;em&gt;aananda&lt;/em&gt; you do not lose it. It is equivalent in some conditions to &lt;em&gt;brahma-gyaana.&lt;/em&gt; And that is happiness indeed, beyond &lt;em&gt;sukha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;duhkha&lt;/em&gt;. So when Aristotle is talking about &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; I understand him and I read him carefully. Of course, there is no translation equivalent of eudaimonia in any of the European languages but that is because they have no access to that world, that conceptual framework like we Indians have. So indeed, I understand you have a problem with Greece and Rome: we understand them much better.&#xA;Two other points &amp;ndash; one on Galileo. I am not conflating the community of Christians with a community of non-Christians because one of the claims I have substantiated to which in the last fifteen years I have found no counter argument, is the following: My claim is that free thinkers and atheists, even the Communists of Europe, are actually disguised theists. That is to say that Christianity has secularized itself in political theory, in social theory, in rational choice theory; a number of theories. I can show you how assumptions from the Bible have taken secular forms. So by saying for instance, ‘look I don’t have a religious background’, it makes no difference. I know people, who do not have a religious background for generations, are atheists but they continue to have the same excuse for speaking as Christians do. For example, your ethics will be absolutely no different from Christian ethics because there is no such thing as non-Christian secular ethics present today. ‘You ought not to kill’. Don’t tell me that is an example of secular ethics. Even the notion of ‘ought not’, the normative notion itself, does not come from English: it comes from Christianity, from the Bible.&#xA;Aristotle, for example, does not have an ‘ought’. Indian languages do not have a ‘moral ought’ nor do the Chinese in their language in which Confucius wrote. These are not linguistic issues, Claus, these are problems of conceptual apparatuses that are culturally developed. So, it is in that sense that I speak about Galileo and say he made sense to the Europeans. They used his findings to investigate nature because they believed fundamentally that nature has a structure and pattern and a law which has to be discovered by human investigation. They would say that without such a structure the universe should be chaos. The whole of 2,000 years of European culture believes that, and that was Galileo’s idea as well. It is a background belief, of course, but it is a background belief of that culture and we are talking about difference between cultures. Translation is always a translation between people who use sentences, who use natural languages. So, I am shifting the level of the problem.&#xA;Last point, there is something to be said for your claim regarding the notion of belief&amp;ndash;that you can have a concept, but do not have a word&amp;ndash;that is absolutely true. That is our daily experience. I feel like saying something but I don’t know how to say it. So, you can have some sense of a concept but defined psychologically not linguistically or so cognitively. I do not know how to put it in a natural sentence. Right. But you are making out of it logical and philosophical points.&#xA;Let me put it very sharply. The notion of having a belief and the belief is always about something; this is a specific conception of man, of human beings&amp;ndash;there is philosophical anthropology which attributes some notion of intention to human beings. One of the extraordinary things about the Indian tradition is the absence of this notion of intentionality:  &lt;em&gt;agyana&lt;/em&gt;. They call it &lt;em&gt;maaya&lt;/em&gt; and many different things. So the nature of human being in the Indian tradition is that we are non-intentional creatures, which is completely incomprehensible within the framework of Christian culture. So, entertaining having a belief is not a linguistic, psychological, epistemological fact which is applicable to all human beings but is a specific assumption about the nature of human beings that comes from the Bible. So when saying that Indians have beliefs, you are not making use of any understanding of language – you are making use of a religious concept/understanding of man and saying that is what Indians have. Of course, you can say that; people have been saying that for 500 years. That is not the issue.&#xA;The issue is: is this how Indians understand themselves? In fact, if you look at the languages you find there is greater affinity when you talk of using work-words. They do not say ‘I got angry’ but ‘anger came upon me’ &amp;ndash; this is a very typical old classical Greek way of talking. ‘Why did you say that?’ ‘I do not know, my tongue moved that way’. I am literally translating local Indian languages into English&amp;ndash;this is the way we talk. In fact, even the subject notion, is not simply a linguistic subject or verb subject in action, the fundamental ontological notion of subject itself is missing in India as also the notion of agency.&#xA;Take the problem about truth: the notion of truth for applying to sentences, to propositions by some other philosophers is a very philosophical disease. If you look at the middle-ages, take Aquinas for example, he had two notions of truth: &lt;em&gt;adeequatio re&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;. One is which is adequate to the object; the other which is adequate to thoughts. Hegel used the same notion. Tarski also says there are multiple notions of truth. That notion of truth — &lt;em&gt;adaquatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt; as it prevailed for 1,900 years in Western culture referred to the fact that objects are adequate to how God conceives them. That is &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;adequate not to human intellects, to God’s intellect. &lt;em&gt;Adequatio re&lt;/em&gt; had to do with how one related the word to both these notions and emerged, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; from any understanding of language, truth, philosophy, or logic, it arose from commenting on theologies and commenting the Bible.  (pp 162-166 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stupidity of Indian meanings of English words</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/stupidity-of-indian-meanings-of-english-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 10:31:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/stupidity-of-indian-meanings-of-english-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: For a broader application and context, please read this paper: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/2014-comparative-theology.pdf&#34;&gt;translation, interpretation and culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;rsquo;temple&amp;rsquo; is not used in English to refer to a place where false gods are worshipped. It is used to speak of &amp;ldquo;the temple of Solomon&amp;rdquo; (the king Solomon of the Jews) too and there is no suggestion in the western culture that the Jews worshipped false gods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Your friend is providing you with an identifying description: &amp;ldquo;this building which&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and identifies it in terms of several functions tied to that building.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Random Substitution: Worship and Puja</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 13:52:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Firstly, you want to know whether there is anything intrinsically  wrong with performing idol worship the way it is with robbery.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us assume that we agree we know what robbery is and that it is intrinsically wrong. We need to make these assumptions because (a) in all probability, the robbers do not see anything intrinsically wrong in the act of robbing; (b) even then, some of us might not be willing to call a &amp;lsquo;Robin hood&amp;rsquo; (who robs only the rich and passes on the spoils to the poor, retaining a modest &amp;lsquo;commission&amp;rsquo; for himself and fellow robbers) an immoral person; (c) to most of us, it is unclear whether the windfall profits that oil corporations have made in the last years constitute robbery or not and so on. Under these assumptions, you are drawing an analogy between idol worship and an act that a human being performs with respect to fellow-human beings. This analogy breaks down because idol worship is not a relation between human beings but between a particular act of a human being (called &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;) and the entity worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How would one translate the word &#39;God&#39; into, say, Sanskrit?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-would-one-translate-the-word-god-into-sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 19:14:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-would-one-translate-the-word-god-into-sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the question: How would one translate the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; into, say, Sanskrit? Now, the answer has to satisfy certain conditions because the question also meets certain conditions. Let me say very clearly what all these are, so that the playground and the rules are transparent and favour no one party in the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I propose we accept the best theory of meaning that exists in the market place. As far as I know, the book that plays this role most admirably, while satisfying the proponents of different theories of meaning expounded during the last century or so, is Prashant Parikh&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Language and Equilibrium&amp;rdquo; (The MIT press, 2010). His formal apparatus allows for the existence of &amp;lsquo;word meanings&amp;rsquo; without sacrificing the idea that the meaning of sentences are context-dependent and makes sense of even such statements as &amp;ldquo;the meaning of red light is&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; That is to say, it does not restrict &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; to words and sentences alone; it also allows us to deal with &amp;lsquo;word meaning&amp;rsquo; as well, as it is in our case. If my colleagues unanimously prefer another &amp;rsquo;theory of meaning&amp;rsquo;, I would like to know what it is. In all probability, I would not take issue with an alternate choice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf&#34;&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf&#34;&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115&#34;&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translating vibhaktis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translating-vibhaktis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 22:06:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translating-vibhaktis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The problem is more complicated and the implications far more massive than either of us can even dream of. In fact, I think we are not even aware of the nature, size and the dimensions of the problem(s) today. We do not even know whether we are dealing with something called the ‘translation’ problem or whole sets of other issues and problems that also redefine what it is to ‘translate’ texts between different cultures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation, Interpretation and Culture: On the disingenuity of a comparative theology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 00:42:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balu&amp;rsquo;s paper on comparative theology, and in particular Francis Clooney&amp;rsquo;s:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/5497443/On_the_Disingenuity_of_a_Comparative_Theology&#34;&gt;Translation, interpretration and culture: on the disingenuity of a comparative theology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation: Spontaneous or Intentional</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 22:10:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If we want to grasp the nature of the discussions in the Indian traditions, there is much we need to do beforehand: (a) identify the entity they were talking about; (b) identify the specific questions they were answering; (c) identify the generic questions that defined both the outlines of the acceptable answers and the formulation of the specific questions; etc. (The &amp;lsquo;cetera&amp;rsquo; indicates that I do not know how to enumerate all the things we need to grasp.) In the case of the propositions you have formulated, I assume that &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; is Vishnu (or even Krishna) and not, say, Shiva or Brahma because you are talking about the Madhvas. However, to keep the discussion faithful to your formulations, I will use the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; to refer to Vishnu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translations or Travesty of Traditions? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:51:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one sense, the title of the piece captures the nature of the tasks facing the contemporary generation, whether in India or in the Diaspora. This generation, unlike many from mine, is confident and self-assured; perhaps, it is proud too about the strength of its culture and traditions. Rightly so. However, personal convictions about the value of our traditions and culture do not automatically guarantee the truth of such convictions. Not only that. It is also the case that the history of India, and that of the entire humankind, requires of us that we are able to say and show what is valuable and what is not in our traditions. This history is the history of colonialism, subservience, and is further weighed down by the scientific, technological, economic and the military weight of the western culture. Today, we need more than a mere practice and a further continuation of our traditions; we need also to examine them honestly and critically in order that we may transmit what we found valuable in them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Theoretical Dispute: electron, dharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 23:12:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our daily life, we hardly pause to reflect upon many problematic things that we routinely assume as self-evident. Such an attitude is useful since it allows us to focus on other things that occupy us at that moment. One such attitude is not to bestow too much care on how we use language: we routinely speak of similarity in meaning, identical concepts, exact and accurate translations and so on. As long as issues like meaning etc. are not at dispute, talking like this causes no harm. However, in the current case, we are talking about the meaning of &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; (in a manner of speaking). Consequently, we have to be careful about how we use language to convey what we want to say, and be clear about what thesis we intend to argue for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apaurusheya, shruti and revelation: theoretical dispute</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/apaurusheya-shruti-and-revelation-theoretical-dispute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:10:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/apaurusheya-shruti-and-revelation-theoretical-dispute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The problem about translating &amp;lsquo;sruti&amp;rsquo; is not as easy as it has been made out to be. Is it possible to translate it as &amp;lsquo;revelation&amp;rsquo; or even as &amp;lsquo;divine revelation&amp;rsquo;? Because it has so far been translated in this manner, we can only conclude that it is indeed possible to do so. Next issue: how accurate is this translation? The answer to this question depends upon what &amp;lsquo;revelation&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;divine revelation&amp;rsquo; is supposed to mean.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Sanskrit Concepts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 05:13:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many are concerned that English translations of some words from native languages distort their meaning. If we restrict ourselves to terms like &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Dharma&amp;rsquo; and such like, the worry is not just that their translations distort the meaning of these words (as we use them in our native languages) but that they suggest something (by way of reference and meaning) that does not even exist in these languages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With respect to some of these words, we can build a reasonable case in defense of this stance. That is because there is at least some theory about religion that we accept (however provisional or conditional such an acceptance might be) using which we can show that &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo; cannot be translated as &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo;. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Brahmins ‘priests’?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 04:01:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not have a theory of meaning. I do not know which of the many fragmentary theories of meaning I should choose from and why. Even though I acknowledge the importance of the topic, I do not feel called upon to do research on it. So far, I have been able to steer clear of the topic in &lt;em&gt;an interesting way&lt;/em&gt;: I am able to show that what appears as translation problem or a meaning problem (how should Sanskrit words be translated or the definition of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, etc) is, at least in some instances, actually not that kind of a problem at all. Such an attitude has generated a psychological bonus for me: I do not go around criticizing Jeffrey Kripal for not knowing Bengali well enough, or for Wendy Doniger for not realizing that Dharma is not religion or that Brahmins are not priests, when my knowledge of either Bengali or Sanskrit does not match up to what they know.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indians’ Barren criticisms of Western translations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 22:53:16 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: &amp;ldquo;Wendy Doniger translates all the Sanskrit words into English and thereby ends up distorting their meaning. Dharma becomes religion, Varna becomes color, and apparently she ends up even translating the names of some tribes into English.&amp;rdquo; Assuming that this is the case (assumption is on my part because I have neither read her translation nor do I intend reading it), what is the problem? Out of the conversation, the following considerations came to the fore: (a) if she had retained some of these Sanskrit words, the Indian scholars could have made more sense of the translation; (b) Dharma and religion are not co-extensive in meaning, any more than Varna is with color; (c) consequently, there is a great distortion in translation. Underlying this discussion was a (fragmentarily explicit) view about translation that if we do not find &amp;lsquo;accurate&amp;rsquo; translations of words form one language into another, we should retain the original words, assign them the status of `technical&amp;rsquo; terms, and not translate them any further.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the Bhagavad Gita a revelation?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:22:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is the Bhagavad Gita revelation? E.g. 15:15, rendered by one translator as &amp;ldquo;And I am seated in the hearts of all; from Me are memory, knowledge, as well as their loss; I am verily that which has to be known by all the Vedas; I am indeed the author of the Vedanta as well as the knower of the Vedas&amp;rdquo;.If nothing else, the authorship of Vedanta is what is revealed here. But the claim is there both to be the subject and author of revelation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is ‘sat’ ‘being’? S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-sat-being-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 03:58:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-sat-being-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To take German language, let us look at how Heidegger talks about &amp;lsquo;being&amp;rsquo;: there is the &amp;lsquo;big Being&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;Sein&amp;rsquo;) and there is the &amp;lsquo;small being&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;Dasein&amp;rsquo; meaning &amp;rsquo;there-being&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;so-being&amp;rsquo;). And then there is &amp;lsquo;Sein&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Seindes&amp;rsquo;. All these are translated by the word &amp;lsquo;being&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To jump back a couple of hundred years, and pick up another philosopher with the same alphabet and the same language, we have G.W.F. Hegel. His &amp;lsquo;Sein&amp;rsquo; of course has nothing to do with the &amp;lsquo;Sein&amp;rsquo; of Heidegger, even though both are translated as &amp;lsquo;Being&amp;rsquo; with a big B. So, even in one language, there are problems with respect to translating words into another language.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Puja and Worship</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:59:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: if &amp;ldquo;pujya&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;worthy of worship&amp;rdquo;, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;puja&amp;rdquo; mean worship?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Pujya&amp;rsquo; means &amp;ldquo;deserving of &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. If &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo; translated as &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;, quite obviously one translates &amp;lsquo;pujya&amp;rsquo; as you do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You see, what is at stake is not a mere &amp;rsquo;translation&amp;rsquo; problem.  It has to do with how the Indian culture (and not merely this one culture, I might add) has been, and continues to be, represented not just by Western intellectuals but also by the Indian intellectuals themselves. Let me give you an example, which should give you a sense of the nature of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why ‘Westology’ ala Indology doomed to fail?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-westology-ala-indology-doomed-to-fail-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 07:51:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-westology-ala-indology-doomed-to-fail-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The inherent logic of such an enterprise forces one, as it were, to build &lt;em&gt;alternate&lt;/em&gt; theories to the existing, &amp;lsquo;western&amp;rsquo; theories. Instead of explaining this statement in the abstract, let me take a concrete example to illustrate what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.2. In the University of Chicago, there is a certain Richard Shweder. He practices &amp;lsquo;Cultural Psychology&amp;rsquo;, and is (was?) professor of &amp;lsquo;Human Development&amp;rsquo;. He is rather well-known for his &amp;lsquo;cross-cultural&amp;rsquo; studies: he and his students have published many works comparing psychological developments across the two cultures that India and America are. (In fact, he received a medal from the American Association of the Advancement of Science, if I remember properly, for one of his articles: &amp;lsquo;Does the concept of the Person vary cross-culturally?&amp;rsquo; This was a study about the concept of &amp;lsquo;self&amp;rsquo; in the USA and Orissa, India.) A few years ago, he published a study on the nature of &lt;em&gt;moral development&lt;/em&gt; and the growth of moral awareness cross-culturally: again, India and the USA were the two compared cultures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
