<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Will Sweetman on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/will-sweetman/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Will Sweetman on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:26:41 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/will-sweetman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Indian Secularists do not think but talk?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:26:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to go deeper into the claim of &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-%e2%80%93s-n-balagangadhara/&#34; title=&#34;Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara&#34;&gt;my earlier post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; that Shabnum Tejanis and Neera Chandhokes of this world do not think but merely talk. In other words, is it possible to identify the problems with their accounts (that explicates more clearly why I say that they do not think) in such a way that it is susceptible to some sort of solution? If, indeed, we can show that such people do not think and we can show that their mistakes have some cognitive roots, then we can also provide additional explanations. In such a case, our answer would be richer and more complex than any other available at the market place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Will Sweetman’s Criticism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-will-sweetmans-criticism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 07:18:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-will-sweetmans-criticism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me just focus on one important and one not-so-important claim from Will Sweetman&amp;rsquo;s article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hinduism&amp;rdquo; and the history of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;: Protestant presuppositions in the critique of the concept of Hinduism.&lt;/em&gt; He suggests that I argue the following.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First premise: Christianity is prototypically what religion is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Second premise: Hinduism does not share all (or perhaps any) of the relevant properties of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: Hinduism is not a religion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem, here, turns around the notion of &amp;lsquo;prototypicality&amp;rsquo;. I explain at length (a) the source of the word; and (b) its meaning. For the role these clarifications play in Sweetman&amp;rsquo;s analysis, I might as well not have written those passages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
