<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Explication on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/explication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Explication on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:36:30 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/explication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Interpretations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:36:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are multiple kinds of interpretation. For instance, there is interpretation of symbols in a domain like Physics: μ (in elementary optics) is &amp;ldquo;interpreted&amp;rdquo; as the refraction index of a substance. We use a more or less analogous notion of &amp;ldquo;interpretation&amp;rdquo; in Chemistry, Mathematics and so on. In logic, we speak of &amp;ldquo;interpretation of variables&amp;rdquo; like &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;, etc. Here, it means that the letters stand-in for arbitrary sentences with truth-values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is critique?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-critique/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 12:35:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-critique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a very interesting notion of &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo;: it begins with Kant and stretches through Marx in the German philosophical tradition. In fact, it is most developed in Marx when he says he develops a &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo; of political economy, a &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo;, which, he says, is nonetheless a &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo;. He does not develop a &amp;ldquo;scientific critique&amp;rdquo; of political economy: he develops a critique of the science of political economy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Westology and its nonsense</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/westology-and-its-nonsense/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:25:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/westology-and-its-nonsense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the logic of &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/&#34;&gt;my argument&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;? Am I proposing a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo;? Let me briefly explicate my stances, beginning with the last question.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If we are not to simply sell slogans and our claims should carry bite, we need to say what this &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; is or could be. My stance: such a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; cannot even be properly conceptualized, let alone carried out.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. What does it mean (however intuitively plausible it might appear at first sight) to build a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; that is, say, an Indian counterpart to &amp;lsquo;indology&amp;rsquo;? Are we to assume that we need to build &lt;em&gt;Indian&lt;/em&gt; theories of &amp;lsquo;democracy&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;state&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;market&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;firm&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;society&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; and such like? If the answer is &amp;rsquo;no&amp;rsquo;, then the notion of &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; does not make sense. Therefore, the answer has to be &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is rubbish about the ‘self’ and what not?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-rubbish-about-the-self-and-what-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 08:49:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-rubbish-about-the-self-and-what-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few points about &amp;lsquo;self&amp;rsquo; and about what I have said and have not.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Comment: &amp;ldquo;Say, Mr. X made 1 run, 2 runs, 3, 4, n, and a total of 50 runs. Now to say &amp;ldquo;I made 50 runs&amp;rdquo; is to assume that, Mr. X who made 1 run, 2 run, etc. is linked to each other, and this organism , in this sense, has a unity. This unity is what Balu calls rubbish&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, I do not call this &amp;lsquo;unity&amp;rsquo; rubbish. Second, this is a problem not pertaining to &amp;rsquo;the self&amp;rsquo; but one applicable to any object or entity that persists over time. Because we can speak about the spatial and temporal career of an object (whether it involves disassembling and then reassembling a watch or whether it is about a merger of two corporations or firms or about our bodies or whatever), the logical problem of identity crops up: what makes some object, any object, the same object at different spatial and temporal intervals? I.e. how can the organism (currently called &amp;lsquo;Balu&amp;rsquo;, say) be the same organism when, as it spatially and temporally moves in the world, it accrues different properties? After all, &amp;lsquo;Balu&amp;rsquo; at some spatio-temporal point (say when the organism is 5 years old) has properties different from &amp;lsquo;Balu&amp;rsquo; at some other spatio-temporal interval. Because these two spatio-temporal units do not have identical properties, they have to be different objects. Yet, we say &amp;lsquo;here is Balu&amp;rsquo;s photo when he was 5 years old&amp;rsquo;. The problem of logical identity crops up in such contexts. As I say, this is a problem that confronts any theory of identity (as a logical relationship). Philosophy of logic has provided a few solutions to this question even if they all face problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Theoretical Dispute: electron, dharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 23:12:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our daily life, we hardly pause to reflect upon many problematic things that we routinely assume as self-evident. Such an attitude is useful since it allows us to focus on other things that occupy us at that moment. One such attitude is not to bestow too much care on how we use language: we routinely speak of similarity in meaning, identical concepts, exact and accurate translations and so on. As long as issues like meaning etc. are not at dispute, talking like this causes no harm. However, in the current case, we are talking about the meaning of &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; (in a manner of speaking). Consequently, we have to be careful about how we use language to convey what we want to say, and be clear about what thesis we intend to argue for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Anubhava? III</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-anubhava-iv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 01:40:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-anubhava-iv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us retain the translation of &amp;lsquo;Anu&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;appropriate&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;apt&amp;rsquo;. Let us emphasize the active dimension of the word &amp;lsquo;Bhava&amp;rsquo; to translate it as &amp;lsquo;coming into existence&amp;rsquo;. (&amp;lsquo;Existence&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;being&amp;rsquo; are also acceptable translations of the word &amp;lsquo;Bhava&amp;rsquo;.) Then &amp;lsquo;Anubhava&amp;rsquo; would mean an apt way of coming-into-existence. The problem here is this: we can ask the question, &lt;em&gt;coming into existence of what?&lt;/em&gt; Of course, we can answer it easily by using hyphenation: it is not the coming-into-existence of any &amp;rsquo;thing&amp;rsquo; but coming-into &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo;. However, this might create more confusion than it solves. So, let us make a compromise here for the sake of clarity: coming-into-existence-of-being. We can also shorten it as coming-into-being, where we understand &amp;lsquo;being&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;origin&amp;rsquo;. We come into existence, we originate. In this sense, &amp;lsquo;Anubhava&amp;rsquo; talks about &amp;ldquo;an appropriate originating&amp;rdquo;. (This is all heavy-duty philosophy stuff, this is what &amp;lsquo;ontology&amp;rsquo; is, the &amp;lsquo;doctrine of being&amp;rsquo;.) As long as we keep these ideas in mind, we can say that &amp;lsquo;bhava&amp;rsquo; can be translated also as &amp;lsquo;being-there-in the world&amp;rsquo;, or as &amp;lsquo;being present in the world&amp;rsquo;. Thus, &amp;lsquo;anubhava&amp;rsquo;, or experience, is &amp;lsquo;being appropriately present in the world&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;being aptly present in the world&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of Essentialism?—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-essentialism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 03:40:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-essentialism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have had difficulties in understanding the use and meaning of some words, especially &amp;rsquo;essentialism&amp;rsquo; and its cognates. Here are some uses of &amp;ldquo;essentialism&amp;rdquo; I am familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; to designate some basic or fundamental or determining properties of an object, as in: &amp;ldquo;Water is essentially H2O&amp;rdquo;. Here the claim is that some liquid is water if and only if it has the chemical structure of containing two molecules of Hydrogen and one molecule of Oxygen for every single molecule of the liquid in question.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; in order to understand counterfactual sentences involving proper nouns, as in: &amp;ldquo;If I were George Bush, I would not have gone to war with Iraq&amp;rdquo;. This sentence is a counterfactual because it begins by assuming a non-fact (I am Balu and not George Bush); picks out a state of affairs where this is true (a possible world where &amp;lsquo;Balu&amp;rsquo; IS &amp;lsquo;George Bush&amp;rsquo;) and makes a (true or false) statement about this (I might or might not have gone to war with Iraq). Many historical claims (and many scientific laws) have the form of counterfactual statements. Here &amp;rsquo;essence&amp;rsquo; is predicated to Balu (something like &amp;ldquo;baluhood&amp;rdquo;) so that Balu remains Balu even if he were to become &amp;lsquo;George Bush&amp;rsquo; in some possible world.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; to solve the problem of providing references to proper names, as in &amp;ldquo;Socrates was not a teacher of Plato&amp;rdquo;. In many cases, we identify Socrates as that person who has the property of &amp;lsquo;being a teacher of Plato&amp;rsquo;. If it transpires that such is not the case, we will still not be in doubt about the identity of Socrates because, much like the previous case, it speaks about some &amp;rsquo;essential property&amp;rsquo; of Socrates by virtue of which he remains the same person even when he does not have some or another accidental or contingent property.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; while solving the puzzle of identity, as in &amp;ldquo;This is me, a photograph taken when I was three years old&amp;rdquo;. Here, &amp;lsquo;me, when I was three years old&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;me in America during the 1990 AAR conference&amp;rsquo; etc. become spatio-temporal slices of an &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;. The &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo; has indefinitely many spatio-temporal slices and these are all slices of one and the same &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;. The idea is that one does not become someone else other than who one is because of the spatio-temporal career of &amp;lsquo;oneself&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even though there are many discussions about each of these uses, there is nothing wrong or illegitimate about using the word &amp;rsquo;essence&amp;rsquo; or indeed to &amp;ldquo;talk in an essentializing way&amp;rdquo;. Quite obviously, the &amp;lsquo;subaltern&amp;rsquo; historiographers could not mean &amp;rsquo;essentialism&amp;rsquo; in any of the above senses, because they suggest that essentialism is something to avoid. I know of one such use of the word in Said&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Orientalism&amp;rdquo;, where he suggests that to correlate climatic conditions with the psychology or culture of a people (something that often happened in the eighteenth nineteenth centuries) is to commit the sin of essentialism. Clearly, this is not the kind of essentialism that is at issue here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
