<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Puja on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/puja/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Puja on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 13:52:54 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/puja/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Random Substitution: Worship and Puja</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 13:52:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Firstly, you want to know whether there is anything intrinsically  wrong with performing idol worship the way it is with robbery.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us assume that we agree we know what robbery is and that it is intrinsically wrong. We need to make these assumptions because (a) in all probability, the robbers do not see anything intrinsically wrong in the act of robbing; (b) even then, some of us might not be willing to call a &amp;lsquo;Robin hood&amp;rsquo; (who robs only the rich and passes on the spoils to the poor, retaining a modest &amp;lsquo;commission&amp;rsquo; for himself and fellow robbers) an immoral person; (c) to most of us, it is unclear whether the windfall profits that oil corporations have made in the last years constitute robbery or not and so on. Under these assumptions, you are drawing an analogy between idol worship and an act that a human being performs with respect to fellow-human beings. This analogy breaks down because idol worship is not a relation between human beings but between a particular act of a human being (called &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;) and the entity worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why study the Western culture?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two substantial questions have been raised in response to &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/&#34;&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;: (a) why do we need to study and understand the Western culture in order to access our own traditions? (b) Is it my claim that Buddha and Shankara (for example) are irrelevant to us? One other sort of &amp;lsquo;objection&amp;rsquo; too has surfaced, albeit disguised as a characterization of what I have said: (c) is not my position itself illustrative of &amp;lsquo;Eurocentrism&amp;rsquo;? These issues are intertwined.  Hopefully, addressing them together will lend some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ad hoc explanations: why do puja to cows?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2011 03:03:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we provide explanations, we should also look at their contrastive nature: why do puja to cows and not to buffalos? The problem in this case, however, is this: the explanation one gives about a tradition (you will soon see that one of the problems is to identify the explanandum itself) must also incorporate this contrast. Someone like Kanch Ilaiah has answered this question thus: the puja to cows and not to the buffalos expresses racism (that is at the origin of the caste system) because cows are white and buffaloes are always dark. In other words, you cannot simply ask for a contrastive explanation without incorporating it in a &amp;lsquo;bigger&amp;rsquo; explanation that explains the explanandum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linga, Puja, Symbolism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/linga-puja-symbolism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 20:24:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/linga-puja-symbolism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symbolic interpretation of lingam from a netizen&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;In ancient India, there was a fertility cult; our ancestors &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that it was a fertility cult; Lingam was a symbol for the phallus then; it continues to be one even when many millions are ignorant of this now; and that the Modern Indians&amp;rsquo; attitude to sex is inhibiting because of which they do not see the symbolism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To keep the contrast between us stark, here is what I say: Lingam is not a symbol of anything or anybody. Lingam is &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; Shiva&amp;rsquo;s puja is done (as against, say, how we do puja to Vishnu) by the Indians. You tell me that this &lt;em&gt;factual claim&lt;/em&gt; is wrong and that by saying what I have just said, I project my present to &amp;rsquo;explain&amp;rsquo; the past. Very well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Puja and Worship</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:59:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: if &amp;ldquo;pujya&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;worthy of worship&amp;rdquo;, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;puja&amp;rdquo; mean worship?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Pujya&amp;rsquo; means &amp;ldquo;deserving of &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. If &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo; translated as &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;, quite obviously one translates &amp;lsquo;pujya&amp;rsquo; as you do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You see, what is at stake is not a mere &amp;rsquo;translation&amp;rsquo; problem.  It has to do with how the Indian culture (and not merely this one culture, I might add) has been, and continues to be, represented not just by Western intellectuals but also by the Indian intellectuals themselves. Let me give you an example, which should give you a sense of the nature of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>God, Devil (Satan), and Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/god-devilsatan-and-polytheism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:47:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/god-devilsatan-and-polytheism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is true that the modern Jewish thought, which is more influenced by the Rabbinic than by apocalyptic or Qumranic literature, places less emphasis on the Devil. Rabbinic Judaism was less interested in building a demonology than others. It is one thing to say this, but quite another to say that the Judaic tradition knows of the Devil only in terms of the psychological &amp;lsquo;inclinations&amp;rsquo; in man. (It is equivalent to suggesting that there is no demonology in Judaic thought, a preposterous suggestion on any count.) Belial, Mastema, Azazel, Satanail, Sammael, Semyzza, or Satan do not name either psychological or spiritual &amp;lsquo;inclinations&amp;rsquo;, surely. (Think further of what Behemoth, Leviathan, etc. are). The Satan in the Book of Job is already an emissary of God (though not yet the personification of evil), and not a mere &amp;lsquo;inclination&amp;rsquo;. The Testaments of the Twelve Patriarchs name Belial or Satan as Chief of evil angels commanding the spirits of wrath, hatred, etc. and as lord of war, fornication, bloodshed, destruction, etc. He tempts and seduces humankind to error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Muslims ‘Mohammedans’?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/are-muslims-mohammeddans/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:14:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/are-muslims-mohammeddans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by Mujeeb&amp;rsquo;s objection to calling the Islamic people &amp;lsquo;Mohammedans&amp;rsquo;. Mujib&amp;rsquo;s objection was that the Muslims do not worship Mohammed, and Naseem spoke of it as an insulting appellation. They are right, of course, but they did not appear to get the authentic problem posed by a Raghavan and a Seshadri: surely &amp;lsquo;Mohammedans&amp;rsquo; are those who follow the doctrines (or teachings) of Mohammed. Marxists, Buddhists, and even Christians were called in to bolster the applicability of such a language-use. Despite the acrimonious sphere among the participants, there is a very, very deep reason why neither understands the other&amp;rsquo;s question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple meanings: puja, thondam—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/multiple-meanings-puja-thondam-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 23:09:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/multiple-meanings-puja-thondam-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the multiple meanings for the Puja of Ganesha. Of course, there is no one &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; to this act either now, or before, or in the future, as far as Indians (and the Westerners) are concerned. But that is not being disputed. The dispute arises when some meaning is alleged to portray the &amp;rsquo;experience&amp;rsquo; of a culture, when all it does is distort and deny the experience it is said to portray. However, there is an interesting question here, which is best illustrated using a contrast. In the Catholic Mass, there are &lt;em&gt;limits&lt;/em&gt; on what it could be said to mean to a believer. These limits are set by the Catholic theology and belief. (For instance, to a believer, it &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; mean celebrating the Devil.) The puja of Ganesha does not set any such limits to the person who does this puja. (But if someone comes and tells me that I cook sweets on Ganesha Chaturthi because it expresses my &amp;lsquo;subconscious&amp;rsquo; desire for Oral Sex, I am justified in challenging this claim as an &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of my cooking the sweets.) Here is the question: what is puja in the Indian traditions, if it does not have a particular meaning, and there are no limits on what it means? One thing is already clear: it cannot mean &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;! These are the kind of questions I would like to ask; not what &amp;lsquo;interpretation&amp;rsquo; one gives to some action or the other. The answer I give should be capable of being &amp;rsquo;tested&amp;rsquo; in the Indian culture. Then, I will have begun producing an &amp;lsquo;objective&amp;rsquo; theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Insider/Outsider game is sterile?—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-insideroutsider-game-is-sterile-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 00:20:56 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-insideroutsider-game-is-sterile-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first point is the difficulty involved in specifying what the &amp;ldquo;real meaning of an experience&amp;rdquo; consists of. Asking an insider would not help us here: the insider may or may not know what the real meaning of his/her own experience is or even how to go about putting it in words.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the first problem somehow gets solved, the second problem lies in the &lt;em&gt;multiplicities&lt;/em&gt; of such meanings: if people differ on what any particular experience means to them (for instance, what doing Puja to Ganesha means to my brother does not mean the same to my sister), which should we choose and for what reason? This problem is virtually unsolvable, especially when you take the interpretations of the past into consideration as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denying Experience: Do Hindus ‘worship’? Do they do Pooja to phallus (linga)?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 20:46:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone, let&amp;rsquo;s say her name is Wendy Doniger, comes along and sniggers &amp;lsquo;when you worship the lingam, you worship a phallus&amp;rsquo;. I do not identify Wendy&amp;rsquo;s statement as an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation. I say that it trivializes what I am doing by providing a distorted description of what I do. Here is what I say: &amp;ldquo;I am doing Puja to Shiva.&amp;rdquo; No discussion about &amp;lsquo;Lingam&amp;rsquo; or its many meanings. This is a &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; way of conducting a discussion. She cannot, therefore, argue that I am giving an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation because I am not giving an &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of what I am doing but merely describing it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Shivalinga ‘mean’ phallus? A theoretical dispute</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 18:58:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: &amp;ldquo;In the context of puja, does Shivalinga denote or connote anything other than Shiva, in particular &amp;ldquo;phallus&amp;rdquo;? A Wendy says &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;, a Balu says &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;. For some person, not on this board, there is not a dialog; it is a reading of Wendy, a reading of Balu - how to decide between the two answers, which one represents the truth about Hindus?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Depending on the patience of the visitor, a number of answers are possible including an identification of the nature of the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
