<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tolerance on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/tolerance/</link><description>Recent content in Tolerance on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/tolerance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Proselytizing drive of the Eastern Christianity in India</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, there are two questions that need to be distinguished from each other. There is, firstly, the question about the nature of &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity. If it is muted in its proselytizing drive in all cultures the &lt;em&gt;same way&lt;/em&gt; and if it is &amp;rsquo;tolerant&amp;rsquo; in &lt;em&gt;exactly the same way&lt;/em&gt; in all cultures, it makes sense to ask the question whether (a) different factors in all these cultures have brought about the same effect (different &amp;lsquo;causes&amp;rsquo; can generate one and the same effect in differing circumstances) or (b) it is due to the nature of the &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity itself. Nobody is able to make such a claim today. We do not possess the theoretical apparatus which would allow us to make sense of the remarks I have made in italics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Proselytization vs. Persecution</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytization-vs-persecution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:03:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytization-vs-persecution/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us would not know the difference between the Syrian Orthodox, the Greek Orthodox and the Russian Orthodox Churches; many will be hard put to differentiate between the Pope and the Patriarch. In these circumstances, it is foolish to write &lt;em&gt;apologetica&lt;/em&gt; for &amp;lsquo;Eastern Christianity&amp;rsquo; and criticise &amp;lsquo;Western Christianity&amp;rsquo;. Let those concerned with the nature of Christian theologies do that. But that does not concern us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rajiv, regarding your #82 (from Sulekha board). The Emperor Constantine &lt;strong&gt;did not&lt;/strong&gt; start a trend. &lt;em&gt;UrChristenthum&lt;/em&gt; was as viciously proselytizing as the most rabid Protestant of today. Before one addresses oneself to the role that &amp;lsquo;power&amp;rsquo; played in the proselytizing drive of Christianity, one needs to know what &lt;em&gt;proselytization&lt;/em&gt; means. Consider the role that the Emperors played in Rome (and the role played by some Kings in India.) They would promote some or another tradition (or &amp;lsquo;cult&amp;rsquo;, as they were called in the Roman Empire), &lt;em&gt;persecute the followers&lt;/em&gt; of some or another tradition (or cult). &lt;strong&gt;Does that mean that the cults proselytized too, or that they were as &amp;lsquo;intolerant&amp;rsquo; as the Semitic religions?&lt;/strong&gt; To affirm either of the two is to lose any ability to understand the difference between Indian traditions (or the Roman cults) and the Semitic religions. &lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The loss of the vibrancy of Indian Traditions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-loss-of-the-vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 12:51:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-loss-of-the-vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I would like to address a very basic issue that many of us have confronted. In its simplest form, the question is this: What should we, a small slice of the Indian intelligentsia, be doing? We can vent our anger and frustration at the way the Indian politicians are handling (or mishandling) the Kashmiri situation; we can express hurt and outrage that &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; are singled out for special treatment both by the &amp;rsquo;liberals&amp;rsquo; and by a section of the Muslim population; we can propose a trifurcation of Kashmir; or that the Muslims be &amp;rsquo;taught&amp;rsquo; a lesson (whatever that lesson consists of); indulge in abuse and name-calling; or whatever else that takes our fancy at any particular moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Theology of Tolerance</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/theology-of-tolerance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 21:39:14 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/theology-of-tolerance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;According to Judaism, Christianity and Islam, &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; is devil&amp;rsquo;s worship. Instead of quoting from their scriptures, let me give the barest of the bare outlines of their fundamental story about &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. No&lt;em&gt;believer&lt;/em&gt;from any of these religions (their religious authorities included) could ever disagree with this outline. There are two &amp;lsquo;Gods&amp;rsquo;: the true God and the false God (notice the capitalization). The first created the world and everything in it; the second, who is his creature too, is the &amp;lsquo;fallen&amp;rsquo; one. (Why he fell, what his &amp;lsquo;sin&amp;rsquo; was, etc. are glossed differently by these three religions.) The devil has &lt;em&gt;many names&lt;/em&gt; (Baal, Beelzebub, Satan, Lucifer, Mephistopheles, &amp;hellip;) and his followers are &amp;ldquo;legion&amp;rdquo;. This devil is the lord of the earth, the prince of darkness, the father of lies, the king of deceit, etc. the devil is the &amp;lsquo;false god&amp;rsquo;, i.e., he constantly seduces mankind into worshipping him as though he was God himself. To worship the devil is to go to hell for eternity; the road to salvation (please, do not confuse this with mukthi or moksha) lies in worshipping the true God. However, how to know who is the true God so that one may worship him? What does it mean to &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo; him? (After all, so their story goes, the false God also parades as &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; and deceives the humankind.) Hence, God &lt;em&gt;reveals&lt;/em&gt; himself (again, please do not confuse this with avataaras.), and tells that he is the true God and how humankind &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to worship him. (&amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, as they see it, is the worship of God.) This &lt;em&gt;revelation&lt;/em&gt; is what their scriptures are about. According to these revelations, God has commanded not to &lt;em&gt;build his likeness&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. create idols); to worship the idols is to worship the devil. This true God is one; the false &amp;lsquo;gods&amp;rsquo; are many (the devil&amp;rsquo;s &amp;rsquo;legion&amp;rsquo;); he has one name (Yahweh written without the consonants in Hebrew; the Holy Trinity in Christianity; the merciful Allah in Islam); the devil has &lt;em&gt;many names&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;Do not confuse names with the hundred and odd properties of God that Koran talks about.&lt;/em&gt; Now, these and more are God&amp;rsquo;s revelations in these three religions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Religious Intolerance and Believers</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/believers-vs-their-religion/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 21:15:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/believers-vs-their-religion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are two distinct problems: one involving religions (like Christianity, Judaism and Islam) and the other involving the believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding these three religions: (a) insofar as these religions (Judaism, Christianity and Islam) are concerned, Hinduism is demonic. It is that because, according to all the three religions, &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; worship the devil (&amp;lsquo;shaitan&amp;rsquo;) and his minions. That is to say, our Rama, Vishnu, Ganesha, Saraswathi, etc. are all lieutenants of the devil himself. The idols, according to their theology, are representations of the devil, and Pat Robertson is simply echoing this standard Christian (Judaic, and Islamic) doctrines. There is nothing &amp;rsquo;extremist&amp;rsquo; about this statement: it is, as I say, one of the basic claims of these three religions. Because we worship the devil, they are convinced, we will all go to hell (do not confuse this with our naraka) for eternity. Because they want to save souls, these religions want to convert others into &amp;lsquo;believers&amp;rsquo;. (By the way, the &amp;lsquo;jealous&amp;rsquo; God is God of the Jews - God of Israel - in one of the more known aspects from the Old Testament Bible. In the New Testament, God is supposed to be &amp;rsquo;loving&amp;rsquo;. If you want to irk a Jew just tell him that his God is jealous and punishing, whereas God of Christianity is loving.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Devil worship in 'Hinduism'</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/devil-worship-in-hinduism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 00:01:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/devil-worship-in-hinduism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Here goes: that &amp;lsquo;Hindu&amp;rsquo; religion is devil&amp;rsquo;s worship is central, crucial and vital to the religions that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are. &amp;lsquo;Why is that?&amp;rsquo;, you may ask. It is impossible to cover this question in the space of a post, and with the details the question demands. So, here is what can be done: (a) I will provide a very crude outline with respect to Christianity; (b) reread what &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/"&gt;I wrote about God and devil .&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Belief vs Faith</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 23:50:22 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(a) It appears to me that in these discussions, a very vital issue (if we want to talk about Judaism, Christianity and Islam, and their &amp;lsquo;problems&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;, etc) is not being recognized. and that is this: religious &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; are not accorded their place, and are talked about as though they are merely a subset of the class of &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(b) &amp;lsquo;Being a believer&amp;rsquo; (I will confine myself to Christianity for the sake of brevity) does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean assenting to the proposition that &amp;lsquo;God exists&amp;rsquo;. For, if this is what it would mean, then the Devil himself is the first believer: after all, he does accept it as true that God exists. (The Devil is not an atheist, mind you.) He knows that God exists: after all, he rebelled against him! As the new testament Bible puts it: &amp;ldquo;thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the devils also believe, and tremble.&amp;rdquo; (James 2: 26)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Wendy Incident: A View from Europe--SN Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-wendy-incident-a-view-from-europe-sn-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 07:00:40 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-wendy-incident-a-view-from-europe-sn-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/TheHeathenInHisBlindness/conversations/messages/6548"&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am from Bangalore, India, but work as a professor in Belgium, Europe. My name is not Batra but am known as ‘Balu’. I am not, nor have I ever been, a member of either the BJP (the nationalist party in India) or organizations collectively known as the ‘Sangh Parivar’. Even though I am born a ‘Hindu’, some of my ‘liberal’ associates are convinced that I am a ‘crypto-Christian’. So much about my credentials, which are required to make two points of some importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Secular State and Religious Conflict: Liberal Neutrality and the Indian Case of Pluralism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 08:27:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s Note: This article appeared in the Journal of Political Philosophy. Authored by SN Balagangadhara and Jakob De Roover. For an alternative research programme (paradigm)  for studying India, Indian culture and Indian culture, study Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Reconceptualizing Indian Studies&lt;/strong&gt;, published by OUP, India.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few places in the contemporary world where the problems of cultural pluralism are as acute as they are in India. The Indian case poses fundamental challenges to the political theory of toleration. By tackling the problem of religious conversion, our analysis shows that the dominant way of conceiving state neutrality becomes untenable in the Indian context. The Indian state, modelled after the liberal democracies in the West, is the harbinger of religious conflict in India because of its conception of toleration and state neutrality. More of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; in India will end up feeding what it fights: the so-called &amp;lsquo;Hindu fundamentalism&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Religious intolerance and terrorism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-and-terrorism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:22:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-and-terrorism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What is the relationship between religious intolerance and the acts committed in Mumbai?&amp;rdquo; This is an empirical question at many levels. If some or another religion is used to defend the attacks in Mumbai, then it depends very much on the kinds of justifications used; the kind of theology in question; the relationship between the belief-states of the perpetrators and their motives; the relationship between their acts and their religious beliefs; and so on. Religious intolerance might or might not lead to conversion, to persecution of those who have &amp;lsquo;other&amp;rsquo; beliefs, to playing the &amp;lsquo;priest&amp;rsquo; and so on. What cannot be said, anyway, is that religious intolerance necessarily leads to Mumbai attacks. However, religious intolerance always harbors such a possibility. Whether or not such a possibility also occurs in our world depends on many, many empirical circumstances I have no clear view of.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Religious tolerance and Ecumenism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-tolerance-and-ecumenism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 04:31:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-tolerance-and-ecumenism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One has faith in God and, therefore, trusts that His message is also The Truth. That is to say, one should not predicate the attitude of having `faith in&amp;rsquo; to the EI account directly. There is a very important additional reason for being clear about our terminologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the distinction between having no idea that the Cosmos is an EI entity and having an account that makes the Cosmos into such an entity. This distinction marks the difference between the heathen and the believer. In religious terminology, the difference can also be expressed as that which exists between the &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;non-converted&amp;rdquo;. This is one meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;conversion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Paradox of Tolerating Intolerance</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/paradox-of-tolerating-intolerance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 22:59:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/paradox-of-tolerating-intolerance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Social issues, inherently, are neither paradoxical any more than they are contradictory. It is the &lt;em&gt;formulation&lt;/em&gt; of these issues that gives birth to paradoxes, contradictions and such like. (For the simple reason that &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;contradiction&amp;rsquo;, etc. are properties of statements, not of objects and events.) If there is a &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo; of freedom, then it lies not in the situation where one tradition (or even a set of traditions) meets another: that is to say, it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the situation of Indian traditions meeting religions like Christianity and Islam that gives birth to the &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo;. Rather, it is by describing this meeting of the Indian traditions with religions like Christianity and Islam &lt;em&gt;as an issue involving freedom&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. conceptualizing this meeting in terms of freedom) that one generates the paradox. There exist &lt;em&gt;other descriptions&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; give birth to this &amp;lsquo;paradox of freedom&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The religion of secular state: deChristianized Christianity –S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-religion-of-secular-state-dechristianized-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:33:30 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-religion-of-secular-state-dechristianized-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the distinction I &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-vs-civic-intolerance/" title="Religious intolerance vs. civic intolerance I"&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; between &lt;em&gt;civic tolerance&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;religious tolerance&lt;/em&gt; is acceptable, let us proceed further to analyze the notion of civic tolerance more closely. (I am simply assuming that it is desirable and that, from now on, we are talking about religious matters.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is (logically) possible that there could be religious intolerance and yet the believers in such religions could have the virtue of civic tolerance. That is to say, even (a) if there is religious intolerance, believers in some religion or another could have a society where there is civic tolerance. As suggested earlier, (b) religious tolerance implies the presence of civic tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Inclusivism, exclusivism, and Ignorance of heathens</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/inclusivism-exclusivism-and-ignorance-of-heathens/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:22:45 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/inclusivism-exclusivism-and-ignorance-of-heathens/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Words like &amp;ldquo;inclusivism&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;exclusivism&amp;rdquo; etc. are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a part of my terminology. They are not only imprecise but also misleading. They have been used mostly as meta-descriptions of the stance that Christian theologies took with respect to other &lt;em&gt;religions&lt;/em&gt;. (To use these loaded notions, even when negatively qualified, to describe the Indian traditions is totally misleading and entirely wrong.) They are also useless to describe (in any accurate manner) the Christian religion because each of the above notions expresses a &lt;em&gt;specific solution&lt;/em&gt; to the Christological dilemma. My discussion of Christianity &lt;em&gt;as a religion&lt;/em&gt; is pitched at another level of abstraction than these notions permit.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is tolerant Christianity a contradiction in terms?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tolerant-christianity-a-contradiction-in-terms-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:19:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tolerant-christianity-a-contradiction-in-terms-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if one insists (wrongly in my view) that I am suggesting that Alex Alexander is not a Christian, there are two ways of looking at the &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; of my assertion: (a) it is about the &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; individual that Alex Alexander is; (b) it is about him in so far as he is an &lt;em&gt;instance&lt;/em&gt; of the tolerant Christianity that some Indian Churches are supposed to be. I am &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; discussing (a): I do not know this unique individual, his history, his feelings and such like. Let us look at what discussing (b) entails.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Religious intolerance vs. civic intolerance I</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-vs-civic-intolerance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 20:45:45 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-vs-civic-intolerance/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, in countries like England, Belgium, Germany, Italy and the United States, many religions (Judaism, Christianity, Islam) and many brands of some of these religions (Catholicism, Protestantism of various shades, Orthodox Churches, etc) coexist. In Belgium or Italy, for instance, the Catholic Christians do not &lt;em&gt;impose&lt;/em&gt; their faiths on those who are not Catholics, i.e., they do not go around &amp;ldquo;proselytizing&amp;rdquo; the non-Catholics in their countries; in The Netherlands and Germany, for instance, the Catholics and the Protestants do not go around assaulting each other the way they did during the period of Reformation. Even the Jehovah&amp;rsquo;s Witnesses do not &lt;em&gt;impose&lt;/em&gt; their faith, when they canvass the &amp;ldquo;Good Word&amp;rdquo; from door to door. The Muslims in Britain, for instance, do not go around converting all non-Muslims either. Questions: Does that mean that Catholic Christianity in Belgium and Italy (for instance) has become &lt;em&gt;more tolerant&lt;/em&gt; than it was couple of centuries ago? Does it mean that Protestantism has become &lt;em&gt;more tolerant&lt;/em&gt; than it was some three centuries or so ago? Does it mean that Islam in Britain (or in the United States) is &lt;em&gt;more tolerant&lt;/em&gt; than Islam, say, in Africa?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or does it mean that these countries have become &lt;em&gt;more tolerant&lt;/em&gt; of the existence of several religions and religious denominations in the interstices of their society than they were a few centuries ago?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>