<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Secularization on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/secularization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Secularization on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 09:39:21 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/secularization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Peoples and Nations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/peoples-and-nations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 09:39:21 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/peoples-and-nations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Ancient Romans spoke of ‘Peoples’ and ‘Nations’. They saw traditions making a group into a people and distinguishing people (and, sometimes, ‘nations’) from each other. Different peoples (distinguished from each other on the basis of ancestral traditions) could live together in a nation and a nation itself could host multiple peoples and traditions. Consequently, they did not see Christians as a people because they did not have ancestral traditions to follow.&#xA;The Christians redefined what it is to be a people: they became a ‘communitas’ (a community) because of their ‘religio’. The Christians became a community because they were united “in God” and “in Christ”. They were united too in their “search for God”, which was what “conversio” (‘conversion’) meant to them. Christians were a ‘people’ now, a community that came into existence by their ‘unity in Christ’. The idea that individuals are “united” in “God and Christ” is what brings about a community and thus a people. This is a very Christian idea, which is based on the thought that individuals are united only in God. When secularized, it takes the shape of the idea that “a people” have a “common religion”. Or that every people is a people (or becomes one) because of religion.&#xA;It is this direction that one will have to go. I am working this idea out (every now and then) in my attempt to build a foundation for a theory of comparative politics, where I contrast these Christain ideas with the Indian ones.&#xA;II&#xA;One is the meaning of ‘nation-state’, which is also abbreviated in colloquial use as ‘nation’. This picks out individual countries with physical borders that have sovereign states internally: U.S., India, Saudi Arabia, Yemen, etc are such nation-states.&#xA;The second idea, which has a venerable history of more than 2000 years, is one which sees ‘nation’ as a ‘people’. In that sense the Jews are a ‘nation’ as are the Christians (as they saw themselves earlier and many, even now) and Muslims. Both the Muslims and the British saw a ‘Hindu’ nation in India as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Servitude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 14:41:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[ Published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://swarajyamag.com/politics/prime-ministers-panch-pran-and-decoloniality-indian-servility-may-have-roots-in-secularised-islam&#34;&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt; Aug 26, 2022]&#xA;Let me recollect the question we agreed upon: &lt;em&gt;how does the combined phrase (colonial mindset and servitude) make sense within the framework of my research programme?&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;My hypothesis on religion includes characterizing the dynamics of its expansion. As I see it, such a dynamic includes (a) conversion and (b) secularization. The first side of the dynamic, ‘conversion’, is well-known to most of us: here, some or another religion &lt;em&gt;inducts&lt;/em&gt; ‘non-believers’ into its fold or into its community of believers and practitioners. (I also called it ‘proselytization’, a term that notices how Judaism and Christianity use ‘proselyte’.) The second side of the dynamic, ‘secularization’, is known to us only very partially.&#xA;Made popular since the Enlightenment period in Europe, this partial description identifies an &lt;em&gt;antithetical movement&lt;/em&gt; where an individual religion begins to lose its earlier influence on its spheres of influence: the civil organizations and the civil authorities. This classical story is about the withdrawal of religion from various domains in society: politics, law, judiciary, and so on. In this ‘age of reason’, it is suggested that human reason begins to govern these institutions and provide their foundations instead of religious opinions and dogmas. One of its consequences is the loss of the power and control of the Church on the State. Called ‘secularism’, this process indicates the waning power of religion on people and their imaginations especially by freeing the civil, the social, and the psychological spheres of human beings and society. The freedom from those shackles that enslaved them over the millennia made human beings and their societies grow and expand. ‘Indian Secularism’ (both as a vacuous doctrine and in the threadbare ‘foundation’ it received in the Indian constitution) expresses this faith and this conviction in an extremely pathetic form ever since (or even decades before) the Indian independence 75 years ago.&#xA;My story, while giving credence to the hostility it expresses, locates the ‘secularization process’ as another side in the expansion of religion. Secularization is antithetical to the expansion of &lt;em&gt;some or another&lt;/em&gt; religion, but it expands religion itself as a phenomenon in a culture or society. As we know, each religion (I have the Semitic religions in mind here) is always &lt;em&gt;a specific religion:&lt;/em&gt; it emerged at some time, in a specific region, among a specific people, in a specific language, embodying specific doctrines, and specific practices. Thus, every religion (even where it aspires to be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; religion for the entire humankind) is always a specific religion. These very specificities that lend identity to some or another religion act as constraints on &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt;, which is, as I characterize it, the explanatory intelligible account of the Cosmos and itself. This account is &lt;em&gt;the truth&lt;/em&gt; about all that was, is and shall be. This truth is not only in the world but religion, as such an account, exhibits that truth. Thus, religion, &lt;em&gt;as religion&lt;/em&gt;, expands itself while this or that specific religion expands through conversion. Both, taken together, are moments in the expansion of religion.&#xA;Even though secularization of religion is a general process, how this process occurs is determined by the conditions of emergence of a specific religion and how that religion converts. That is, how religion secularizes itself is subject to the nature and constraints that the specific religions face. Thus, the secularization of Judaism, Christianity and Islam occur &lt;em&gt;differently&lt;/em&gt; even where each of them undergoes secularization as a moment in its expansion. In each of these religions, secularization is inimical and hostile to a particular religion because of the specificities that give us an individual religion.&#xA;In ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ I said that Indians were children of two colonialisms: one colonizer was Islam and the other was the British. This means that &lt;em&gt;religions too colonize&lt;/em&gt;. I did not expand on the idea in that book (you must wait for the upcoming works to grasp the idea more fully), but I will briefly outline only one element of this colonizing event. It is true that Islam tried to convert Indians and it is also true that it did so violently. While Islam launched many waves of destructive attacks on Indian traditions, their temples, and practices, etc., we were not colonized by this aspect or phase of Islamic expansion. (It is in the nature of religions, Christianity and Islam, to convert through extremely violent means when conversion is directed towards larger populations and established cultures. Judaism, after around 5th century C.E., almost stopped conversion. There are various reasons for this cessation, none of which is relevant for my story here.) &lt;em&gt;We were colonized by secularized Islam&lt;/em&gt;. That is, conversion into Islam did not colonize us; the secularized Islam did.&#xA;I have already noted that secularization is inimical and hostile to religion. What does it mean in our case? It means that the secularized Islam that colonized us was hostile to &lt;em&gt;Islam as a religion&lt;/em&gt;. Among other things, it means that it is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to Islamic doctrines as well. How? In very simple religious terms: &lt;em&gt;secularized Islam is blasphemy&lt;/em&gt; (within the framework of Islam as a religion). What does this mean?&#xA;According to Islam, Allah is the Lord and the Ruler of the Universe. As the word ‘Islam’ indicates, it demands an attitude of absolute submission and total surrender to Allah and His will. It requires a complete obedience to Him; human beings must follow His rules and Laws unconditionally. In its phase of conversion into a religion, Islam tried to inculcate this reverential attitude and habit towards Allah among the converted. In its secularizing moment, Secularized Islam reversed this thought and attitude entirely and gave it &lt;em&gt;a blasphemous form&lt;/em&gt;: among Indians, it inculcated and induced such a habit and attitude, &lt;em&gt;not towards Allah&lt;/em&gt;, but towards human rulers. &lt;em&gt;Secularized Islam put human Muslim rulers of India above the Prophet Mohammed and placed the same rulers as Allah’s equals&lt;/em&gt;. This is how secularized Islam expressed its antithetical attitude to Islam as a religion and expressed its hostility towards Islam.&#xA;I have claimed that colonialism transforms the experience of people and prevents the colonial subjects from accessing it in any form other than how the colonizer defines it. This inability to access our experience is what I call ‘colonial consciousness’. This is what secularized Islam also did: it introduced slavishness and servitude into Indian psychology. Centuries of this colonization made a &lt;em&gt;slavish submission to civil authorities&lt;/em&gt; the hallmark and an important trait of Indian cultural psychology. In very simple terms: &lt;em&gt;Indians became slavish, submissive, and servile to civil (i.e., human) authorities&lt;/em&gt;.&#xA;The British noticed this psychological trait of Indians and said that Indians were ‘effeminate’ and had ‘no backbone’. Though this is what all the Bengalis were in their eyes, after all, Bengal was one of first important ports of call to the British; very soon, all Indians joined the group of a servile people. That is why they went in search of ‘military’ castes in their attempts to recruit Indians to the British army. They found such ‘castes’ among the Sikhs and the Marathas (both of whom fought the Muslim rulers over long periods) and the Gurkhas (who were least subject to secularized Islamic rule). They found it among some ‘sub-castes’ as well: the Coorgis in Karnataka belonged to the ‘martial type’. The rest of India was too effeminate to be of much use except to slavishly obey the British authorities and lick their boots. How Indian child-rearing practices and the socialization processes in India succumbed to cultivating servility in Indian children because of Islamic colonization has not been understood yet. But that is not relevant to this story now.&#xA;When British ‘gave’ India her independence, the Indian servility did not disappear. It continues to be produced and reproduced even today. If we look at how Indians relate to &lt;em&gt;civil authorities&lt;/em&gt;, we see this servitude everywhere. The bureaucracy, the police, the ministers receive obsequiousness without demanding it. They punish those who dare ‘defy’ them. This is not merely how ordinary Indians relate to political and administrative authorities: this is institutionalized within these organizations too. How a peon responds to the boss; how a junior secretary bows down to the Deputy secretary; how the Chief secretary deals with Principal secretaries; how the chief minister treats the principal and the chief secretaries, how the circle inspector treats the local constable and is treated in turn by the assistant commissioner of police… This servitude, often called sycophancy, goes all the way to the very top.&#xA;This is how Indians are seen abroad: whether by the Chinese or in the West. Obsequious, eager to please and servile. This cultural psychology expresses our colonial consciousness as induced by Islamic colonization. Very recently, a few weeks ago, I read somewhere that Rahul Gandhi fulminated against the Indian foreign service officials thus: Indian diplomats are seen to have become &lt;em&gt;arrogant&lt;/em&gt; by others elsewhere in the world (due to Modi’s government). This perception makes sense: Indian diplomats are not any more as servile as they were in the last sixty years. They continue to have this psychology, but they do not express it as ‘the normal’ anymore.&#xA;There is much, much more to say than what I have. The story is bigger, broader, and richer than what I have penned so far. But I will round-off here. The phrase that combines ‘colonial mindset’ and ‘servitude’ makes sense within my research programme this way. It tells me how one colonialism has generated one aspect of our psychology. This attitude and orientation are in us and with us even now and will have their own poisonous and deleterious impacts on the development of the amritkaal that the PM spoke about. As I told you in an earlier mail, I have no clue what the PM intended or meant. This post is merely an attempt to see whether the combination makes sense within my research programme. It does. However, the implications are &lt;em&gt;gigantic&lt;/em&gt;: both for pursuing the pledge (the pran) and to fulfill it in the amritkaal that the PM seeks. They have their own pernicious effects on the current programmes of the government and all its future policies.&#xA;I must apologize for the brevity. You must wait for the upcoming works to understand this story properly. But I do hope this post will have done enough to keep the promise that I made in my earlier post.&#xA;Clarifications:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularization of Communitas</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularization-of-communitas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 01:47:24 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularization-of-communitas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Ancient Romans spoke of ‘Peoples’ and ‘Nations’. They saw traditions making a group into a people and distinguishing people (and, sometimes, ‘nations’) from each other. Different peoples (distinguished from each other on the basis of ancestral traditions) could live together in a nation and a nation itself could host multiple peoples and traditions. Consequently, they did not see Christians as a people because they did not have ancestral traditions to follow.&#xA;The Christians redefined what it is to be a people: they became a ‘communitas’ (a community) because of their ‘religio’. The Christians became a community because they were united “in God” and “in Christ”. They were united too in their “search for God”, which was what “conversio” (‘conversion’) meant to them. Christians were a ‘people’ now, a community that came into existence by their ‘unity in Christ’. The idea that individuals are “united” in “God and Christ” is what brings about a community and thus a people. This is a very Christian idea, which is based on the thought that individuals are united only in God. When secularized, it takes the shape of the idea that “a people” have a “common religion”. Or that every people is a people (or becomes one) because of religion.&#xA;I am working this idea out (every now and then) in my attempt to build a foundation for a theory of comparative politics, where I contrast these Christain ideas with the Indian ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is humility a virtue?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-humility-a-virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 21:37:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-humility-a-virtue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First: there is nothing morally wrong in posting an opinion. My problem is that (a) it occurs within the context of generating and criticising knowledge; (b) its cognitive value is either zero or negative; (c) it is presented as though thoughtless opinions (almost all opinions are thoughtless) form a counterpoint to knowledge or are themselves candidates for knowledge (the latter are the hypotheses); (d) one acts as though the fact that opinions could have some moral value (because a human being expresses them) is sufficient to make them cognitively worthy; (e) cognitive nonsense is provided with a foundation in Christian (and Semitic) religious value (like ‘IMHO’, ‘humility’ for example), which is itself placed beyond discussion as though its importance is universally recognized; (Neither the Ancient Pagans nor the Asian traditions consider ‘humility’ a moral virtue. It is immoral to these traditions because it is seen as dissimulation and deception.); and so on. There is place on this forum for dissent, disagreement and criticism, but their foundation is not moral but cognitive. I do not tolerate opinions on this board, but I am willing to think about any hypothesis that appears reasonable. I will respond to misunderstandings, queries and criticisms. However, those who find my reactions (to their ‘humble opinions’) offensive should leave this group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secular theme: cognitive stages of development -- concrete vs abstract</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secular-theme-cognitive-stages-of-development-concrete-vs-abstract/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2015 23:42:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secular-theme-cognitive-stages-of-development-concrete-vs-abstract/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The religious idea I am talking about in chapter 3 is this: Concrete and abstract characterize human thinking in the different phases of its development. By the time we reach chapter 7, and start thinking in terms of &amp;lsquo;secularization’, I will be talking about secularizing religious themes with respect to the same.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; Neither the words ‘concrete’ or ‘abstract’, nor the concepts associated with them are &amp;lsquo;religious’. (In this sense, concepts are neither &amp;lsquo;religious’ nor &amp;lsquo;scientific’.) The same applies to the use of words ‘concrete thought’ and &amp;lsquo;abstract thought’ (or to their meaning). But what is religious is the above idea, which speaks of different stages of human cognitive growth in terms of &amp;lsquo;concrete’ and ‘abstract thought’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dawkin’s  Delusion or The God Delusion?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:10:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While re-reading certain passages from Richard Dawkins&amp;rsquo; The God Delusion (2006), I was so shocked by his combination of ignorance and arrogance. Forgive me for some Dawkins- bashing:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In a memorable passage, Dawkins discusses the problem of Trinitarianism in Christianity and extends it to other forms of &amp;ldquo;polytheism,&amp;rdquo; such as the cult of the Virgin Mary and the saints in Roman-Catholicism. &amp;ldquo;What impresses me about Catholic mythology,&amp;rdquo; he shares with the reader, &amp;ldquo;is partly its tasteless kitsch but mostly the airy nonchalance with which these people make up the details as they go along. It is just shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo; (Dawkins 2006: 35). As a reader, try to bracket away all presuppositions about religion and reread the sentences. If you succeed in doing so, the impact of Dawkins&amp;rsquo; claim dissolves. So what, if certain details of Roman-Catholicism are human inventions? What is the problem in aspects of religion being &amp;ldquo;shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo;? From a non-Christian, neutral point of view, it is unclear why Dawkins bothers to mention this. However, anyone with a basic understanding of the history of Christianity will note where his claim comes from: Dawkins himself reproduces a piece of theology in this sentence (apparently without knowing it). From its earliest beginnings, Christianity claimed that it was the original and pure revelation of God, first given to Adam. This original revelation had been corrupted by sinful idolaters, seduced by the Devil into the worship of the false god and his minions. This corruption, according to Christian theology, took the form of human additions to the pure divine revelation: rites and myths, fabricated by priests and prelates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the Protestant Reformation, Luther, Calvin and their followers began to accuse the Roman-Catholic Church of the same sin of idolatry. They cried that the pope and his priests had invented a plethora of dogmas and rituals and imposed these on the believer as though they were part of God&amp;rsquo;s revelation and necessary to salvation. In this sense, the worst accusation one could make against Roman- Catholicism was that it consisted of &amp;ldquo;shameless human inventions.&amp;rdquo; The Enlightenment philosophes extended such charges of idolatry to all of Christianity and to all &amp;ldquo;religions&amp;rdquo; of humanity. All of these, including the notion of God itself, were human fabrications, the atheists among them claimed. Ironically, Enlightenment atheism thus presupposed and built on the claims of Christian theology. Without the background belief that there is something intrinsically wrong in religion being a human invention—very much a Christian belief—the impact of such charges simply disappears into thin air.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theology and evolutionary explanations of religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:00:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People like Scott Atran and Sloan Wilson abuse evolutionary biology to produce ad hoc explanations of an explanandum whose truth they presuppose: the universality of religion. Their explanations are no better than those discussed by Balu in chapter 5 of &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness&#34;&gt;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Paraphrasing Balu, we may say that they consist of &amp;rsquo;two quarters of theology, a quarter of evolutionary biology and a quarter of illiterate ethnology&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary explanations of religion: an exercise in petitio principii</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 04:49:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is very disappointing to see how these evolutionary theorists of religion lack knowledge of religions other than garden variety Judeo-Christianity (where they seem to have at least some factual knowledge, as in Scott Atran&amp;rsquo;s case, they reproduce standard textbook stories about Hinduism that have been left behind a few decades back).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If they did a serious study, it would perhaps strike them that no one has ever given either theoretical or empirical proof for the claim that religion is a human universal. From the 13th century onwards, European travelers, missionaries, merchants and scholars simply assumed that there would be religion in all societies. With this assumption in the background, they looked for the &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;gods&amp;rsquo; of these societies. In the process, these western minds invented religions everywhere. Later scholars began to create all kinds of definitions of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; in order to accommodate their (cultural) intuition that religion is universal. As though a definition of a word can help us decide on the universality of a phenomenon. After all, we don&amp;rsquo;t use a definition of the word &amp;ldquo;gravitation&amp;rdquo; in order to find out whether gravitation exists on all planets, do we?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theme: Hacker’s inclusivism and exclusivm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-hackers-inclusivism-and-exclusivm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 02:43:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-hackers-inclusivism-and-exclusivm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we consider  Paul Hacker&amp;rsquo;s story on &amp;lsquo;inclusivism as a typically Indian thought form&amp;rsquo;, all we can conclude is that he has used a &lt;em&gt;typically Christian  thought form&lt;/em&gt; to understand an aspect of the Indian cultural traditions, which he is unable to understand because it is completely different from what he knows. Hacker&amp;rsquo;s inclusivism is merely an attempt to strip the following Christian account from its recognizably Christian characteristics: &amp;ldquo;When God created man he inscribed him with a sense of divinity, and when it is &lt;em&gt;not corrupted&lt;/em&gt; this sense is the true religion. Throughout human history the devil and his minions corrupted this sense of divinity into false religion or worship of the devil among all human peoples. Until the good Lord brought mankind back to the true religion by revealing himself in Jesus Christ. Thus, Christianity is the one true religion. It is the message of self-disclosure in which God reveals his Will for the universe to the humankind. Of course, all other traditions contain traces of divine revelation, but these are nothing but the preparation of the Gospel. Once the true religion was revealed again, all non-Christian traditions could be nothing but pale and erring variants of Christianity.&amp;rdquo; Now Hacker has merely taken this Christian conceptual scheme to make sense of the attitude the Indian traditions take towards other traditions. Although it happens unconsciously most of the time, this is &lt;em&gt;the basic method of Indology&lt;/em&gt;: one looks at the Indian traditions, and the only way to make sense of them is to make them fit into a conceptual framework of secularized Christian theology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is  laukika-adhyatimika distinction same as secular-sacred distinction?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 22:21:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The theories (and discussions) about secularism constitute a test case for the claims advanced in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo; about the universalizing drive of religion. I have suggested that religion spreads by secularizing itself, and that the distinction between the secular and the religious is drawn by and within a religion. If this is the case, then it must be possible to show that the current theories of secularism are secularizations of a particular set of theological claims. (Theology draws these distinctions and defends them.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christian Attitudes and The Rule of Law as the Mechanism of Secularization </title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/law-secularization-and-religious-attitudes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 06:22:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/law-secularization-and-religious-attitudes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;So far, our answers have always taken this form: in the moment of secularization, the formal structures or cognitive schemes of Christianity are diffused accordingly as they lose their specific doctrinal content. In this formulation, it is as though the logical form of religion is able to spread itself by disposing of its semantic content. Thus, both the common sense of the West and the scholarly consensus of the academia accept the background assumptions of Christian doctrine, while they do not adopt its specific teachings. Balu has always been somewhat unhappy about this formulation. As he argues in &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness&#34;&gt;chapter 11 of `The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;, it is not a specific set of assumptions which spreads in society, but rather certain attitudes. The claims about the universality of religion, the meaning of life, the necessity of norms, the superiority of liberal democracy, etc. do not generally appear as explicit premises held by a group of people. Then, it seems the only explanation one can give is to ascribe them to these people as implicit assumptions. To some extent, this works: theories about the origin of religion, or the nature of morality, or human psychology all presuppose that certain assumptions are true. So if one intends to reveal the conceptual problems of these theories, it is fruitful to analyze these assumptions as the hidden premises of theorizing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, when it comes to explaining how the Christian religion spreads in a secular form, these accounts are unconvincing. What happens? Do the implicit assumptions or formalized theological schemes expand their scope as a kind of unit ideas by jumping from mind to mind? In what realm do these assumptions and background frameworks exist and procreate? The problem becomes acute when we turn to the spread of secularized Christianity in pagan societies like the Indian. Do the elite of alienated intellectuals suddenly adopt these assumptions as the starting points of reasoning about politics and society? Do they spread automatically from the colonized elite to other layers of Indian society, because this is a basic dynamic of societies? Such answers would be unsatisfactory. But what then is the mechanism through which secularized religious schemes spread and structure the experience of an ever increasing number of individuals? This and other related questions have been bothering me for some time (not least because I have failed to solve any of them in my doctoral thesis).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended reproduction of religion and revitalization of Indian traditions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:21:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Why did Christianity become a &amp;lsquo;universal&amp;rsquo; religion? How did Christians replace the &amp;lsquo;chosen&amp;rsquo; people? What was the logic behind the transformation of the Jewish god into God of the humankind?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the literature on the subject that I have read, the first two questions get a historical (semi-psychological) answer. Traces of this answer can also be found between the lines in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen…&amp;rsquo;. There is a great deal of theological discussion on the third issue but I have not followed them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dynamic of religion: secularization and proselytization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:05:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with the idea that religion is some kind of a system (or structure or whatever you feel like using) that maintains itself. That is to say, it is able to reproduce itself, and sustain itself. I call this the `simple reproduction&amp;rsquo; of religion. This dynamic enables not only the reproduction of the community of believers but also the experiential intelligibility that the Cosmos has for them. (Worship, for instance, is one such means for the reproduction of religion.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian belief: worldview is a cultural universal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 20:50:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lets become clear about the nature of my claims about worldviews.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The word carries multiple meanings. It has partly to do with the multiple meanings of the component words: world&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;. In daily language-use, &amp;lsquo;world&amp;rsquo; is used to pick out (a) a spatial and temporal slice of the cosmos (b) and/or the entire Cosmos itself. The first, the slices, are many: from the &amp;lsquo;social world&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;rsquo;emotional world&amp;rsquo;; from earth (&amp;lsquo;our world&amp;rsquo;) to parts of the same (&amp;lsquo;our part of the world&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;in different parts of the world&amp;rsquo;) and so on. The same consideration applies to &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;: it could refer to perspectives (&amp;lsquo;my view of the issue&amp;rsquo;) and to the totality (&amp;lsquo;we now have a clear view of the situation&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As though this is not enough, the word &amp;lsquo;world view&amp;rsquo; also carries additional multiple meanings: it picks out a totality of beliefs that some individual has; it refers at times exclusively to false beliefs (the Marxist use of the notion of ideology); it is either necessary or strictly superfluous (depending on how one interprets the scope of &amp;lsquo;ideology&amp;rsquo;); it picks out the common denominator among a group of people and the latter itself can refer to a nation, a class, a culture, the species, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularization and world views</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularization-and-world-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 19:03:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularization-and-world-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To begin with the question raised in `The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;: Do all cultures, peoples, and individuals need a world view to navigate themselves in the world? The answer is in the negative because religion is not a cultural universal and the only examples we have of world views are religions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Are the atheists, free thinkers, and people ignorant of religious doctrines of Christianity (in the West) also religious? This question has a positive answer because of the process of secularization of religion. In this sense, keeping in mind that the process of secularization is how a religion attempts to transcend its constraints, the atheists etc. in the west do have a Christian world view. This means the following: they accept the doctrines of a de-Christianized Christianity and, for these to be continually transmitted and make sense to those who accept them, this religion requires to be present in the background (and is subject to secularization movement). That is to say, we can identify elements of a Christian world view in the west, and we can do that only because that religion is present in the culture. We need to keep in mind that these beliefs are part of a world view only because such a world view is present in that culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of the Present. Thinking Through Orientalism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:40:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Though the book was published nearly two decades ago, Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt; continues to be topical. Many have rejected the message of this work; others have attempted to develop its arguments yet further. This article will not be one more interpretation of Said&amp;rsquo;s book; after all, there are many such interpretations, including Said&amp;rsquo;s own. Instead, it probes the phenomenon of &amp;lsquo;post-Orientalism&amp;rsquo;. Even here, the intention is not to map its contours either historically or conceptually. Rather, the focus is on raising the question: what next after &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Amartya Sen&#39;s Argumentative Indian—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:17:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, there are multiple images of India current in the West. There is the mystic India, an image that the German Romantics created and the &amp;lsquo;flower children&amp;rsquo; of the sixties made popular. There is the third world India with enormous poverty and suffering, which the developmental workers have projected. There is also the India, the centre of IT outsourcing, which the developments in the last decade have brought into existence, and so on. Amartya Sen, the Indian noble prize-winner in Economics, has written a book on &amp;ldquo;The Argumentative Indian&amp;rdquo; which speaks of an India that he wants us to consider. This India is an India with a history of toleration and pluralism, an India that has brought forth its own version of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo;, and an India that is every bit rational, discursive and analytical as the western culture itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atheism: a secularized theism—Jakob de Roover</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 01:25:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1: Atheism is a phenomenon that came into being in the western culture at around the time of the so-called Enlightenment. The West claims that it liberated itself from the dogmas of the Christian religion in this Enlightenment, and those who call themselves atheists mean by this that they belong to the enlightened people who &amp;ldquo;have escaped from the dogmatic illusions of religion.&amp;rdquo; Now, as it has always done, Christian Europe simply identified its own history with human history in general, and it claimed that all cultures had so far been under the ignorant spell of religion, but that they could now be liberated by the Enlightened West. This claim needs two separate premises: (a) That all cultures have religion (b) That atheism was a new and rational system of beliefs that could liberate people from all cultures from this illusion of religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legislations against proselytization: a weakness of Indian culture –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:03:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: One thing that Balu says is that propping up legislations against tricky proselytizations reflects the weaknesses of Indian culture needs to be explained though. How is it a weakness? How is it not a strength?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In both the theory of rights and in discussions about liberty (or freedom), the following two ways of conceptualizing the issues have been present. One could see rights as an &amp;ldquo;ability or power or capacity&amp;rdquo; to do something (this is called &amp;ldquo;active rights&amp;rdquo;) or as a &amp;ldquo;duty someone else has towards the rights subject&amp;rdquo; (called the &amp;ldquo;passive rights&amp;rdquo;). Equally, liberty has been conceptualized &amp;lsquo;positively&amp;rsquo; (as one&amp;rsquo;s capacity) or &amp;rsquo;negatively&amp;rsquo; (what the other should not do to you). Any good introduction to the theory of rights or theory of liberty will provide you with the details you require as well as the limitations of these two conceptualizations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christological dilemma and “who is a Christian”</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-and-who-is-a-christian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:26:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-and-who-is-a-christian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Christians of all hue agree that the &lt;em&gt;figure of Christ&lt;/em&gt; is central to the religion that Christianity is. This figure is &amp;ldquo;the promised one&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;messiah&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;anointed one&amp;rdquo;, and so on. Kindly note that there is a difference between the Christ as a figure and &lt;em&gt;Jesus of Nazareth&lt;/em&gt;. The Jews also believe in the Christ figure, but they figure that he has not yet come, and they are awaiting his arrival. The Christians reckon that the Christ has come and that Jesus of Nazareth was the &amp;ldquo;prophesied one&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theme: interests of a social institution/Christian Church</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-interests-of-a-social-institutionchristian-church/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:08:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-interests-of-a-social-institutionchristian-church/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the state, state action and the issue of public interest. There are multiple problems here, which I am only slowly beginning to recognize. I will share two such problems with you without, however, being able to concretely spell out the alternatives. (a) Consider the belief that the state &amp;lsquo;ought&amp;rsquo; to act in the public interest. This belief makes sense if we assume that it is possible to speak in terms of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo; in some non-trivial fashion. Both Kenneth Arrow and Amrtya Sen have proved theorems that show that any such use incoherent: Arrow argued that we cannot speak of &amp;lsquo;public will&amp;rsquo; in any coherent way; Sen argued that we cannot aggregateprivate preferences into a consistent and coherent set of &amp;lsquo;public preferences&amp;rsquo;. Our notion of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo; includes these two notions and, as a consequence, does not allow of a coherent conceptualization. Even banning smoking in public places (whatever the notion of a &amp;lsquo;public space&amp;rsquo; be) is not very coherent, if argued in terms of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo;. In this sense, justifying complex actions, which carry unintended consequences, in the name of public interest is not an interesting exercise. (b) Despite this, the idea of the state and its relation to public interest preoccupies people because of something else: that is the belief that every institution in society has an &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; and the state has a &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo;. That is, there is an underlying assumption of &amp;lsquo;intelligibility&amp;rsquo; to claims about &amp;ldquo;institutional interests&amp;rsquo;: each institution has an interest the way each individual has either a &amp;lsquo;desire&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo;. The more I read history, the less intelligible it has become to me. I believe that this claim is a &amp;lsquo;secular translation&amp;rsquo; of the idea that &lt;em&gt;the Christian Church has some set of interests&lt;/em&gt; and political thinking, since the Middle Ages in Europe, has so constantly hammered on this theme that it has become a trivial fact that we take for granted. It is totally unclear to me how we identify the &amp;lsquo;interests&amp;rsquo; of a social institution, the State included, and how we find out whether we are wrong or right in attributing such an &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; to a social institution. In other words, we have no clue how we solve our disagreement in this area of legal and political philosophy: the more radical the disagreement, the less clear how we should solve the issue: suppose I deny that the State has any set of interests that it can call its own, how do we solve this disagreement? On the basis of some or another definition about what &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; is or what &amp;lsquo;State&amp;rsquo; is?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian Theme: Moral Certainty and Proof Beyond a Reasonable Doubt</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-moral-certainty-and-proof-beyond-a-reasonable-doubt/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:58:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-moral-certainty-and-proof-beyond-a-reasonable-doubt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Larry Laudan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/805698/Is_Reasonable_Doubt_Reasonable&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Reasonable is &amp;lsquo;Proof Beyond a Reasonable Doubt&amp;rsquo;?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (published in the journal Legal Theory), shows how the principle of proof beyond a reasonable doubt is utterly unreasonable when one analyzes it in terms of  epistemological standards. Laudan&amp;rsquo;s argument is convincing. The problem is it makes all these judges and lawyers look like &lt;em&gt;fools&lt;/em&gt;. Balu was not satisfied by Laudan&amp;rsquo;s pragmatic justification of proof  beyond a reasonable doubt (of 10 accused, the principle will lead to 9 being legitimately convicted and 1 innocent fellow going to the gallows). Interestingly, the advocacy of this legal principle often invokes a notion of &amp;lsquo;moral certainty&amp;rsquo;. It is as though when a group of 12 (?) jury members and a judge unanimously come to the decision that there is proof beyond a reasonable doubt, then the individual at the other end must be guilty of whatever he or she is accused of. Now, this attitude, Balu suggests, reflects the notion of conscience in the Christian religion. According to the theology of conscience, God has inscribed His Law for humanity in all human creatures. A few definitions can show what conscience means to Christians: &amp;ldquo;The conscience of man…Is a man&amp;rsquo;s judgement of himselfe, according to the judgement of God of him.&amp;rdquo; Or: &amp;ldquo;Conscience is that Power, or Faculty of the Mind, which judges of our Actions according to a right Rule, whether they be agreeable to it or not.&amp;rdquo; This rule is God&amp;rsquo;s Will. Conscience is called &amp;ldquo;that universal Monarch, whose Ubiquitary Throne is establish&amp;rsquo;d in every mortal Breast.&amp;rdquo; A Quaker writes that conscience is &amp;ldquo;an Ability in the Understanding of man, by a reflective act to judge of himself in all he does, as to his acceptance or rejection with God&amp;rdquo; and he adds that &amp;ldquo;this is the inward Rule he hath to walk by.&amp;rdquo; Before the fall, Adam had been perfectly good and even after the fall, humankind retained the knowledge of the perfectly good in contrast with evil. This perfect knowledge allowed man to distinguish &amp;ldquo;between Good and Evil,&amp;rdquo; and worked as &amp;ldquo;a constant witness to God in his soul, and by secret reference to what he was at firrst, tells him what he still ought to be.&amp;rdquo; The left-over of God&amp;rsquo;s Will in us after the Fall is what we still call conscience. In other words, conscience tells us how we ought to act according to God&amp;rsquo;s Will and judges every act of ours in relation to this norm. Given the belief that each individual conscience still reflects the Will of God to some extent (unless it is completely corrupted, but this the selection of jury members is supposed to prevent), the origin of the notions of moral certainty and proof beyond a reasonable doubt becomes clear. When so many good Christians agree on the guilt of the accused, it must be God&amp;rsquo;s Will speaking through their consciences. It is sickening to see how law&amp;rsquo;s reproduction of secularized Christian attitudes towards morality leads to the upholding of a silly principle in the American courts (and to the conviction of innocents).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian Belief: Religion is a cultural/human universal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-religion-is-a-culturalhuman-universal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:39:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-religion-is-a-culturalhuman-universal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of these so-called secular accounts that are in fact Christian is the belief that all cultures have a religion. It is simply a secularization of the Christian belief that the biblical God gave religion to humankind, which was transformed into the assumption that religion is a cultural universal during the Enlightenment. This pre-theoretical assumption precedes all empirical research and theory-formation on religion and culture. From the early missionaries to the contemporary anthropologists, no one has ever even doubted that the phenomenon of religion is universal to all cultures. All psychological and sociological and even biological and neurological explanations of religion take this pre-theoretical Christian theological assumption as a starting point. Now, this is hardly scientific, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? In &lt;a href=&#34;http://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness&#34;&gt;his book &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;, Balagangadhara shows that the belief that all cultures have religion has more to do with the structure of the Christian religion than with the nature of human cultures. Furthermore, he develops a theory of religion which reveals that Christianity, Islam, and Judaism are at present the only instances of the phenomenon of religion. On top of that, he shows why those belonging to these religions and to the cultures they have created, are deeply inclined to believe that all human cultures must have a religion or at least a world view. The latter belief in the universality of religion is not a scientific hypothesis at all, but a religious doctrine. He also shows that the pagan traditions have a structure that is completely different from that of these three religions. In other words, the semitic religions and the pagan traditions are not variants of the same supposedly universal phenomenon of religion, rather they are &lt;strong&gt;different phenomena&lt;/strong&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The religion of secular state: deChristianized Christianity –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-religion-of-secular-state-dechristianized-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:33:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-religion-of-secular-state-dechristianized-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Assuming that the distinction I &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-vs-civic-intolerance/&#34; title=&#34;Religious intolerance vs. civic intolerance I&#34;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; between &lt;em&gt;civic tolerance&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;religious tolerance&lt;/em&gt; is acceptable, let us proceed further to analyze the notion of civic tolerance more closely. (I am simply assuming that it is desirable and that, from now on, we are talking about religious matters.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is (logically) possible that there could be religious intolerance and yet the believers in such religions could have the virtue of civic tolerance. That is to say, even (a) if there is religious intolerance, believers in some religion or another could have a society where there is civic tolerance. As suggested earlier, (b) religious tolerance implies the presence of civic tolerance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the distinction between ‘secular’and ‘religious’ neutral? –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:30:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question appears to be: need one accept certain premises of Christianity (whether Protestant or Catholic varieties) in order that the dominant understanding of, say, the secular state and the caste to make sense? That those to whom such accounts make sense do not explicitly subscribe to the premises of a specific religious appears to throw doubt on our claims.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the very distinction between &amp;rsquo;the religious&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the secular&amp;rsquo;. Historically, Christianity has drawn this line. (Theologians have spent much ink over the last two thousand years drawing, defending, and elaborating upon this distinction.) It is also the case that political thinkers in the West, some of whom were militantly atheistic, have made this distinction into a cornerstone of their theories. Further, many Indian thinkers, most of whom know very little of Christian theologies, base their arguments on these and allied distinctions. The existence of the last two groups appears to tell us that even when one rejects some or all religions, even when one is utterly oblivious to the histories and theologies of the Christianities, this distinction does make sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Social sciences are not providing knowledge, including the likes of Wendy Doniger and her children?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The general pattern that has come to the fore is that Wendy and her children (including Jeffrey Kripal) &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt; portray the Indian traditions in an unfavorable light, even when compared to how religions like Christianity, Islam and Judaism are portrayed. This claim is made in several articles, independent of whether these religions and the Indian traditions are true or false, whether they are irrational or rational, and so on. The discussion is not about the truth-claims of these religions and traditions but about their depictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative portrayals of non-Western Cultures like Indian: Secularization of Christianity – S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 04:59:02 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to raise three issues: (a) how to analyze what Rajiv portrays about Wendy and her children in the field of religious studies; (b) depending on that, what an adequate response consists of. Before we do either (this is one of the things I have discovered through my own research during the last two decades), we need to be clear about (c) how we &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; analyze this situation. Given that all three (in their general form) have been my obsessions, I have been reflecting on them deeply, seriously and systematically for some time now. I would like to share some of the results of this reflection. In the first part, I will take a (rather slow) run up to tackling the third issue first. And even here, I look at RISA &lt;em&gt;lila&lt;/em&gt; as an exemplification of a more general issue or as an expression of a much broader tendency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
