<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dialogues on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/dialogues/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dialogues on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:27:43 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/dialogues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Anthropology and Rhetorics in Cultures.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-rhetorics-in-cultures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:27:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-rhetorics-in-cultures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is best that we begin on a personal note. Neither of the two authors of this article is a &amp;lsquo;specialist&amp;rsquo; in the domain of argumentation theory. Even though we have picked up smatterings of logic, we are not professionals working on either informal or formal logic. One of us is a practicing anthropologist, while the other is oriented towards comparative anthropology. And yet, we are invited to speak to an audience comprising of people specializing in dialogue logics, argumentation theory, psychology and such like. If the invitation to present a paper is not mistake or an oversight on the part of the organizers of this colloquium, then it could only mean that there is an expectation regarding our contributions: anthropologists have something to say about rhetorics, argumentations and their norms, which is of relevance to specialists like you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denying experience in intra-cultural communication—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-in-intra-cultural-communication-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 08:44:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-in-intra-cultural-communication-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with one of the minimal conditions for inter-cultural (verbal) communication. And that is: people should be able to have conversations with each other. It is legitimate to claim that one does not need to know what a &amp;lsquo;conversation&amp;rsquo; is in order to have a conversation. Therefore, whatever else we may want to say, it would be very difficult to maintain that there is no conversation in other cultures. Equally difficult would it be to hold that some cultures are inferior to others regarding their practice of conversational activity. In other words, our intuitions do not allow us to assert either a factual or a normative claim, which would either deny the existence of conversation in other cultures or suggest that members from some cultures are incompetent conversationalists.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
