<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Secularism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/secularism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Secularism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 18:26:26 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/secularism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dark Hour of Secularism: Hindu Fundamentalism and Colonial Liberalism in India</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dark-hour-of-secularism-hindu-fundamentalism-colonial-liberalism-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 18:26:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dark-hour-of-secularism-hindu-fundamentalism-colonial-liberalism-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The relation between religion and politics remains one of the important issues of our time. The discussions on this relation swing between two extremes: religious fundamentalism and liberal secularism. These are regarded as opposites. As the liberal perspective sees it, the secular state and its principles of neutrality and toleration are antidotes to religious fundamentalism[1]. Recently, this view has been challenged. Several authors point out that fundamentalism and secularism are not self-contained opposites, but are intertwined in significant ways[2].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Secular State and Religious Conflict: Liberal Neutrality and the Indian Case of Pluralism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 08:27:21 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s Note: This article appeared in the Journal of Political Philosophy. Authored by SN Balagangadhara and Jakob De Roover. For an alternative research programme (paradigm)  for studying India, Indian culture and Indian culture, study Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Reconceptualizing Indian Studies&lt;/strong&gt;, published by OUP, India.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are few places in the contemporary world where the problems of cultural pluralism are as acute as they are in India. The Indian case poses fundamental challenges to the political theory of toleration. By tackling the problem of religious conversion, our analysis shows that the dominant way of conceiving state neutrality becomes untenable in the Indian context. The Indian state, modelled after the liberal democracies in the West, is the harbinger of religious conflict in India because of its conception of toleration and state neutrality. More of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; in India will end up feeding what it fights: the so-called &amp;lsquo;Hindu fundamentalism&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How do we understand the concept of Communal Violence?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 05:17:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all agree that events like the Gujarat riots are tragic and terrible. But what is the role of intellectuals in avoiding similar tragedies in the future?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why can’t religion be political?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the duty of the intellectual is to try and help us understand the nature of the events and the violence involved. In India and abroad, the concepts of ‘communalism’ and ‘communal violence’ are often used to analyse these riots. These tell us that the main cause behind the Hindu-Muslim conflicts in India is the use of religion for political ends. It is often added that religion itself is not responsible for the riots, but rather its misuse by power-hungry clerics and politicians. The harm of communalism lies in its mixing of political aims and religious identities, which is taken to cause violence. Let us have a closer look at this concept of communal violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incoherence of Indian scholars on secularism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/incoherence-of-indian-scholars-on-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 20:42:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/incoherence-of-indian-scholars-on-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sasheej Hegde in his EPW article says: &amp;ldquo;A theory of secularism in the sense of a theory about possessing the concept &amp;lsquo;secular&amp;rsquo; is quite distinct from a theory about how the concept secular represents.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is downright incoherent. He obviously thinks that a theory about secularism (which is a political theory) is about &amp;lsquo;possessing the concept of the secular&amp;rsquo; (which is &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categories-ii/&#34;&gt;a psychological theory about having concepts&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; in general). The latter, he says, is different about a philosophical theory about how any concept &amp;lsquo;represents&amp;rsquo;. It is true, a political theory about secularism is different from a psychological theory about human beings acquire concepts and both of these are different from a philosophical theory about how any concept represents what it purports to represent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is  laukika-adhyatimika distinction same as secular-sacred distinction?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 22:21:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The theories (and discussions) about secularism constitute a test case for the claims advanced in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo; about the universalizing drive of religion. I have suggested that religion spreads by secularizing itself, and that the distinction between the secular and the religious is drawn by and within a religion. If this is the case, then it must be possible to show that the current theories of secularism are secularizations of a particular set of theological claims. (Theology draws these distinctions and defends them.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularism and Absence of Theory</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:23:55 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A text like &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/&#34; title=&#34;The Vacuity of Secularism&#34;&gt;my article on the secularism debate&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; (&lt;em&gt;EPW&lt;/em&gt;, September 28, 2002), is something more than a sequence of sentences. This is a scientific text, which builds an argument. Therefore, the different sentences have different status according to their function in the argument. Some are premises, and others state the conclusions that follow from these. Some sentences illustrate the point made, yet others provide evidence. To understand such a text, one has to grasp the logical relations between these different sentences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vacuity of Secularism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:20:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Indian Debate and Its Western Origins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The rise of Hindutva has often been interpreted as a threat to the secular state. Similarly, the recent outbursts of Hindu-Muslim conflict are said to be related to the decay of secularism. The author argues that the concept of secularism is fundamentally obscure, since it is founded upon an arbitrary distinction between the religious and the secular. The belief that religion should be separated from politics is a normative dogma that precedes all theoretical analysis of the Indian situation. Therefore, this concept of secularism prevents us from understanding the problems of pluralism in contemporary India, instead of helping us to solve them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularism, Colonialism and Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:01:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few decades, &amp;ldquo;secularism&amp;rdquo; has become the subject of caustic debate in the Indian media. The dispute about the value of this idea to contemporary India is no longer confined to the academic circles. Politicians, journalists and others have strong views on the topic. Secularism regularly surfaces in newspaper articles, speeches and public meetings. The critics of the idea, however, are not often taken seriously at the theoretical level. The proponents of secularism dismiss all objections against their pet idea as misguided. Critics are either considered to be naive obscurantists, who dream of a return to a romantic image of Indian traditional society; or they are condemned as Hindu fundamentalists, who resist modern secular values and strive for a Hindu religious state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Indian Secularists do not think but talk?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:26:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to go deeper into the claim of &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-%e2%80%93s-n-balagangadhara/&#34; title=&#34;Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara&#34;&gt;my earlier post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; that Shabnum Tejanis and Neera Chandhokes of this world do not think but merely talk. In other words, is it possible to identify the problems with their accounts (that explicates more clearly why I say that they do not think) in such a way that it is susceptible to some sort of solution? If, indeed, we can show that such people do not think and we can show that their mistakes have some cognitive roots, then we can also provide additional explanations. In such a case, our answer would be richer and more complex than any other available at the market place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 07:56:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; Consider the thought that &amp;lsquo;meanings&amp;rsquo; (leave aside the distinction between words and sentences on the one hand and concepts and categories on the other) do not exist outside historical contexts. What exactly does this thought say? Begin with &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;. Either every situation that an individual human being finds himself is a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; (because human beings are always &amp;lsquo;in a context&amp;rsquo; and these contexts always occur &amp;lsquo;in history&amp;rsquo;) or there is a difference between &amp;rsquo; a context&amp;rsquo; and a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;.  She cannot possibly make the latter of the two claims because if the meaning of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; changes only in &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo; but not in &amp;lsquo;other kinds of contexts&amp;rsquo;, it follows that &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; has a stable meaning in other contexts than  &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo;, which she would want to deny. So, for the sake of consistency, we have to assume that &amp;lsquo;context&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; are synonyms. Then, the thought is that meaning varies according to contexts. Consider the word &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo;: the only way I can imagine that the meaning of this word varies according to individual contexts is the following: to one, it means a &amp;rsquo;life saver&amp;rsquo;; to the other &amp;lsquo;fattening&amp;rsquo; and to the third &amp;lsquo;sweet&amp;rsquo; and so on. (In fact, to one and the same individual &amp;lsquo;ice cream&amp;rsquo; could &amp;ldquo;mean different things&amp;rdquo; at different points in time: what ice-cream meant  when one was 3 years need indeed not be the same as what it means when one is 50 and suffers from Diabetes and obesity.) So far so good. But the problem is this: these different meanings of &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; presuppose that we are talking about the same thing. Only under this condition can we say that &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; means different things to different people (or to the same person at different times).  To talk about the same thing, ice-cream, we need a reference for that word and, in many cases (like secularism and communalism, for example) it is a &amp;rsquo;linguistic description&amp;rsquo; of that word (a &amp;lsquo;definition&amp;rsquo;, or its &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo;) that provides us with reference. (In the case of ice-cream, one might use gestures to point out an ice-cream; you cannot do that for &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;communalism&amp;rsquo;.) In other words, the ONLY possible way for secularism to have multiple meanings in multiple historical contexts is by having a meaning that is INDEPENDENT of contexts. (Or having a meaning that is common across all POSSIBLE contexts.) In other words, when Neera or Shabnum or anyone else makes the claim that meanings do not transcend contexts either (a) they are making the trivial point that every word uttered by any human being always takes place in a context (which no one had ever denied) or (b) by saying that meaning is totally context bound they are contradicting themselves. Of course, to notice that one is inconsistent, one needs to think according to the rules of grammar and rules of logic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
