<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Epw on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/epw/</link><description>Recent content in Epw on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:28:31 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/epw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Courting controversy in the West</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:28:31 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sustained efforts by certain Hindu groups in the west to redefine and &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; long existing Hindu traditions are perhaps reflective of their desire to put in place a cogent and structured religious system that is able to hold its own against other scripture-based religions. Concomitantly, American identity politics and European political correctness is also &amp;ldquo;forcing&amp;rdquo; minority communities to assert their separate &amp;ldquo;churches&amp;rdquo;, as a way of emphasising their own distinct religious or ethnic identity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secularism and Absence of Theory</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:23:55 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A text like &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/" title="The Vacuity of Secularism"&gt;my article on the secularism debate&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;EPW&lt;/em&gt;, September 28, 2002), is something more than a sequence of sentences. This is a scientific text, which builds an argument. Therefore, the different sentences have different status according to their function in the argument. Some are premises, and others state the conclusions that follow from these. Some sentences illustrate the point made, yet others provide evidence. To understand such a text, one has to grasp the logical relations between these different sentences.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Vacuity of Secularism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:20:34 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Indian Debate and Its Western Origins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The rise of Hindutva has often been interpreted as a threat to the secular state. Similarly, the recent outbursts of Hindu-Muslim conflict are said to be related to the decay of secularism. The author argues that the concept of secularism is fundamentally obscure, since it is founded upon an arbitrary distinction between the religious and the secular. The belief that religion should be separated from politics is a normative dogma that precedes all theoretical analysis of the Indian situation. Therefore, this concept of secularism prevents us from understanding the problems of pluralism in contemporary India, instead of helping us to solve them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Question of Conversion in India</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:14:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian debate on religious conversion has been an ongoing one for a few centuries now. However, the mutual understanding between the advocates and the adversaries of conversion has not advanced much. This paper suggests that this is due to the fact that Hindus and Christians refer to two different objects when they discuss &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. The traits which the Christians ascribe to religion account for the premium they put on the right to convert, while the traits of the Hindu view of religion explain the opposition to conversion. As the two parties attribute mutually exclusive properties to religion, they encounter difficulties while seeking to make sense of each other&amp;rsquo;s claims about religion and conversion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>