<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vibrancy on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/vibrancy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vibrancy on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/vibrancy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Proselytizing drive of the Eastern Christianity in India</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually, there are two questions that need to be distinguished from each other. There is, firstly, the question about the nature of &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity. If it is muted in its proselytizing drive in all cultures the &lt;em&gt;same way&lt;/em&gt; and if it is &amp;rsquo;tolerant&amp;rsquo; in &lt;em&gt;exactly the same way&lt;/em&gt; in all cultures, it makes sense to ask the question whether (a) different factors in all these cultures have brought about the same effect (different &amp;lsquo;causes&amp;rsquo; can generate one and the same effect in differing circumstances) or (b) it is due to the nature of the &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity itself. Nobody is able to make such a claim today. We do not possess the theoretical apparatus which would allow us to make sense of the remarks I have made in italics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibrancy of Indian traditions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:21:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The discussion about re-accessing the vibrancy of the Indian culture and the question whether or not to legislate against conversion, are best treated separately. An answer to the latter does not necessarily count as an answer to the first. In fact, the tendency to counter the proselytising drive of Christianity and Islam by voting laws against conversion is itself an &lt;em&gt;indication&lt;/em&gt; of India’s cultural weakness. Hence, it cannot be a means to re-kindle the flame of India’s pluralistic tradition. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The loss of the vibrancy of Indian Traditions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-loss-of-the-vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2014 12:51:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-loss-of-the-vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I would like to address a very basic issue that many of us have confronted. In its simplest form, the question is this: What should we, a small slice of the Indian intelligentsia, be doing? We can vent our anger and frustration at the way the Indian politicians are handling (or mishandling) the Kashmiri situation; we can express hurt and outrage that &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; are singled out for special treatment both by the &amp;rsquo;liberals&amp;rsquo; and by a section of the Muslim population; we can propose a trifurcation of Kashmir; or that the Muslims be &amp;rsquo;taught&amp;rsquo; a lesson (whatever that lesson consists of); indulge in abuse and name-calling; or whatever else that takes our fancy at any particular moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Follow Our Forefathers: The Nature of Tradition –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:25:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading this contribution and all the others (&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;) I hope to write, we need to keep the context in mind. The context is this: many intellectuals, both in India and among the NRIs elsewhere, appear bent on transforming our multiple traditions into a single &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. The problem does not lie in the transformation of variety and diversity into a unity. Rather, it lies in trying to fit our traditions into the straightjacket of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. While calling ourselves &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; might be a convenient way of talking, the danger lies in going further and trying to develop &amp;lsquo;doctrines&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;theologies&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;catechisms&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Ten Commandments&amp;rsquo; so that those around us in the West could recognize us as followers of a religion called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. (These reflections are also applicable to &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Jainism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Saivism&amp;rsquo; and all such entities.) In the course of my future contributions, I will look at some of the compulsions that force us to manufacture &amp;lsquo;Hinduism as a religion&amp;rsquo;. In this piece, I want to focus on the nature of traditions. What is a tradition? What differentiates religions from traditions? The second question will remain implicit until the end. By that time, we should have a better understanding of what it means to speak of a tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended reproduction of religion and revitalization of Indian traditions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:21:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Why did Christianity become a &amp;lsquo;universal&amp;rsquo; religion? How did Christians replace the &amp;lsquo;chosen&amp;rsquo; people? What was the logic behind the transformation of the Jewish god into God of the humankind?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the literature on the subject that I have read, the first two questions get a historical (semi-psychological) answer. Traces of this answer can also be found between the lines in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen…&amp;rsquo;. There is a great deal of theological discussion on the third issue but I have not followed them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legislations against proselytization: a weakness of Indian culture –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:03:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: One thing that Balu says is that propping up legislations against tricky proselytizations reflects the weaknesses of Indian culture needs to be explained though. How is it a weakness? How is it not a strength?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In both the theory of rights and in discussions about liberty (or freedom), the following two ways of conceptualizing the issues have been present. One could see rights as an &amp;ldquo;ability or power or capacity&amp;rdquo; to do something (this is called &amp;ldquo;active rights&amp;rdquo;) or as a &amp;ldquo;duty someone else has towards the rights subject&amp;rdquo; (called the &amp;ldquo;passive rights&amp;rdquo;). Equally, liberty has been conceptualized &amp;lsquo;positively&amp;rsquo; (as one&amp;rsquo;s capacity) or &amp;rsquo;negatively&amp;rsquo; (what the other should not do to you). Any good introduction to the theory of rights or theory of liberty will provide you with the details you require as well as the limitations of these two conceptualizations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
