<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Proselytization on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/proselytization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Proselytization on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/proselytization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Proselytizing drive of the Eastern Christianity in India</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually, there are two questions that need to be distinguished from each other. There is, firstly, the question about the nature of &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity. If it is muted in its proselytizing drive in all cultures the &lt;em&gt;same way&lt;/em&gt; and if it is &amp;rsquo;tolerant&amp;rsquo; in &lt;em&gt;exactly the same way&lt;/em&gt; in all cultures, it makes sense to ask the question whether (a) different factors in all these cultures have brought about the same effect (different &amp;lsquo;causes&amp;rsquo; can generate one and the same effect in differing circumstances) or (b) it is due to the nature of the &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity itself. Nobody is able to make such a claim today. We do not possess the theoretical apparatus which would allow us to make sense of the remarks I have made in italics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proselytization vs. Persecution</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytization-vs-persecution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:03:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/proselytization-vs-persecution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Most of us would not know the difference between the Syrian Orthodox, the Greek Orthodox and the Russian Orthodox Churches; many will be hard put to differentiate between the Pope and the Patriarch. In these circumstances, it is foolish to write &lt;em&gt;apologetica&lt;/em&gt; for &amp;lsquo;Eastern Christianity&amp;rsquo; and criticise &amp;lsquo;Western Christianity&amp;rsquo;. Let those concerned with the nature of Christian theologies do that. But that does not concern us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rajiv, regarding your #82 (from Sulekha board). The Emperor Constantine &lt;strong&gt;did not&lt;/strong&gt; start a trend. &lt;em&gt;UrChristenthum&lt;/em&gt; was as viciously proselytizing as the most rabid Protestant of today. Before one addresses oneself to the role that &amp;lsquo;power&amp;rsquo; played in the proselytizing drive of Christianity, one needs to know what &lt;em&gt;proselytization&lt;/em&gt; means. Consider the role that the Emperors played in Rome (and the role played by some Kings in India.) They would promote some or another tradition (or &amp;lsquo;cult&amp;rsquo;, as they were called in the Roman Empire), &lt;em&gt;persecute the followers&lt;/em&gt; of some or another tradition (or cult). &lt;strong&gt;Does that mean that the cults proselytized too, or that they were as &amp;lsquo;intolerant&amp;rsquo; as the Semitic religions?&lt;/strong&gt; To affirm either of the two is to lose any ability to understand the difference between Indian traditions (or the Roman cults) and the Semitic religions. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended reproduction of religion and revitalization of Indian traditions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:21:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Why did Christianity become a &amp;lsquo;universal&amp;rsquo; religion? How did Christians replace the &amp;lsquo;chosen&amp;rsquo; people? What was the logic behind the transformation of the Jewish god into God of the humankind?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the literature on the subject that I have read, the first two questions get a historical (semi-psychological) answer. Traces of this answer can also be found between the lines in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen…&amp;rsquo;. There is a great deal of theological discussion on the third issue but I have not followed them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dynamic of religion: secularization and proselytization</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:05:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with the idea that religion is some kind of a system (or structure or whatever you feel like using) that maintains itself. That is to say, it is able to reproduce itself, and sustain itself. I call this the `simple reproduction&amp;rsquo; of religion. This dynamic enables not only the reproduction of the community of believers but also the experiential intelligibility that the Cosmos has for them. (Worship, for instance, is one such means for the reproduction of religion.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Legislations against proselytization: a weakness of Indian culture –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:03:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/legislations-against-proselytization-a-weakness-of-indian-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: One thing that Balu says is that propping up legislations against tricky proselytizations reflects the weaknesses of Indian culture needs to be explained though. How is it a weakness? How is it not a strength?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In both the theory of rights and in discussions about liberty (or freedom), the following two ways of conceptualizing the issues have been present. One could see rights as an &amp;ldquo;ability or power or capacity&amp;rdquo; to do something (this is called &amp;ldquo;active rights&amp;rdquo;) or as a &amp;ldquo;duty someone else has towards the rights subject&amp;rdquo; (called the &amp;ldquo;passive rights&amp;rdquo;). Equally, liberty has been conceptualized &amp;lsquo;positively&amp;rsquo; (as one&amp;rsquo;s capacity) or &amp;rsquo;negatively&amp;rsquo; (what the other should not do to you). Any good introduction to the theory of rights or theory of liberty will provide you with the details you require as well as the limitations of these two conceptualizations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
