<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Sciences on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/social-sciences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Sciences on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:10:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/social-sciences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Naming a phenomenon</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:10:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) Paolo Friere, a Brazilian educationalist, has spoken about such a phenomenon at length in his &lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt;. He calls it as an ‘internalisation of the oppressor by the oppressed’. Whether we use Paolo Friere’s terminology or the much later one of ‘Stockholm Syndrome’, the problem is the same: both &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; the phenomenon without &lt;em&gt;explaining it&lt;/em&gt;. In and of itself, not such a big problem if it is not for a cognitive tendency that is &lt;strong&gt;dominant&lt;/strong&gt; in the ‘social sciences’, which brings me to the second point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two kinds of research in social sciences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/two-kinds-of-research-in-social-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 22:27:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/two-kinds-of-research-in-social-sciences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is, on the one hand, the intellectual tradition of expressing opinions and points of view. Here, as it suits thoughtful minds, one tries to express ideas carefully and in a nuanced fashion. Recent peer-opinions are taken into account; generalizations are avoided; the attention is on the specific and the concrete; and, where possible, one’s ideas are either founded upon or embroidered by some or another of the many philosophical stances that are available. The goal of the discussion is to endorse these opinions, or express disagreement on the broad idea expressed by the author. Any other kind of intellectual exercise of often seen as either nit-picking or engaging in polemics. To those who have grown up in this culture, it is obvious what the sought-after intellectual virtues are and how one should cultivate it. In other words, this culture surrounds itself with meta-arguments that is either founded upon or embroidered by some or another meta-philosophy about what intellectuals are, what their role in the realm of ideas should be and how they should relate to the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Feynman know about his culture?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/does-feynman-know-about-his-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 08:15:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/does-feynman-know-about-his-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Paraphrasing Feynman: &amp;ldquo;the answers proposed like counting angels that can dance on the head of a pin are trivial.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am not in the least impressed by (in fact, I am disgusted by and contemptuous about) the attitude of the likes of Feynman. Here is one reason why: I too have a criticism of (some) social sciences and (some) aspects of the western philosophy. I too consider that some of these social sciences are not sciences in any sense of the term. But that is because I believe that some of these disciplines endlessly embroider theology and I feel that my research might go someway in setting the situation straight. In other words, as far as I am concerned, the current state of social science is a problem which requires to be addressed seriously. The reason for the seriousness must be obvious: we &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to urgently understand the nature of human beings in all its facets, if we have to survive as a species. Making fun of philosophy and social sciences is one thing; to do something about it is entirely different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Kripal have an agenda?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 04:56:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do understand the anger that people feel when they read Jeffrey Kripal&amp;rsquo;s and other people&amp;rsquo;s assessment of Indian traditions. If someone were to come up with a similar distortion of my own cultural heritage, I would probably feel the same. However, I do feel troubled when people end up calling Kripal a &amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;ldquo;spiritual bandit&amp;rdquo; or begin to speculate about hidden &amp;lsquo;agendas&amp;rsquo;. My problem is not that these accusations are ad hominem. My problem is that they threaten to obscure a genuine intellectual problem of a more serious nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of the Present. Thinking Through Orientalism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:40:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Though the book was published nearly two decades ago, Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt; continues to be topical. Many have rejected the message of this work; others have attempted to develop its arguments yet further. This article will not be one more interpretation of Said&amp;rsquo;s book; after all, there are many such interpretations, including Said&amp;rsquo;s own. Instead, it probes the phenomenon of &amp;lsquo;post-Orientalism&amp;rsquo;. Even here, the intention is not to map its contours either historically or conceptually. Rather, the focus is on raising the question: what next after &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about people and their cultures?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:53:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us begin in a very intuitive way and ask ourselves this question: where do we encounter &amp;lsquo;cultural differences&amp;rsquo;? In human contacts, of course. What kind of human contacts? &lt;em&gt;In inter-individual contacts&lt;/em&gt;. That is, we see (or sense, or intuit or whatever) cultural differences in our contacts with &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; human beings. You do not meet &amp;rsquo;the western culture&amp;rsquo; but individual Americans, Germans, French, etc. Neither do these individuals meet &amp;rsquo;the Indian culture&amp;rsquo;: they meet individual Indians (or, even better, a &amp;lsquo;Madrasi Brahmin&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;lsquo;Gujerati Baniya&amp;rsquo; - even these are general categories but I use them just to get the point across.) And yet, we appear to see cultural differences in these contacts. How to make &amp;lsquo;sense&amp;rsquo; of &lt;em&gt;this experience&lt;/em&gt;? Let us first see what is partially involved to truly appreciate the complexity of our &amp;lsquo;perception&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Each individual human being is a complex combination of at least four aspects. There is his biological (or genetic) inheritance; there is his &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; inheritance (whether he is from the Middle Ages or from a capitalist society); there is his psychological makeup (let us say his &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;); and there is his cultural upbringing (whether he is a Madhva Brahmin or a Lingayat, say). When we meet individuals, in many different ways we notice these &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt;: the biological, the psychological and, after some time perhaps, &amp;rsquo;the social&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the cultural&amp;rsquo;. Let us bracket the biological away so that the situation becomes deliciously complex. Let us agree to use the following &amp;lsquo;words&amp;rsquo; (they are just words for now) in order to go ahead and raise the problem. Let us call the &amp;lsquo;social aspects&amp;rsquo; of a person the &amp;lsquo;sociality&amp;rsquo; of the person; the psychological aspects the &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo; of the person; and the &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; aspects the &amp;lsquo;culturality&amp;rsquo; of the person. Thus we meet individual human beings and see the differences between ourselves and the other human beings. What kinds of differences do we see?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On explanations that make people stupid—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-explanations-that-make-people-stupid-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 00:57:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-explanations-that-make-people-stupid-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not believe that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; cultural practice (i.e. a practice that has survived and been transmitted through successive generations) should be explained by attributing beliefs to its practitioners in such a way that the beliefs make the practitioners come out stupid. Why do I say this? There are primarily two reasons: our ignorance and the principle of &amp;lsquo;charity&amp;rsquo;. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) &lt;strong&gt;Our ignorance&lt;/strong&gt;. We know very little about how cultures come into being, how they reproduce themselves and how they disappear. Until such a stage, where we are able to discuss each cultural practice (like rain dance, for example) individually, we should avoid making a virtue of our ignorance. One could come up with any number of explanations today to explain a cultural practice like rain dance. Without exception, they would &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; be ad hoc in nature and, as such, the opposite of what a scientific explanation is. Therefore, my criticism of such explanations is to show their ad hoc character and, where possible, identify what makes them ad hoc. The purpose? To move forward in order to develop a science of cultures and cultural differences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Social sciences are not providing knowledge, including the likes of Wendy Doniger and her children?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The general pattern that has come to the fore is that Wendy and her children (including Jeffrey Kripal) &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt; portray the Indian traditions in an unfavorable light, even when compared to how religions like Christianity, Islam and Judaism are portrayed. This claim is made in several articles, independent of whether these religions and the Indian traditions are true or false, whether they are irrational or rational, and so on. The discussion is not about the truth-claims of these religions and traditions but about their depictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reductive explanations in social sciences – S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/reductive-explanations-in-social-sciences-s-n-balagangadh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 21:28:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/reductive-explanations-in-social-sciences-s-n-balagangadh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To begin with, there is the feeling that scientific explanations, with their emphasis on rationality and objectivity, are reductive in nature. Wherein lies the &lt;em&gt;root&lt;/em&gt; of this feeling? Let us say that some physical theory describes the motion of a snow flake gently floating down to earth or a rose petal lazily spinning in the air. Or that some branch of human genetics computes the probability of a particular human child being born with absolutely dark eyes or ones that are brilliantly blue. Is either of these two explanations reductive in nature? Not quite: their mathematical calculations tell us very little about the laziness of the petal or about the brilliance of blue eyes, it is true, but it is not their &amp;lsquo;job&amp;rsquo; to do so. If you want to relish descriptions of an autumn evening or a spring morning, you do not open Feynman&amp;rsquo;s Lectures on Physics, do you? You go elsewhere. In other words, the theories in the natural sciences are not &amp;lsquo;reductive&amp;rsquo; in the sense that they do not reduce the &lt;em&gt;beauty&lt;/em&gt; of a particular sunset to the motion of earth around the Sun even if they explain sunrise and sunset.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative portrayals of non-Western Cultures like Indian: Secularization of Christianity – S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 04:59:02 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to raise three issues: (a) how to analyze what Rajiv portrays about Wendy and her children in the field of religious studies; (b) depending on that, what an adequate response consists of. Before we do either (this is one of the things I have discovered through my own research during the last two decades), we need to be clear about (c) how we &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; analyze this situation. Given that all three (in their general form) have been my obsessions, I have been reflecting on them deeply, seriously and systematically for some time now. I would like to share some of the results of this reflection. In the first part, I will take a (rather slow) run up to tackling the third issue first. And even here, I look at RISA &lt;em&gt;lila&lt;/em&gt; as an exemplification of a more general issue or as an expression of a much broader tendency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
