<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Caste on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/caste/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Caste on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/caste/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enlightenment by Grace or Efforts or Birth?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-by-grace-or-efforts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 13:41:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-by-grace-or-efforts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;9.32 Bhagavadgita&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;māṃ hi pārtha vyapāśritya&#xA;ye &amp;lsquo;pi syuḥ pāpayonayaḥ&#xA;striyo vaiśyāstathā śūdrās&#xA;te&amp;rsquo; pi yānti parāṃ gatim&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The situation is a bit more complex. The word &amp;lsquo;yoni&amp;rsquo; here does much more work than one assumes. All the four are born from &amp;lsquo;Yoni&amp;rsquo; but yet are distinguished in terms of punya and paapa. The last two are earnt by the organism in question: &amp;lsquo;svayaarjita&amp;rsquo;, suggesting that being a brahmana and a rajarshi are earnt titles. As against it, we have a gender and a shudra. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central features of studies on Caste</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/central-features-of-studies-on-caste/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 11:23:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/central-features-of-studies-on-caste/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://creative.sulekha.com/the-hindu-defeat-role-of-caste_103411_blog&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; on Sulekha says:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ut there can be no doubt that for the past thousand years at least the caste system has been a great nightmare for the majority of our people and continues to be a great bane of hindu society as well as hinduism today.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When you write this article on the caste system, I do want you very much to make clear where your &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; regarding the nature of the caste system and its baneful impact both on the hindu and the indian society comes from. There is a reason for this request. For some time, I too thought that the ‘Indian caste system’ was an abomination. In order to find out where it came from, the nature of its foundations, and the causes for its continued reproduction, I started reading and researching into the question. Normally, research renders the questions &lt;strong&gt;sharper&lt;/strong&gt;, but in this case the subject became &lt;strong&gt;vaguer!&lt;/strong&gt; The more I read, the more confusing it all became: everyone seemed to be against the caste system (with a few exceptions) but no one seemed to know what it was! While each had very clear moral opinions on the subject, none had any clear understanding of what they were for/against. Consequently, my request: in your article, please (1) do not &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt; that the caste system is an evil, but show that it is; (2) do not just say it is &lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt;that it is a bane, but demonstrate it;  (3) do not &lt;em&gt;just affirm&lt;/em&gt; that ‘the dalits’ are victims of an immoral and unjust social organisation, but show how and why they are that. So far, I have not been able to prove any of the above claims &lt;em&gt;scientifically&lt;/em&gt; (or even unscientifically). Everyone seems to assume it, and the (literally) thousands of books and articles I have read on this score fail miserably in even saying what ‘the caste system’ is, leave alone &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; that it is the cause of many social and cultural ills in our culture and society. May I look forward to something that at least provides me with a semblance of a proof?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common sense ideas about the caste system</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/common-sense-ideas-about-the-caste-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 23:49:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/common-sense-ideas-about-the-caste-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When I took the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/&#34;&gt;caste-system as an example&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, what am I doing? I am showing that turning the standard story on its head is a child&amp;rsquo;s play: caste has been said to be an antiquated, rigid,  dogmatic, etc social structure, which is &amp;ldquo;very difficult&amp;rdquo; to eradicate. If this is true, most of the rantings  seem to subscribe to this text book story, then this can be put on its head very easily. A word of warning, therefore, to those who ramble on about the &amp;lsquo;immoral&amp;rsquo; caste system: take heed! You do not know what you are talking about.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The issue is not about whether there is poverty and injustice in India. Instead, it is about wanting to correlate these with the caste system. To do this, all one has to show is that poverty and injustice in India is the causal result of the caste system in India, whereas, in other countries of the world, they are the results of &amp;lsquo;something else&amp;rsquo;. No one in the world has been able to show this; if some among you have proof to the contrary, kindly demonstrate. Indulging in shouting matches is easier than arguing reasonably.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What can India offer?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 23:26:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, India has become a global player of significant political and economical impact. Europe and India are facing each other as equal partners in pursuit of greater economic and political co-operation. This confronts both India and Europe with a challenge. The intelligentsia, the business world, politicians, educators and others, will have to answer the following question: What can India offer to the world of today and tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I will not tackle this problem directly but instead take up one of its sub-questions: to whom is this problem important and why? I believe it is important to both Indians and Europeans but for different reasons. In this article, I will spell out and reflect upon some of these reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caste Sytem III</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 18:09:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As I have said before, my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-i/&#34;&gt;hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; is meant to guide the research and, as such, suggests that we find that the Brahmins will exhibit more of a heterarchical organization than a hierarchical one. Let us assume that what you say is true. In that case, this anomaly (or these anomalies) will become the problem(s) that my hypothesis has to solve. That is, the hypothesis will force one to look for an explanation in multiple directions: for instance, have these hierarchies emerged due to induction of new groups and individuals in the course of history? (That means, this hypothesis forces one to probe the truth of the statement that once one is born into a jati, there is no way of moving to another Jati. The Madhva conversion in South India has disproved it but no one I know has taken this fact into consideration.) Who were the majority jati&amp;rsquo;s in the area and what was the nature of interaction between these Brahmin groups and other Jati&amp;rsquo;s? And so on. In other words, each anomaly we confront forces further research. There is always the possibility that my research hypothesis will crumble under the weight of accumulated anomalies but that is not the case yet. At the moment, they merely call for further research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caste System II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 17:51:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two small points before I respond to your questions. One: all I have is &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-i/&#34;&gt;a hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; that can guide research. In itself, it is not a theory and I cannot hope to convince anyone (at this stage) that this hypothesis is true. It requires years of research (of different kinds) before it can be made compelling. Therefore, please know that I understand your skepticism and find it only natural. Two: However, I will give you some indications about why I find the hypothesis interesting and worthy of further research. I will choose some examples at random to indicate the kind of problems that this hypothesis promises to solve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caste hierarchies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-hierarchies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 17:41:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-hierarchies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You ask whether &amp;ldquo;there is a perception of caste hierarchies among Brahmins&amp;rdquo;. My guess is that there is no such general perception, even if, regionally, multiple Brahmin jati&amp;rsquo;s fight for superiority. There is no way to establish, say, that the &amp;lsquo;Babburkamme&amp;rsquo; is superior to &amp;lsquo;Havyaka&amp;rsquo; in Karnataka. In fact, many from either of the two would not even know of the existence of the other. In Bangalore itself, for instance, where the former is preponderant, I did not even know of their existence until I was 15 years old. In this sense, even in areas where they might claim to &amp;lsquo;superiority&amp;rsquo;, it is difficult to establish hierarchies among the Brahmins in any one region. This, as I say, is my guess.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caste system I</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 17:32:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-system-i/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let me reconsider the hypothesis I propose: what we call &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo; in India today is a hybrid beast. It is not a social structure but a linguistic entity (i.e., a set of sentences) which is an incoherent admixture to two unconnected descriptions (of the world): a generalization of the description of a structured set of interactions (let us leave aside the question of what kind of mathematical properties that this &amp;lsquo;structured set&amp;rsquo; has: how it is ordered, whether the ordering is strong or weak and so on) among &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-hierarchies/&#34;&gt;the so-called &amp;rsquo;lower castes&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, while fitting this description within the framework of the varna system, which, I say, is a description of social stratification at a very high level of abstraction or generality. It is incoherent by virtue of its claim to being a &amp;lsquo;unified&amp;rsquo; (and unifying) description of the social structure of Indian society: it collapses descriptions of different things at different levels (of descriptions) into a single alleged description of social reality. That is why these &amp;rsquo;theories&amp;rsquo; of caste are either incoherent, nonsensical or, where neither, false.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: M.N. Srinivas and Sanskritization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-m-n-srinivas-and-sanskritization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 04:25:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-m-n-srinivas-and-sanskritization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;M. N. Srinivas (MNS) claims that &amp;ldquo;a caste was able, in a generation or two, to rise to a higher position in the hierarchy by adopting vegetarianism and teetotalism and by changing its rituals and deities.&amp;rdquo; The first basic problem here is how one can establish the position of a jati in the supposed hierarchy and measure it in such detail that one can see over two generations that the jati has attained a higher position. Which standard does one use to establish the position of jati x? What members of jati x say about its position relative to other jatis? What members of other jatis say about the position of x relative to their own jatis? As our fieldwork in Karnataka has already shown, it is impossible to infer any hierarchy from such empirical data, because all one gets is a series of inconsistent statements with regard to the relative positions of jatis. This basic problem becomes even more intractable when we take into account the history of assigning positions to jatis in the so-called &amp;ldquo;caste hierarchy&amp;rdquo;. When the British had their caste census in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, many jatis classified as shudras or untouchables sent in petitions arguing that they held higher positions; they were kshatriyas, they said. Today, the same jatis insist that they are really shudras or untouchables and should be classified as OBCs or SCs. When jatis can radically revise their &amp;lsquo;position in the hierarchy&amp;rsquo; according to the status or benefits they win by doing so, what could one ever conclude about their position and how it changes over generations?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Should one calculate the average socio-economic level of jati x and compare it to the average level of other jatis? Apart from difficulties in calculating this socio-economic level, one faces an even more difficult problem: how does one circumscribe jati x? Are two groups with the same name both sub-divisions of jati x? What if they claim they are different jatis? What geographical or social unit should one begin with to establish the (socio-economic) position of jati x in the hierarchy? Let us say one takes the village as the relevant unit. How does the socio-economic level that jati x enjoys in some village tell us anything about its position in the hierarchy? If the socio-economic welfare of jati x increases markedly over two generations in this village, does this mean it has attained a higher position? What if the same jati in the surrounding villages has declined? In terms of empirical data, then, it becomes impossible to say (a) what the position is of a jati in the supposed hierarchy and (b) when it has attained a higher position. In other words, MNS can never have inferred his conclusions about Sanskritization and castes rising to higher positions from his &amp;lsquo;fieldwork data&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jati, Varna and Caste</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/jati-varna-and-caste/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:15:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/jati-varna-and-caste/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Are there Jati&amp;rsquo;s in India? Yes, there are. What kind of units or entities are they? I do not know; neither does anybody for that matter. It is a matter of fact that (a) they are not occupational groups; (b) they are not social classes (that is, there is no correlation between Jati&amp;rsquo;s and the &amp;lsquo;means of production&amp;rsquo;); (c) appear hereditary (though one could obtain certificates that &amp;lsquo;change&amp;rsquo; one&amp;rsquo;s Jati legally). Some Jati&amp;rsquo;s are organized as some kind of legal or semi-legal associations, some Jati&amp;rsquo;s are not.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dominant story about the ‘caste system’</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-dominant-story-about-the-caste-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 07:25:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-dominant-story-about-the-caste-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You say: &amp;ldquo;If &amp;lsquo;caste&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;jati&amp;rsquo; has the same status as alumni associations and similar social groups, with their varying practices, it seems we are prepared to say that &amp;lsquo;jati&amp;rsquo; has no special place in the Indian society in the same way that my alumni association has no special status in Indian society.&amp;rdquo; This sentence is the problematic one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First of all, it does not follow (either empirically or logically) that if Jati is a social group much like alumini associations, trades unions, etc it has no special status in Indian society. That depends upon the role, function and the nature of such social groups and these are issues for empirical investigation. For instance, the &amp;ldquo;old boys&amp;rdquo; network&amp;quot; in Britian (comprising of aluminis from public schools and Oxbridge students) apparently plays a very important role in the British society. In certain circles of power in India, alumminis from private schools (like the Doon school, Lawrence school) and colleges like St. Stephens have built sophisticated networks that function like service clubs. In this sense, one cannot claim that alumini networks, by virtue of their composition, do not have a special status in a society. This is an empirical question. Your alumini association might indeed have no special place; that does not preclude some other alumini association from having an important place. (Similarly, by virtue of the fact that some particular trade union does not have a special status in Indian society, it is not possible to make claims about whether trades unions have a special status or not.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caste and Caste system</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-and-caste-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 07:10:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/caste-and-caste-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I would like to pick up the thread on ‘the caste system’ and begin at the beginning. Let us find out what we are discussing about and disagreeing with.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assuming for this entire post, ‘caste’ is an English word for ‘Jati’, the first question is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.   Are there Jati’s in India?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course, there are. No one is denying this obvious fact.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2.   Is there a system of Jati in India?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translations or Travesty of Traditions? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:51:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one sense, the title of the piece captures the nature of the tasks facing the contemporary generation, whether in India or in the Diaspora. This generation, unlike many from mine, is confident and self-assured; perhaps, it is proud too about the strength of its culture and traditions. Rightly so. However, personal convictions about the value of our traditions and culture do not automatically guarantee the truth of such convictions. Not only that. It is also the case that the history of India, and that of the entire humankind, requires of us that we are able to say and show what is valuable and what is not in our traditions. This history is the history of colonialism, subservience, and is further weighed down by the scientific, technological, economic and the military weight of the western culture. Today, we need more than a mere practice and a further continuation of our traditions; we need also to examine them honestly and critically in order that we may transmit what we found valuable in them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Yoga, shudras, and women</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/yoga-shudras-and-women/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 00:23:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/yoga-shudras-and-women/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: Yoga practice of self attainment without the help of external deity worship so common in those days of Patanjali as today was restricted to very few as it required proper initiation from the guru and renunciation of normal humdrum lifestyle of a common man. I say man because fewer women go for that kind of ascetic lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What has self-attainment to do with worshipping the deity (whether internal or external) in the Asian (or Indian) traditions? Except for what has been talked about the Bhakti tradition (especially by the European intellectuals, and picked up later on by the Indians), &amp;lsquo;self-attainment&amp;rsquo; stands radically divorced from any notion of deity &amp;ndash; as far as one can tell. The path of yoga (to stick to what this word refers to in the popular western consciousness) is different from that of meditation or bhakti, in the sense that the former focuses on control (as against &amp;rsquo;letting go&amp;rsquo; in the Buddhist traditions for instance). Renunciation, contrasting it to the &amp;rsquo;normal humdrum lifestyle&amp;rsquo;, is a pre-requisite primarily because this &amp;lsquo;attainment&amp;rsquo; (of &amp;lsquo;self&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo;, Mukti, or whatever) is predicated upon a meta-reflection (and a deep understanding) of the &amp;lsquo;humdrum&amp;rsquo; life. Such a reflection is cognitively impossible when you are involved (entangled would perhpas be a better word here) precisely in the very dynamic on which you have to reflect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vivekananda and Caste Discrimination: theory-ladenness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:52:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You ask whether or not it was &amp;lsquo;factual&amp;rsquo; that a &amp;lsquo;paraiah&amp;rsquo; was not allowed on the same street as a Nair or a Brahmin. The evidence we have says that a Paraiah was not allowed to be on the same street as a Nair, but it is not clear whether it also applies to the presence of a Brahmin. First, here is some of the evidence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Portuguese traveler Duarte Barbosa was among the first to talk about it in &amp;lsquo;The Book&amp;rsquo;. Though written in 1518, it became known to the European world through the Italian translation in the book of travels edited by Gian Baptista Ramusio. In the English translation, we hear who the Nairs are: &amp;ldquo;None may become a Nayre, save only he who is of Nayre lineage. They are very free from stain in their nobility. They will not touch anyone of low caste&amp;rdquo; . You need to keep in mind that Barbosa does not speak of &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo;, as an earlier footnote by the English editor and translator, Dames, indicates: &amp;ldquo;The word used in the text in vilam (villão in modern spelling) corresponding to the English villain in its ancient sense&amp;rdquo; . In other words, Barbosa appears to have seen a distinction in lineage or a distinction between the Nobility and the Rural folk when he saw the Nairs and the &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo; people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Anthropology and Action Sciences. An Essay on Knowing to Act and Acting to Know—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:48:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.philosophica.ugent.be/article/82484/galley/202298/view/&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, published  &lt;em&gt;Philosophica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;40&lt;/strong&gt; (2): 77–107]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Should action sciences exist, it is obvious what they would have to study; the nature of human action, the kind of knowledge that actions generate, the process of learning to perform different types of action and so forth. Comparative anthropology, as a discipline, studies and contrasts, where such contrasts are possible, the different ways in which human beings organize their lives, think about and experience both themselves and world around them. A culture is a form of life and, as such, it is a way of going about the world. One would therefore expect to find a deep and intimate relation between action sciences on the one hand, and studies of culture on the other. A perusal of literature, however, shows the fact of the matter to be different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and Imagination: A Critical Notice of Halbfass and Inden</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 07:10:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the last decade or so, a new restlessness has begun to disturb the calm facade of the social scientific academia. As yet, it has no name. Better said, it has many names: from &amp;lsquo;reflexive&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;lsquo;post-modern&amp;rsquo;. The ferment is not widespread, but the voices of discontent are coherent and articulate. The critical voices indicate the many kinds of dissatisfaction they have with the status and nature of social sciences. Even though most dissenters cannot be grouped as representatives of any one tradition, many of their writings stand out above the rest. Two such authors are Wilhelm Halbfass and Ronald Inden; each has written a book that is worthy of attention and respect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: Burden of Proof</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-burden-of-proof-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 00:22:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-burden-of-proof-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The first thing that is really striking involves what I will call the &lt;em&gt;burden of proof&lt;/em&gt;. That is, I am being asked to prove that my assertions about corruption are true. In one sense, it appears an entirely reasonable demand to make: after all, one should not entertain gratuitous claims. But what seems to have escaped the attention of many is this: what precisely do I have to prove? Who has the burden of proof?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Let us strip the issue to its barest form. I am supposed to prove that we Indians are not corrupt, immoral and/or moral imbeciles. Without proof, is it difficult to accept these claims? But who has proved that we are any or all of these things? Not the western theorists, surely. Not any Indian either. All that exist are bare-bone assertions that some moral principles are violated in a systematic fashion in India. So, what exactly do I have to prove?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: The Logic of “India is Corrupt”</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 22:17:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(A)&lt;/strong&gt; Consider the following sequence of sentences:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are perfectly and fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are perfectly fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For sentences (1) and (2), all it takes is one instance of immorality to be proven wrong. Our proverbial municipal clerk would be immoral, and it would disprove the sentence (1). The same example could also confirm sentence (3); an instance of a moral act would also be a counter-example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Colonial Experience and the Indian Renaissance: A prolegomenon to a Project—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the striking things about the British colonial rule is its success in developing certain ways of talking about the Indian culture and society. The British criticised the Indian &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;, the Indian &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo;, the Indian education system, practices like &amp;lsquo;sati&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;untouchability&amp;rsquo;, and so on and so forth. They redrew the outlines of Indian intellectual history as indigenous responses to some of the ills they saw in the Indian society and culture: for example, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, as it emerged out of their reconstruction, was a revolt against &amp;lsquo;Brahmanism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo;. Many Indian intellectuals emphasized British criticism by making &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; in the latter their own: the Arya Samaj, the Brahmo Samaj, many Hindu &amp;lsquo;reform&amp;rsquo; movements, and so on exemplify this trend. I say &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; and place it in scare quotes because the &lt;em&gt;unbroken line of continuity&lt;/em&gt; between the colonial period and the one following the Indian independence raises two &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of questions. The first is this: would there have been such a line of continuity if there was no &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; to the British portrayal of our history, traditions, and culture? This question uses the &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; of continuity to suggest that the British descriptions &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; That is, our current experience of our culture and society appears to lend truth-value to the colonial descriptions of India. The second question transforms our &amp;lsquo;current experience&amp;rsquo; itself into a problem: does such a line of continuity indicate that our experiences themselves are still colonial in nature? This question throws doubts upon the &amp;lsquo;facticity&amp;rsquo; of the British descriptions of India, and suggests that they &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;lsquo;untrue&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; In the process, it also challenges us to look more closely and investigate our own experiences today. That is, the second question withholds assent to the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of the colonial descriptions of India and of some of the claims we make about our experiences of our culture and society today. To some extent, and only to some extent, the so-called &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; writings can be seen as attempts to make sense of the second question. Even though I do not fancy the label of being a &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; myself, I perceive a shared sense of a quest with them. &lt;em&gt;There is something deeply, deeply wrong with the line of continuity that exists between the colonial period and today&amp;rsquo;s India,&lt;/em&gt; and the challenge is to say what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation of social and cultural changes?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/simulation-of-social-and-cultural-changes-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 03:10:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/simulation-of-social-and-cultural-changes-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A question: Is it desirable to have a model that can simulate social and cultural changes?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I cannot see what good reason there is not to find it desirable. It would be eminently desirable. It will take some time though before we get there, but we will surely get there. Thanks to computers, we have a possibility of talking realistically about simulation. However, we have to still go a very long way before we are able to do so. We need to build some theories about social and cultural change and evolution; we need to develop suitable algorithms for simulating these changes; we need to develop more and different kinds of logics (non-monotonic ones) than exist today; we need to simulate some relevant aspects of human reasoning process … It is only now that we are &lt;em&gt;beginning&lt;/em&gt; to simulate the evolutionary process and have developed some kinds of algorithms to do so. We need to overlay this with developments (hardly understood today) about social dynamics and cultural dynamics. And then study what could happen. So, it is definitely going to take some time. In all probability, we will first start simulating some fragments of social or cultural reality first (after all, this is what modeling means).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
