<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bullshit on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/bullshit/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bullshit on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 21:22:43 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/bullshit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Accessing knowledge through past theories</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/past-theories-and-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 21:22:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/past-theories-and-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You raise the question whether using earlier theories, which are &lt;em&gt;superseded&lt;/em&gt; by newer theories, one can (or even could ever) access knowledge? (I am not a physicist, but I do not think that physicists have junked Newtonian theories. I think that Newtonian physics retains its validity in the macroworld we live in and is not considered false. As far as I remember, I have not come across writings that claim that Newton’s theory is false but that most of its consequences (but not all) are derivable in Einsteinian theory, under some ‘limiting conditions’ (like mass remaining invariant, etc.) Anyway, I do not know enough Physics to enter a discussion about it. Arun and Kannan are more competent here than I am.) If we do not get stuck on any one example, it appears to me that there are three questions here: (a) Could defective, incomplete, partial theories help us access knowledge?; (b) Could false, or partially false and partially true, theories help us access knowledge?; (c) Was knowledge ever accessed by past theories, which, as we know today, expressed ignorance?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Para vs. Apara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/para-vs-apara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 23:22:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/para-vs-apara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: I have some problems understanding &lt;em&gt;apara, para, existence, and presence&lt;/em&gt;. Apara exists, but is not present; para is present but does not exist. Are you saying that what is present does not exist, what exists is not present? If so, how can you reconcile with our common sense notion that what exists is present?  Even though presence doesn’t imply existence, we can’t say that existence imply non-presence. So, this is an issue of definitional equivalence: para = presence; apara = existence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tattvadarshi, Gyaani, and Bullshitter</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 22:07:10 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us agree on the proposed division into two categories: “1) That which exists or could exist (2) That which could not and does not exist but is present (therefore ‘Real’)”. Let us also accept that (1) collects: “(a) everything that we know like Earth, stars, mud, (b) everything that we can think of or imagine - models, formulas, triangles, present and future scientific theories, tooth fairies, ‘murtis’ of Ganesha, methods or procedures of performing ‘abhisheka’ etc. (these exist and could exist in our minds, even the ‘Real’ we imagine still belongs here as long as it is an imagined object)”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knowledge and Bullshit about Daffodil</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shock-and-awe-of-enlightenment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 15:38:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shock-and-awe-of-enlightenment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To help you think through the problem you &amp;ldquo;whether Christians can get enlightened&amp;rdquo;, try using this analogy. Something, let us call it ‘daffodil’, fascinates us. Let us also assume that a great deal of concern and interest is expressed about it. Consider two scenarios now, each of which testifies to our fascination.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first scenario is this. There is versification (call it ‘poetry’) and ‘embodiment’ (paintings and sculptures) of ‘daffodil’; imaginative eulogies (novels) and intimidating discourses (‘philosophy’) about ‘daffodil’ abound, etc. These classifications are based on our understanding of what art, poetry, philosophy etc. are. There are also many collations of fragmentary sentences that appear to violate metres of poetry or styles of prose. They are revered as revolutionary breakthroughs (made by the heroes of the ‘masses’ transgressing such elitist notions like ‘grammar’, ‘style’, etc.) that are ‘blinding in their beauty’. In short, there is a huge collection of material about ‘daffodil’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Enlightenment</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 15:31:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post will use an imagery as its organising thread, which tracks the search for enlightenment in terms of notions known to us from our secondary and higher education.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If we consider the search for happiness in these terms, then the ideas expressed &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/&#34;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/strong&gt; could be reformulated thus: as human beings, almost all of us would like to be literates or would like to have a primary education. This is the move ‘away’ for unhappiness that all of us aim at, namely, to be ‘less unhappy’. After a period of time, many of us would like to move further. This is the move ‘towards’ (peace of mind, contentment, satisfied, etc.) happiness now formulated in positive terms: the phase of secondary education. The completion of this process is to reach a state of peace (shanti), or contentment (samadhana), or satisfaction (trupti) etc. The Sri Sri’s and the Sadguru’s of this world help us here through their Sudarshan Kriya’s, their yogic practices, their meditative courses and so on. The vipassana meditation, the Satsangh’s, the bhajans, the dhyaanas etc. are also situated here. Some people in this phase also call themselves Saadhakas, doing their ‘saadhana’ on a very regular basis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you want to go further and, therefore, seek higher education (call it Ananda, or happiness). There are two broad routes here: technical or vocational education is one route; university education is another. If you want to be plumber, a carpenter, a sculptor, a painter, a machinist…then you are better-off choosing technical education. However, you could also go for a university education. There is no ‘higher’ or ‘lower’ here; both are different forms of higher education. (Of course, there are endless discussions about ‘superiority’: one group disparagingly calls the other ‘vocational training’, while the other caricatures the first as ‘purely theoretical’ that is unsuited for fulfilling the ‘need’ for useful education or the ‘needs’ of society.) A society cannot survive without plumbers, electricians, machinists, artists, etc. Nor can it live without the ‘ivory tower’ that universities are and should be. Individual students make their choice based on multiple reasons (from aptitude to financial rewards) and many gifted teachers prefer to teach in vocational or professional schools than in a university. However, whatever the choice, both demand that the student specifies clearly what s/he wants to learn: do you want to be a sculptor or a machinist; in which subject do you want  your bachelor and Master’s degree? ‘Ananda’, the generic word, does not suffice here because it merely picks out ‘higher education’: do you want to do physics or chemistry or biology or English literature at the university? ‘Gyaana marga’ (the university) on the one hand and ‘other routes’ (vocational and professional training) on the other hand are the main avenues in higher education.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of this imagery, ‘enlightenment’ refers to the total process of ‘higher education’ and ‘seeking ananda’ fixes the goal of higher education. Each avenue has its way of classifying its internal levels or divisions (Bachelors, Masters, Doctoral, Post-doctoral in the university, for example) and teaches students accordingly. They share many commonalities: the subject matter, the instruments, the theoretical frameworks, etc. etc. They are also different from each other in ways of teaching, investigating, making and reporting discoveries, and so on. The names of some teachers in higher education are known to us: Buddha, Shankara, Ramanuja, Madhva, Vallabha, Ramakrishna Paramahamsa, Ramana, Nisargadatta Maharaj, etc. Let us not deal with the question whether they taught at the University or were active in professional or technical education because something else of greater importance has to be noticed: you have to choose the ‘subject’ of higher education first. ‘Seeking Happiness’ or ‘wanting enlightenment’ are not adequate at all. You need to specifiy what you are seeking and, preferably, why.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is every description knowledge?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-every-description-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 08:10:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-every-description-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us call the descriptions of what you see &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo;. Are your &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; a contribution to human knowledge? In one sense they are; the way any description of anything by anybody is a &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; and thus knowledge. One needs, and one has, a way of not wanting to call every piece of &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; as knowledge. Hence, we can reformulate the issue: does it contribute towards building a scientific theory of cultural differences? Do your observations in some African country tell us what &lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; their drinking habits and body decorations into a cultural difference? And how these and other differences allow us to say what the &amp;lsquo;African culture&amp;rsquo; is? In other words, not every fact, because it is a fact about people from another culture, is interesting from the point of view of building a scientific theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about people and their cultures?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:53:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us begin in a very intuitive way and ask ourselves this question: where do we encounter &amp;lsquo;cultural differences&amp;rsquo;? In human contacts, of course. What kind of human contacts? &lt;em&gt;In inter-individual contacts&lt;/em&gt;. That is, we see (or sense, or intuit or whatever) cultural differences in our contacts with &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; human beings. You do not meet &amp;rsquo;the western culture&amp;rsquo; but individual Americans, Germans, French, etc. Neither do these individuals meet &amp;rsquo;the Indian culture&amp;rsquo;: they meet individual Indians (or, even better, a &amp;lsquo;Madrasi Brahmin&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;lsquo;Gujerati Baniya&amp;rsquo; - even these are general categories but I use them just to get the point across.) And yet, we appear to see cultural differences in these contacts. How to make &amp;lsquo;sense&amp;rsquo; of &lt;em&gt;this experience&lt;/em&gt;? Let us first see what is partially involved to truly appreciate the complexity of our &amp;lsquo;perception&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Each individual human being is a complex combination of at least four aspects. There is his biological (or genetic) inheritance; there is his &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; inheritance (whether he is from the Middle Ages or from a capitalist society); there is his psychological makeup (let us say his &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;); and there is his cultural upbringing (whether he is a Madhva Brahmin or a Lingayat, say). When we meet individuals, in many different ways we notice these &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt;: the biological, the psychological and, after some time perhaps, &amp;rsquo;the social&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the cultural&amp;rsquo;. Let us bracket the biological away so that the situation becomes deliciously complex. Let us agree to use the following &amp;lsquo;words&amp;rsquo; (they are just words for now) in order to go ahead and raise the problem. Let us call the &amp;lsquo;social aspects&amp;rsquo; of a person the &amp;lsquo;sociality&amp;rsquo; of the person; the psychological aspects the &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo; of the person; and the &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; aspects the &amp;lsquo;culturality&amp;rsquo; of the person. Thus we meet individual human beings and see the differences between ourselves and the other human beings. What kinds of differences do we see?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
