<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Concept(category) on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/conceptcategory/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concept(category) on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 00:42:15 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/conceptcategory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Translation, Interpretation and Culture: On the disingenuity of a comparative theology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 00:42:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balu&amp;rsquo;s paper on comparative theology, and in particular Francis Clooney&amp;rsquo;s:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/5497443/On_the_Disingenuity_of_a_Comparative_Theology&#34;&gt;Translation, interpretration and culture: on the disingenuity of a comparative theology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercultural exchange of categories</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 19:42:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is wrong with the intercultural exchange of categories? Throughout one gets the impression that there is something “fundamentally wrong” with categories shifting in meaning over time or with the introduction of categories from one culture into another culture. But what is important about these shifts in meaning? What exactly is the problem in introducing the category of religion into India or among Native Americans? The category “yuppie” did not exist in the Middle Ages, while “orange” came through Arabic from Sanskrit, and “girl” used to refer to a young person of either sex. When we analyse the genetics of early modern populations, we are also introducing categories that they did not possess. Or take the word “silly,” which in Old English used to mean blessed. So what? An historical analysis of discourse and categories is significant not to identify shifts in meaning per se. Shifts in meaning become significant only against the background of a theory on the historical development of the western culture and its understanding of other cultures. Such a theory is needed to clarify as to why a shift in the meaning of “religion” or “the secular” is of crucial importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Theoretical Dispute: electron, dharma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 23:12:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translation-meaning-concepts-electron-dharma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our daily life, we hardly pause to reflect upon many problematic things that we routinely assume as self-evident. Such an attitude is useful since it allows us to focus on other things that occupy us at that moment. One such attitude is not to bestow too much care on how we use language: we routinely speak of similarity in meaning, identical concepts, exact and accurate translations and so on. As long as issues like meaning etc. are not at dispute, talking like this causes no harm. However, in the current case, we are talking about the meaning of &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; (in a manner of speaking). Consequently, we have to be careful about how we use language to convey what we want to say, and be clear about what thesis we intend to argue for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Sanskrit Concepts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 05:13:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many are concerned that English translations of some words from native languages distort their meaning. If we restrict ourselves to terms like &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Dharma&amp;rsquo; and such like, the worry is not just that their translations distort the meaning of these words (as we use them in our native languages) but that they suggest something (by way of reference and meaning) that does not even exist in these languages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With respect to some of these words, we can build a reasonable case in defense of this stance. That is because there is at least some theory about religion that we accept (however provisional or conditional such an acceptance might be) using which we can show that &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo; cannot be translated as &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo;. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Indian reformers understood Protestant Reformation?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-indian-intellectuals-understood-protestant-reformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 03:42:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-indian-intellectuals-understood-protestant-reformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the second half of the nineteenth century, some western-educated, Bombay intellectuals came together in the Prarthana Samaj (inspired by Keshub Sunder Sen of the Brahmo Samaj). Perhaps the best known members of the Prarthana Samaj were Mahadev Govind Ranada and Narayan Chandavarkar (the Vice-Chancellor of Bombay University). Both reformers advocated what they literally called &lt;em&gt;Hindu Protestantism&lt;/em&gt;. Below, I will present what I believe to be illustrations of the distortion that occurs when these intellectuals talk about reform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bankruptcy of postcolonial intellectuals and their defense of secularism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/bankruptcy-of-postcolonial-intellectuals-and-their-defense-of-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:47:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/bankruptcy-of-postcolonial-intellectuals-and-their-defense-of-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have developed partial explanations of why the secularism debate in India takes such peculiar forms and why otherwise intelligent people talk nonsense here. But we don&amp;rsquo;t do so by pegging our use of the word secularism &amp;ldquo;onto Balu&amp;rsquo;s theory about the nature of religion and how that entity religion behaves in the world&amp;rdquo; and then expecting that other people do the same.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let me quickly repeat our argument: Concepts like religion and secularism and principles of the secular state developed in Europe against the background of larger conceptual frameworks. Broadly speaking, one knew what &lt;code&gt;religion&#39; and &#39;the secular state&#39; referred to or what the separation of &lt;/code&gt;the religious&amp;rsquo; and `the political&amp;rsquo; amounted to, because these terms were embedded in such a common background framework. Naturally, there were many different positions and discontinuities in the debates. But disagreements about the precise meaning of terms or clashes between conflicting normative positions made sense to the participants, precisely because they occurred against the background of this type of framework. The framework put semantic limits on the potential interpretation of terms and principles, as it related concepts to each other in particular systematic ways. This background framework reflects not only generic Christian theology and political theory, but also the common cultural and historical experience of Europeans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fallacy of Equivocation: Indian Secularism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fallacy-of-equivocation-indian-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 23:03:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fallacy-of-equivocation-indian-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading Shabnum Tejani&amp;rsquo;s *Indian Secularism: A Social and Intellectual History (*2008), I ran into the same weird point that Neera Chandhoke also tried to make at the RRI platform debate on secularism. This is a combination of the old claim that &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; has acquired a different meaning in India and a general theoretical point: &amp;lsquo;secularism does not have any essence or universal meaning, but gets different meanings dependent on the historical and cultural contexts in which it has developed&amp;rsquo;. There are different variations on this formulation, but the general point is one that is becoming increasingly popular (especially among historians), because of the influence of Talal Asad and other postmodernators. Hence, I wanted to try and address the point by taking the example of Tejani&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why use Indic categories to describe the world?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-use-indic-categories-to-describe-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 22:38:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-use-indic-categories-to-describe-the-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The issue is simply this: why use Indic categories to describe the world? What is interesting or important about this goal or venture? This, as I said, is the issue but we need to do some amount of thinking before we can identify the real question. That is so because there is a lot of deadwood floating around that makes navigation difficult. So, let me begin the process of clearing some of the debris.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuss about Indic categories II</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categories-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 22:14:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categories-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Social psychology, for instance, speaks of &amp;lsquo;categorization theory&amp;rsquo;, and we do use &amp;lsquo;categorization&amp;rsquo; also in the sense of classification. However, unless one gives a technical meaning to &amp;lsquo;category&amp;rsquo; (which one can), these usages do not violate the primary distinction between a word from some natural language and its meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider a classificatory scheme, say, cubes. Here, &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; is a word, it has some meaning, and we classify (let us say) some objects together. That is, we say that some objects can be categorized as cubes. However, by saying this we do not mean that some objects (say some coloured, and some wooden objects) are instances of the English word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;. (Assume that we are teaching English to someone who does not know that language. When we classify some objects and teach him the word, we are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; teaching him how the word is written, what the constituent alphabets of that word are but its meaning. Now he understands the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;.) What we mean is that each of these objects is an instance of the category &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; (i.e. the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;). Even here, we do not mean that the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;= some physical object. (That is, we do not suggest that &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; looks like a physical object. The physical object is not an embodiment of the meaning of a word.) What we mean is that the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; allows us to bring descriptions of some other objects together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuss about Indic categories(concepts) I</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categoriesconcepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 21:21:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categoriesconcepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me give the gist of the consensus and overlook philosophical nuances about categories.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following sentences: &amp;lsquo;It is raining&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;het regent&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Es Regnet&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Baarish aa raha hai&amp;rsquo;. All these sentences have the same meaning, namely that it is raining. Or it could also be said that they all express the same &amp;ldquo;proposition&amp;rdquo;. So, &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;proposition&amp;rdquo; are used as quasi-synonyms; and sentences from natural languages have meaning or express propositions. Another synonym to &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; would be the &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; of a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 07:56:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; Consider the thought that &amp;lsquo;meanings&amp;rsquo; (leave aside the distinction between words and sentences on the one hand and concepts and categories on the other) do not exist outside historical contexts. What exactly does this thought say? Begin with &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;. Either every situation that an individual human being finds himself is a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; (because human beings are always &amp;lsquo;in a context&amp;rsquo; and these contexts always occur &amp;lsquo;in history&amp;rsquo;) or there is a difference between &amp;rsquo; a context&amp;rsquo; and a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;.  She cannot possibly make the latter of the two claims because if the meaning of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; changes only in &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo; but not in &amp;lsquo;other kinds of contexts&amp;rsquo;, it follows that &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; has a stable meaning in other contexts than  &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo;, which she would want to deny. So, for the sake of consistency, we have to assume that &amp;lsquo;context&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; are synonyms. Then, the thought is that meaning varies according to contexts. Consider the word &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo;: the only way I can imagine that the meaning of this word varies according to individual contexts is the following: to one, it means a &amp;rsquo;life saver&amp;rsquo;; to the other &amp;lsquo;fattening&amp;rsquo; and to the third &amp;lsquo;sweet&amp;rsquo; and so on. (In fact, to one and the same individual &amp;lsquo;ice cream&amp;rsquo; could &amp;ldquo;mean different things&amp;rdquo; at different points in time: what ice-cream meant  when one was 3 years need indeed not be the same as what it means when one is 50 and suffers from Diabetes and obesity.) So far so good. But the problem is this: these different meanings of &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; presuppose that we are talking about the same thing. Only under this condition can we say that &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; means different things to different people (or to the same person at different times).  To talk about the same thing, ice-cream, we need a reference for that word and, in many cases (like secularism and communalism, for example) it is a &amp;rsquo;linguistic description&amp;rsquo; of that word (a &amp;lsquo;definition&amp;rsquo;, or its &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo;) that provides us with reference. (In the case of ice-cream, one might use gestures to point out an ice-cream; you cannot do that for &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;communalism&amp;rsquo;.) In other words, the ONLY possible way for secularism to have multiple meanings in multiple historical contexts is by having a meaning that is INDEPENDENT of contexts. (Or having a meaning that is common across all POSSIBLE contexts.) In other words, when Neera or Shabnum or anyone else makes the claim that meanings do not transcend contexts either (a) they are making the trivial point that every word uttered by any human being always takes place in a context (which no one had ever denied) or (b) by saying that meaning is totally context bound they are contradicting themselves. Of course, to notice that one is inconsistent, one needs to think according to the rules of grammar and rules of logic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
