<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Neutral on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/neutral/</link><description>Recent content in Neutral on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:30:09 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/neutral/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is the distinction between ‘secular’and ‘religious’ neutral? –S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:30:09 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The question appears to be: need one accept certain premises of Christianity (whether Protestant or Catholic varieties) in order that the dominant understanding of, say, the secular state and the caste to make sense? That those to whom such accounts make sense do not explicitly subscribe to the premises of a specific religious appears to throw doubt on our claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the very distinction between &amp;rsquo;the religious&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the secular&amp;rsquo;. Historically, Christianity has drawn this line. (Theologians have spent much ink over the last two thousand years drawing, defending, and elaborating upon this distinction.) It is also the case that political thinkers in the West, some of whom were militantly atheistic, have made this distinction into a cornerstone of their theories. Further, many Indian thinkers, most of whom know very little of Christian theologies, base their arguments on these and allied distinctions. The existence of the last two groups appears to tell us that even when one rejects some or all religions, even when one is utterly oblivious to the histories and theologies of the Christianities, this distinction does make sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>