<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Westology on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/westology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Westology on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:25:05 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/westology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Westology and its nonsense</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/westology-and-its-nonsense/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:25:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/westology-and-its-nonsense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is the logic of &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/&#34;&gt;my argument&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;? Am I proposing a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo;? Let me briefly explicate my stances, beginning with the last question.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If we are not to simply sell slogans and our claims should carry bite, we need to say what this &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; is or could be. My stance: such a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; cannot even be properly conceptualized, let alone carried out.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. What does it mean (however intuitively plausible it might appear at first sight) to build a &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; that is, say, an Indian counterpart to &amp;lsquo;indology&amp;rsquo;? Are we to assume that we need to build &lt;em&gt;Indian&lt;/em&gt; theories of &amp;lsquo;democracy&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;state&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;market&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;firm&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;society&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; and such like? If the answer is &amp;rsquo;no&amp;rsquo;, then the notion of &amp;lsquo;westology&amp;rsquo; does not make sense. Therefore, the answer has to be &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why ‘Westology’ ala Indology doomed to fail?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-westology-ala-indology-doomed-to-fail-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 07:51:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-westology-ala-indology-doomed-to-fail-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The inherent logic of such an enterprise forces one, as it were, to build &lt;em&gt;alternate&lt;/em&gt; theories to the existing, &amp;lsquo;western&amp;rsquo; theories. Instead of explaining this statement in the abstract, let me take a concrete example to illustrate what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.2. In the University of Chicago, there is a certain Richard Shweder. He practices &amp;lsquo;Cultural Psychology&amp;rsquo;, and is (was?) professor of &amp;lsquo;Human Development&amp;rsquo;. He is rather well-known for his &amp;lsquo;cross-cultural&amp;rsquo; studies: he and his students have published many works comparing psychological developments across the two cultures that India and America are. (In fact, he received a medal from the American Association of the Advancement of Science, if I remember properly, for one of his articles: &amp;lsquo;Does the concept of the Person vary cross-culturally?&amp;rsquo; This was a study about the concept of &amp;lsquo;self&amp;rsquo; in the USA and Orissa, India.) A few years ago, he published a study on the nature of &lt;em&gt;moral development&lt;/em&gt; and the growth of moral awareness cross-culturally: again, India and the USA were the two compared cultures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
