<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Normative on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/normative/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Normative on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 09:21:28 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/normative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to understand corruption?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 09:21:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us take the word ‘duty’ for the moment. Conflict in duties does not give you a moral dilemma. For a moral dilemma to occur two necessary conditions must exist: the prescribed set of duties must be logically consistent by virtue of which one is obliged to perform them all.  A dilemma pertains to a situation where one has an obligation to do A and an obligation to do B; but can in fact do only one. It is the perfect consistency of the system of duty that gives rise to the dilemma: a choice between A and B, between a banana and an orange is not a dilemma. It becomes a dilemma when you want both and can have only one. So, a moral dilemma cannot possibly describe a conflict of duties if one uses the word ‘duty’ here.  A conflict of &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; is not a dilemma at all.&#xA;What I mean by decolonizing social Sciences is very simple thing. There are many domains today: sociology, political science, psychology, and anthropology that call themselves social sciences as distinct from humanities. So, I am not talking about decolonizing science in the specific sense given by Mohini Mullick. I do not consider the theories in these domains which call themselves social sciences to be science at all. Today, I see all of them without exception as ideologies. I call my project ‘Comparative Science of Culture’ because existing theories are not social sciences.&#xA;For instance: political corruption refers to the act of an individual public servant who is part of a state or a government and who acts against the public interest of the people or the interest of the state. Because state has an interest which coincides with the interest of the society, then any action that supports an individual’s interest is morally wrong. This is the meaning of political corruption.&#xA;I am very conservative. I want a scientific hypothesis in the sense that it solves a problem, has an explanatory potential and there is some way to test it. In this sense, political theory is completely bankrupt. I proffer two hypotheses which at least minimally do what you expect a hypothesis to do.&#xA;The first is purely historical in nature. You raised a question about the moral evaluations which comes from a completely Western ethics and is not Indian at all. We in India had our own forms of social organization. We had certain indigenous ways of governing, of organizing production. But with colonization came industrialization, bringing with it management institutions from the West; structures were imposed on native Indian industries, on native structures, which today are taught in MBA courses all over India. The result is institutional distortion, so that you come across extraordinary things that baffle management theorists.&#xA;More concretely: how were questions asked about tradition? Can we use the resources of our ancient Indian literature to tackle and explain this problem? I find the Indian tradition powerful because it can help generate scientific hypotheses beyond the reach of Western social scientists. That’s why I am against the latter, not because they are Western. I am not against everything Western: Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics, Biology come from the Western tradition.&#xA;(pp 206-8 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truth, belief, intentionality, eudaimonia, ought</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:15:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to respond to three of your points Claus. First you are not talking only about the Greeks and the Romans because all the problems arising with respect to the phenomena of non-Western societies and culture are/were equally the problems in the frameworks of different varieties of culture. You not only talk about the Greeks and the Romans, you gave examples about the French and the English as well.&#xA;The second point is: you talk about the fact that people face the same problem in Europe of today when they talk about the Greeks and the Romans. You are absolutely right. But that confirms my point, namely, that the Greeks and the Romans had no religion. They were Pagan cultures and this is exactly the problem with India. The Christian culture doesn’t understand Greek — the whole of Heidegger’s philosophy is an example of that. He says we cannot think Greek. And his whole attempt to speak about what thinking is, what truth is, etc. — is an attempt to rescue the Greek language from what he called the Christianization of Latin. I am aware that contemporary European languages and modern Europe do have problems with the Greeks and Romans. But just because of the fact that Ancient Greece and Rome are located in the Western hemisphere does not make them part of Western culture. In an earlier publication, I showed that neither Greece nor Rome were cradles of Western civilization. Western Civilization is Christian Civilization, although you might not agree with that. Greece and Rome do not belong to it. That is why we Indians can understand them. Let me give you a small example — One of the most fundamental notions of Aristotle is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, which gets translated with great difficulty as ‘well-being’, ‘feeling good’, ‘happiness’ and so on. It is a very difficult word to translate. This is not merely a translation problem because I have had discussions with Greek scholars. Aristotle asks: what is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;? It is very difficult to achieve of course but he says once you have it you cannot lose it. I told a Greek Specialist once ‘you know nothing about Greek language’, He responded: ‘how dare you say that’! So, I said: ‘here is a simple thing, forget the translation of &lt;em&gt;eudaimoni&lt;/em&gt;a, give me one example of a human  property which once you possess, you do not lose.’ I said: ‘I do not have to understand Greek to understand what &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; means.’ And of course to this day, no Greek scholar could help me in giving one example of one human property which if once you possess you do not lose&amp;ndash;this is a fundamental property of &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;. For the Indians here is my answer. &lt;em&gt;Eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;aananda.&lt;/em&gt; Once you have &lt;em&gt;aananda&lt;/em&gt; you do not lose it. It is equivalent in some conditions to &lt;em&gt;brahma-gyaana.&lt;/em&gt; And that is happiness indeed, beyond &lt;em&gt;sukha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;duhkha&lt;/em&gt;. So when Aristotle is talking about &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; I understand him and I read him carefully. Of course, there is no translation equivalent of eudaimonia in any of the European languages but that is because they have no access to that world, that conceptual framework like we Indians have. So indeed, I understand you have a problem with Greece and Rome: we understand them much better.&#xA;Two other points &amp;ndash; one on Galileo. I am not conflating the community of Christians with a community of non-Christians because one of the claims I have substantiated to which in the last fifteen years I have found no counter argument, is the following: My claim is that free thinkers and atheists, even the Communists of Europe, are actually disguised theists. That is to say that Christianity has secularized itself in political theory, in social theory, in rational choice theory; a number of theories. I can show you how assumptions from the Bible have taken secular forms. So by saying for instance, ‘look I don’t have a religious background’, it makes no difference. I know people, who do not have a religious background for generations, are atheists but they continue to have the same excuse for speaking as Christians do. For example, your ethics will be absolutely no different from Christian ethics because there is no such thing as non-Christian secular ethics present today. ‘You ought not to kill’. Don’t tell me that is an example of secular ethics. Even the notion of ‘ought not’, the normative notion itself, does not come from English: it comes from Christianity, from the Bible.&#xA;Aristotle, for example, does not have an ‘ought’. Indian languages do not have a ‘moral ought’ nor do the Chinese in their language in which Confucius wrote. These are not linguistic issues, Claus, these are problems of conceptual apparatuses that are culturally developed. So, it is in that sense that I speak about Galileo and say he made sense to the Europeans. They used his findings to investigate nature because they believed fundamentally that nature has a structure and pattern and a law which has to be discovered by human investigation. They would say that without such a structure the universe should be chaos. The whole of 2,000 years of European culture believes that, and that was Galileo’s idea as well. It is a background belief, of course, but it is a background belief of that culture and we are talking about difference between cultures. Translation is always a translation between people who use sentences, who use natural languages. So, I am shifting the level of the problem.&#xA;Last point, there is something to be said for your claim regarding the notion of belief&amp;ndash;that you can have a concept, but do not have a word&amp;ndash;that is absolutely true. That is our daily experience. I feel like saying something but I don’t know how to say it. So, you can have some sense of a concept but defined psychologically not linguistically or so cognitively. I do not know how to put it in a natural sentence. Right. But you are making out of it logical and philosophical points.&#xA;Let me put it very sharply. The notion of having a belief and the belief is always about something; this is a specific conception of man, of human beings&amp;ndash;there is philosophical anthropology which attributes some notion of intention to human beings. One of the extraordinary things about the Indian tradition is the absence of this notion of intentionality:  &lt;em&gt;agyana&lt;/em&gt;. They call it &lt;em&gt;maaya&lt;/em&gt; and many different things. So the nature of human being in the Indian tradition is that we are non-intentional creatures, which is completely incomprehensible within the framework of Christian culture. So, entertaining having a belief is not a linguistic, psychological, epistemological fact which is applicable to all human beings but is a specific assumption about the nature of human beings that comes from the Bible. So when saying that Indians have beliefs, you are not making use of any understanding of language – you are making use of a religious concept/understanding of man and saying that is what Indians have. Of course, you can say that; people have been saying that for 500 years. That is not the issue.&#xA;The issue is: is this how Indians understand themselves? In fact, if you look at the languages you find there is greater affinity when you talk of using work-words. They do not say ‘I got angry’ but ‘anger came upon me’ &amp;ndash; this is a very typical old classical Greek way of talking. ‘Why did you say that?’ ‘I do not know, my tongue moved that way’. I am literally translating local Indian languages into English&amp;ndash;this is the way we talk. In fact, even the subject notion, is not simply a linguistic subject or verb subject in action, the fundamental ontological notion of subject itself is missing in India as also the notion of agency.&#xA;Take the problem about truth: the notion of truth for applying to sentences, to propositions by some other philosophers is a very philosophical disease. If you look at the middle-ages, take Aquinas for example, he had two notions of truth: &lt;em&gt;adeequatio re&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;. One is which is adequate to the object; the other which is adequate to thoughts. Hegel used the same notion. Tarski also says there are multiple notions of truth. That notion of truth — &lt;em&gt;adaquatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt; as it prevailed for 1,900 years in Western culture referred to the fact that objects are adequate to how God conceives them. That is &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;adequate not to human intellects, to God’s intellect. &lt;em&gt;Adequatio re&lt;/em&gt; had to do with how one related the word to both these notions and emerged, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; from any understanding of language, truth, philosophy, or logic, it arose from commenting on theologies and commenting the Bible.  (pp 162-166 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of &#39;Supererogation&#39;</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolution-of-supererogation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 16:56:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolution-of-supererogation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is advisable to get into a discussion about this question only after one knows what ‘supererogation’ means and how it has been discussed for centuries.  In the Greek ethics (especially as Aristotle formulated it), the notion plays a very crucial role without it being related to a normative sense of duty. With the Catholics, especially as Aquinas gave expression to it, a normative notion of duty cohabits the moral universe together with supererogation. To the Protestants, it makes sense to speak only of duty and not of supererogation because the latter does not simply exist. Without understanding the issues involved in these controversies, to make a bald assertion about supererogation (while appealing to a Protestant commonsense idea of duty without even realizing its Protestant origin) is to “…rush in, where Angels fear to tread”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real and Practical Uses of Normative Ethics</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/real-and-practical-use-of-normative-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 16:58:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/real-and-practical-use-of-normative-ethics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When you provide a moral criticism of someone, you are saying that such a person is morally wrong. If you bracket, for a moment, my writings and talks on the subject, then you see that no moral criticisms are possible without using a normative language.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About realizing moral ideals: do you know any way of showing how some or another event in the world is not an &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; realization of the relevant moral ideal? In fact, a reasonably capable intellectual acrobat could show that Nazism or Idi Amin&amp;rsquo;s Uganda were merely &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; moral realizations of United Nations Declaration of Human Rights or that they did &amp;lsquo;realize&amp;rsquo; the moral ideals albeit in an &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; manner. The problem is this: we cannot put limiting conditions on the degrees of imperfection unless one compares. Even that is quite problematic: is the US, with the NSA surveillance of its citizens, less or more &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; than France, which very recently demanded the introduction of fingerprinting (and other biometric identifications ) for EU citizens traveling within the EU countries?  With the vast array of CCTV&amp;rsquo;s monitoring its streets, is UK, previously the home of Locke and Mill, any less or any more the &amp;rsquo;land of freedom&amp;rsquo; it was and is alleged to be? Is it an &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; realization or a severe deformation of the relevant moral ideals?  The only real and practical use of the normative ethical theories appear to be: justify any immoral behavior as an &amp;lsquo;imperfect&amp;rsquo; realization of a noble moral ideal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principle of Charity and Normativity</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity-and-normativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 12:38:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity-and-normativity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This one begins to reflect about the principle of charity in relationship to the current US President, Donald Trump (from now on, Trump).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As you might know, the principle of charity has been formulated in different ways by different people. (Even the first page of a google search of the word ‘principle of charity’ allows you to access many of these documents quickly.) This post will stick strictly to your formulation: “a principle of charity says that (like the rain dance) a long-standing  practice should not be attributed to idiocy without strong evidence”. This formulation itself will not be questioned but assumed as a given. The only evidence used in this post is an extremely fragmentary viewing of the CNN and the BBC World coverages of Trump during the last week or so. (No thorough viewing of either of the two channels is claimed; the references in this post merely pick out fragments from programs as memory ‘recalls’ them today.) Two dramatis personae: Some media coverage and the event of Trump presidency; one question: what does the principle of charity do or advocate in the following cases? Such cases can be indefinitely multiplied but it is restricted here to five. One side of the argument is presented briefly only because that side of the argument is in wide circulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is humility a virtue?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-humility-a-virtue/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 21:37:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-humility-a-virtue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First: there is nothing morally wrong in posting an opinion. My problem is that (a) it occurs within the context of generating and criticising knowledge; (b) its cognitive value is either zero or negative; (c) it is presented as though thoughtless opinions (almost all opinions are thoughtless) form a counterpoint to knowledge or are themselves candidates for knowledge (the latter are the hypotheses); (d) one acts as though the fact that opinions could have some moral value (because a human being expresses them) is sufficient to make them cognitively worthy; (e) cognitive nonsense is provided with a foundation in Christian (and Semitic) religious value (like ‘IMHO’, ‘humility’ for example), which is itself placed beyond discussion as though its importance is universally recognized; (Neither the Ancient Pagans nor the Asian traditions consider ‘humility’ a moral virtue. It is immoral to these traditions because it is seen as dissimulation and deception.); and so on. There is place on this forum for dissent, disagreement and criticism, but their foundation is not moral but cognitive. I do not tolerate opinions on this board, but I am willing to think about any hypothesis that appears reasonable. I will respond to misunderstandings, queries and criticisms. However, those who find my reactions (to their ‘humble opinions’) offensive should leave this group.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Saint, The Criminal and The Terrorist—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:10:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the phenomenon of terrorism has begun to occupy the media, politics, and the lives of people in different parts of the world. The more the attention, however, the less the clarity: what kind of a phenomenon is terrorism? What generates it, what sustains it, and what allows it to expand on an ever-increasing scale?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lack of clarity has to do with the fact that our ideas about terrorism appear as an incoherent set. First, terrorism horrifies most of us; the acts of terrorists are seen as monstrous in scope and size. But the number of deaths or the human suffering, even if we look at an event as momentous as 9/11, is dwarfed by what traffic accidents and smoking do in any given year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ought one to be generous?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-one-to-be-generous/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:46:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-one-to-be-generous/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is ethics in India, but it is not normative ethics. It is a non-normative ethics. To get you going, consider acts like &amp;lsquo;generosity&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;kindness&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;bravery&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;friendliness&amp;rsquo; and such like. Often called &amp;lsquo;virtues&amp;rsquo;, these actions do not come under the scope of normative ethics. You cannot say: &amp;ldquo;one ought to be generous&amp;rdquo;, because generosity implies doing &amp;lsquo;more than&amp;rsquo; what is expected in the act of giving. Such notions are also called &amp;lsquo;supererogatory&amp;rsquo; in the literature, i.e. they are &amp;lsquo;over and beyond the call of duty&amp;rsquo;. This is one way to start coming to grips with the idea of non-normative ethics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is ethical about pursuit of happiness (Ananda)</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-ethical-about-pursuit-of-happiness-ananda/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 22:09:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-ethical-about-pursuit-of-happiness-ananda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is what I say in my article on &amp;lsquo;how to speak for the Indian traditions&amp;rsquo;: &amp;ldquo;Our middle-aged man is, thus, raising the question of Aristotle.&amp;ldquo;I have pursued many things in life. I have acquired wealth and status, and aimed with varying degrees of success to become powerful and famous. I have been successful in some of my endeavors, while failing in yet others. I thought these things would make me happy, but I discover that, apart from moments when I felt &amp;lsquo;good&amp;rsquo;, these projects have only made me unhappy. What should I do? How should I live?&amp;rdquo; Today, these questions are not a part of ethical enquiry, any more than a quest for eudemonia is: at best, these are the &amp;rsquo;esoteric&amp;rsquo; questions and quests of &amp;rsquo;exotic&amp;rsquo; religions; at worst, one raises them with one&amp;rsquo;s psychoanalyst during a &amp;lsquo;mid-life crisis&amp;rsquo;. This situation should already indicate the distance between what is called an &amp;rsquo;ethical enquiry&amp;rsquo; today, and what Aristotle thought was the subject of all such enquiries. But that is not the focus of this piece now. However, there is no need to confuse matters by continually drawing the distinction between &amp;lsquo;modern&amp;rsquo; ethics and &amp;lsquo;Aristotelian&amp;rsquo; ethics. So, let us follow the contemporary consensus and call the quest of our middle-aged man &amp;lsquo;spiritual&amp;rsquo; (from now on without scare quotes). Seeking spirituality, and not having found it in those objects that he once so passionately pursued, he is now raising a spiritual question: in fact, he is undergoing a spiritual crisis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Justice belong to ethical domain?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-justice-belong-to-ethical-domain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 21:45:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-justice-belong-to-ethical-domain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In &amp;ldquo;An Enquiry Concerning the Principles of Morals&amp;rdquo;, David Hume, the philosopher of the Scottish Enlightenment, raises a question, which has always been one of the basic concerns of ethical investigations in the modern western intellectual tradition: what theory of morals could serve any useful purpose, he asks, unless it can be shown that all the duties it recommends are also in the true interest of each individual? Even though there are several interesting things about this question, I will just indicate two of them. Firstly, the belief is that an individual requires reasons to behave morally which is what a theory of morals is supposed to provide. Secondly, he requires reasons to be moral because moral rules constrain his actions. Since it is rational that each individual pursues his &amp;lsquo;own&amp;rsquo; interests, any constraint placed on his behavior requires some kind of justification. Together, these two assumptions yield us the better-known question in ethical theorizing: is it rational to be moral? Or, more imply put in terms of an even older question: why ought we to be moral?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ever since the German Romantics, another thought, which reverses the above question, is also a part of the modern-day consciousness: is it moral to be rational? However, the elaboration of this question is not only implicit but it is also confined mostly to a criticism of local rationalities: the economic rationality, the technological rationality, the scientific rationality, the rationality of progress, etc. The reversal is only implicit and the criticisms only local because even where some person formulates criticisms of (some such) rationality in some domain or the other, there the same individual chooses to be rational in other fields of human endeavor. Of course, there is nothing wrong with this attitude: we are rightly afraid of obscurantist rejections of rationality. However, the problems are these: of what kind of rationality ought we to be critical? That is to say, when are we morally obliged to criticize rationality? What kind of rationality is susceptible to such a moral criticism?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is normative about Corruption being a hindrance to development?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-normative-about-corruption-being-a-hindrance-to-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 21:02:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-normative-about-corruption-being-a-hindrance-to-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While translating Russell L. Ackoff, you say that such a translation is &amp;ldquo;not a moral judgment now, but a statement about the state of the economy&amp;rdquo;. But your claim, according to Ackoff&amp;rsquo;s own argument, is untrue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Consider how he describes corruption: &amp;ldquo;We concluded that corruption occurs when one party, A (for example, a policeman), who has an obligation to a second party, B (for example, the government), to provide service to a third party, C (for example, a member of the public), serves C in such a way as to benefit A more than he or she is supposed to. In addition, anyone who induces another to behave corruptly is corrupt. Therefore, corruption is the exploitation for one&amp;rsquo;s personal benefit of a position in which one is expected to serve others.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;B (the policeman) has an obligation to serve C (a member of the public) and this obligation is a moral obligation; A has a derived moral obligation to serve C because A is under the moral obligation to do what B (the government) expects him to. A violates his moral obligation to B because as a part of B, he serves C in such a way that A benefits more, that is, A&amp;rsquo;s (moral) abuse of his position makes him receive more benefits than he morally deserves. (What A deserves by virtue is serving C is a moral reward.) In this sense, Ackoff is making a moral claim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of NRIs and their symbolic interpretations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:34:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vyasa&amp;rsquo;s argument (to the extent we can speak of an argument in this context) is quite subtle: When Urvasi comes to Arjuna at the behest of his father, and when she is possessed by desire, and when the Apsaras choose freely and unconfined, then (a) one cannot reject her; (b) and with the argument that she is a superior to him. If you split this conjunction and cast in normative terms, it says something like this: (a) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when one&amp;rsquo;s father indicates that a son should sleep with a woman; (b) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when the woman is sexually attracted to oneself; (c) Rejection of a woman, whoever she might be, is not permitted when she chooses freely and without confines. Because such a rejection is triply prohibited (or forbidden), Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s argument that he &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the parent of his race (which has only one prohibition) possesses less value. So, Urvasi is justified in her curse of Arjuna. In other words, if we read this fragment of Mahabharata in normative terms, Arjuna was wrong in not having an incestuous relationship with one of his great-great-grandparents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1&amp;rsquo;. While one could argue that one &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the &amp;lsquo;superiors&amp;rsquo;, Urvasi suggests that because she has chosen freely, this argument is void. On top of saying why Arjuna is wrong to reject sleeping with her, she also comes up with two other reasons why he could sleep with her: (a) Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s ancestors have done so and without committing any &amp;lsquo;sin&amp;rsquo;; therefore, it is &amp;lsquo;permissible&amp;rsquo; that he does the same; (b)  it is a morally good thing to emulate one&amp;rsquo;s ancestors and therefore Arjuna &amp;lsquo;ought to&amp;rsquo; sleep with her.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Victorian Morality</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 06:13:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You suggest that calling Apsaras as &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo; is an extreme statement. Of course, you would be right if you mean that the English word does not carry all the connotations of &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; or even that our current usage of the word &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; is not as rich as the earlier uses of the same word were. You are right too when you point out that the word &amp;lsquo;Kama&amp;rsquo;, as a pursushartha, embraces a bigger set than sexual pleasure or romantic love. Perhaps, one might prefer the word &amp;lsquo;courtesan&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; but that distorts the Indian &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; too: a courtesan was either a mistress of the wealthy or a prostitute who entertained only the rich. However, I am not sure whether my claim is really that extreme (with the proviso that we keep in mind the current-day changes in the meanings of the words in both English and Indian languages). Let me explain why.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we read, say, Kamasutra, we discover that prostitutes had to be cultured and learned human beings; they were supposed to be proficient in multiple arts including music, poetry, dance, handicrafts and so on. &amp;lsquo;Treating the prostitutes humanely&amp;rsquo; includes teaching these skills to them: after all, many of the arts they practiced to entertain men requires teaching and learning. This suggests that a teacher could take prostitutes as his/her students and that the society did not disapprove. Instead, it countenanced such teaching. However, this is not all there is to the story. Consider the fact that a prostitute is also called &amp;rsquo;nitya sumangali&amp;rsquo;: one who can never become a widow. As you know, the word &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; is not usedlightly in India and it carries a very positive connotation as is also indexed by the use of &amp;lsquo;su&amp;rsquo;. (Of course, one uses this term also sarcastically in colloquial language but such use does not take away the positive connotation.) Even though the prostitute never marries, our traditions did not withhold the appellation &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; from her. Consider too, in this context, the &amp;lsquo;good qualities&amp;rsquo; of a wife: &amp;lsquo;Karyeshu dasi, Karaneshu mantri&amp;hellip;.&amp;rsquo; As this verse (I have forgotten both its source and how it ends) continues, it appears that a wife should also be &amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo; (a prostitute in bed). Quite independent of the conjectures we can make about its anti-feministic character or whatever, think about what this verse is suggesting: the wife should behave like a prostitute in the bedroom. What does that mean? Whether or not it also means that she should entertain her husband through music, recitation of poetry, dance and such like, one thing is clear: she must be well-versed in sexual matters. Step back for a moment and ask yourself how any girl could be well-versed (better than her husband, in fact) in sexual matters. There are only two possibilities: either the girl had a lot of experience in sex before marriage (there goes the idea of virginity of one&amp;rsquo;s wife) or she was trained and educated in the art of sex in her family. Irrespective of which of the possibilities is true, this verse indicates at least two things: being a prostitute did not make one immoral anymore than visiting a prostitute made one immoral. The prostitute had qualities which a &amp;lsquo;good wife&amp;rsquo; should emulate. Note that these qualities are not those that prostitutes also have; the wife is supposed to have those qualities that make a woman into a prostitute (&amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo;).  Furthermore, in so far as women were taught the &amp;lsquo;art of loving&amp;rsquo; (kama-sutra) in their families, surely, it tells us that the reaction of the middle class in India today is anything but Indian: it is an inherited prudishness drawn from the Victorian morality. It is in this sense that I suggested that the Indians are not prudes in matters of sexuality. In this sense too, in this Indian sense, Apsaras, I claim, are &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victorian morality of NRI and middle class Hindus: Prostitution, Adultery</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 05:53:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The Indian traditions did not have the same attitude as Christianity towards prostitution or adultery. And the Indians of yesteryears were not defenders of the Victorian (and Christian) morality. Of course, I approvingly said that the &amp;ldquo;Indians are not prudes&amp;rdquo; but this approval has to do with the thrust of Indian thought, as I have understood it: the impossibility of prohibiting or making obligatory some or another action universally. (This is my formulation, of course.) I do believe that the Indians recognized the impossibility of abolishing prostitution (which is why it is called &amp;ldquo;the oldest profession&amp;rdquo;). Instead, therefore, of banning and condemning prostitution (and subsequently turn a blind eye towards its existence), Indian thinkers suggested that we treat the prostitutes humanely. I have never been to a prostitute nor will I ever go to one; but that does not mean that I want to ignore their existence and treat them as non-humans. Nor am I willing to call all those who visit prostitutes as criminals and perverts. I know of too many lonely men and women who have found human warmth and personal comfort in the arms and companionship of prostitutes to consider them as perverts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is tradition akin to following moral obligations?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 04:45:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditions are inherited practices, which mean two things: they are both transmitted and learnt. The learning occurs through imitation, following instructions, through stories and so on. Consequently, traditions &amp;lsquo;change&amp;rsquo; (i.e. undergo modifications) even as they are being transmitted and learnt. This makes traditions flexible and adaptive.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human practices conserve, that is, we do not go around inventing new practices every day. In this sense, traditions are essentially conserving in their nature. This is one of the reasons why we see &amp;lsquo;being traditional&amp;rsquo; as `being conservative&amp;rsquo; as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Norm, utilitarian ought,  Patanjali</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/norm-utilitarian-ought-patanjali/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 01:18:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/norm-utilitarian-ought-patanjali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assume that India (or any other society) does not have an ethics. What would happen? Surely, if ethics has something to do with coordinating human actions, we know of several ways to do the same without taking recourse to ethical thinking: laws, rules (like those in games), agreements, pacts, covenants, &amp;hellip; are some of the candidates.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Assume that India does not know of normative ethics. So, what is wrong with this state of affairs? If something is wrong, what kind of &amp;lsquo;wrong&amp;rsquo; are we talking about here?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The word ‘Normative’</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-word-normative/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 23:03:56 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-word-normative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are other normative statements besides ethical ones: even aesthetic statements are normative (when you judge something to be ugly or beautiful) or statements about the presence of other values (say, &amp;rsquo;the meaning of life&amp;rsquo; questions). I have never denied it. As you rightly point out, legal norms are normative but they are not co-extensive with the ethical ones.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If there are standards to measure some entity or phenomenon and that such measurements are not &amp;ldquo;necessarily normative&amp;rdquo;, of course, you are right. We can say whether a car has been properly assembled by referring to the standards of putting the parts of the car together; we can say that rice has been adulterated or even that storm has a strength measured by the Beaufort scale. None of these is normative. I am not claiming that &amp;lsquo;all&amp;rsquo; measurements (or evaluations) are normative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normativity as ‘parasitic’ behavior</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normativity-as-parasitic-behavior/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 22:11:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normativity-as-parasitic-behavior/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We need to tackle the following issues properly if we want to get a handle on normativity and its relation to a configuration of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Normativity cannot be the product of ethical learning. If it were that, say, by being a biological inheritance, then normative thinking would be the form of all ethics and my claim is that it is not so.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.2. Nevertheless, we need to explain the success of the normative mode of thinking. That is, almost all aspects of human existence appear susceptible to the process of &amp;rsquo;norming&amp;rsquo; and this process is also capable of expressing our ethical judgments about issues. This suggests that normativity exemplifies a &amp;lsquo;parasitic&amp;rsquo; behavior: it can infect different learning process and their products. Put differently: it is capable of piggybacking upon different learning processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Ethics III</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 22:01:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I still have some difficulty in figuring out the problem about normative ethics expressed on the Abhinavagupta forum. There is obviously something that bugs people, but I cannot make out what it is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, about the counter evidence. If the Indian film censor board is a statutory body, then it derives its powers from the laws that have brought such an entity into being. Its tasks (viz. whether it is an advisory organ or can enforce its decisions, for instance) would be defined by the laws that govern such an entity and the same laws should also make it clear what &amp;lsquo;obscenity&amp;rsquo; is. (Assuming that such an entity has the task of censoring &amp;lsquo;obscenity&amp;rsquo;.) Establishing such an entity tells us something about the conceptions regarding the state and underlying such conceptions would be some normative doctrine about the relation between the state and citizens. (For instance it could be about the state guarding the &amp;lsquo;public morality&amp;rsquo; or the educative role of the state or whatever else.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ought vs. should</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-vs-should/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 21:46:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-vs-should/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X asks: I am unable to figure out what the special significance is of not having a &amp;lsquo;moral ought&amp;rsquo; in the Indian traditions. If &amp;lsquo;should not&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;must not&amp;rsquo; have the same practical consequences as &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo;, that is we are obligated to behave in a certain way, why does it make a difference how it is expressed in our language?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Your question is probably the best way of showing the difficulty we have with normative thinking. That is one of conceptualizing something called a normative ethical domain. Let us see if a simple (and simplistic) answer will help. Consider:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Ethics II</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 21:36:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever I discuss the absence of normative ethics in India, people, especially Indians, get agitated. They hear me say that India has no ethics. Consequently, they want to show that I could never be right in my claim. This has happened on the Abhinavagupta forum as well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, I should say that the Indian understanding of ethics is different from the western understanding. While this might prevent a knee-jerk reflex, it is not quite so informative.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Anthropology and Moral Domains. An Essay on Selfless Morality and the Moral Self—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 21:48:10 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Disquieting Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;Arthur Danto, the well-known American philosopher, prefaced a book he wrote in the 70’s on oriental thought and moral philosophy titled &lt;em&gt;Mysticism and Morality&lt;/em&gt; with the following words:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The factual beliefs (that the civilizations of the East) take for granted are &amp;hellip;too alien to our (the West’s) representations of the World to be grafted on to it, and &lt;em&gt;in consequence their moral systems are unavailable to us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Anthropology and Action Sciences. An Essay on Knowing to Act and Acting to Know—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:48:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.philosophica.ugent.be/article/82484/galley/202298/view/&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, published  &lt;em&gt;Philosophica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;40&lt;/strong&gt; (2): 77–107]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Should action sciences exist, it is obvious what they would have to study; the nature of human action, the kind of knowledge that actions generate, the process of learning to perform different types of action and so forth. Comparative anthropology, as a discipline, studies and contrasts, where such contrasts are possible, the different ways in which human beings organize their lives, think about and experience both themselves and world around them. A culture is a form of life and, as such, it is a way of going about the world. One would therefore expect to find a deep and intimate relation between action sciences on the one hand, and studies of culture on the other. A perusal of literature, however, shows the fact of the matter to be different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logic of normative ethics: Immorality</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logic-of-normative-ethics-immorality-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 04:16:56 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logic-of-normative-ethics-immorality-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why does one bring up the issue of one&amp;rsquo;s grandmother&amp;rsquo;s judgment about a clerk taking bribes as a counter-example? First, what do I say? That he &lt;em&gt;calls&lt;/em&gt; it as corruption has to do with western normative ethics. Does it follow from this that the action of the municipal clerk is ethically &lt;em&gt;good?&lt;/em&gt; It does not, unless one assumes either (a) I am presenting an &lt;em&gt;alternate&lt;/em&gt; moral principle, which will make the action of the clerk morally good; or that (b) the only morality that will make the action of the clerk ethically bad is the one that construes it as corruption. I am not presenting an alternate moral rule that justifies the action of the clerk. But I want to know why the so-called corruption comes about and whether it is that. My attempt at doing this is &lt;em&gt;assumed&lt;/em&gt; to make the action of the clerk or the building contractor morally good. Why this assumption? I suggest that it comes about because of the assumption (b).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating circumstances, normative ethics</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mitigating-circumstances-normative-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 03:55:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mitigating-circumstances-normative-ethics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The universalisability of norms does not mean that the western people all factually follow these norms. Even if everyone were to lie, the ethical statement &amp;ldquo;No one ought to lie&amp;rdquo; is a universal moral statement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The existence of &lt;em&gt;debates&lt;/em&gt; about abortion, war, etc. is indicative of the nature of normative rules. Because &amp;ldquo;one ought not to kill&amp;rdquo;, debates and doctrines about &amp;ldquo;justified war&amp;rdquo; come into being. It is important to note that these doctrines do not contradict the injunction not to kill but provide justifications for undertaking such an immoral action. (They provide, so to speak, the mitigating circumstances.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ethically Bad Action vs. Corruption—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ethically-bad-action-vs-corruption-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:57:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ethically-bad-action-vs-corruption-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The &amp;lsquo;corruption&amp;rsquo; refers to the social phenomenon in India which makes about 20% of the adult population into immoral people. When I said that I refuse to call the clerk &amp;lsquo;corrupt&amp;rsquo; or that the issue I raise is anterior, I am talking about this phenomenon. One uses the word &amp;lsquo;cheating&amp;rsquo; (something like the Hindi &amp;lsquo;Dhoka&amp;rsquo; probably). One could, for instance, use this word to describe the individual action of the clerk as an unethical one without &lt;em&gt;making&lt;/em&gt; it into corruption.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Are these two conversationally synonymous? I suppose it depends on the person with whom you are having a conversation, the context and the language used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is relative ethics coherent?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-relative-ethics-coherent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:40:07 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-relative-ethics-coherent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does the notion of &amp;ldquo;relative ethics&amp;rdquo; make sense within the context of the western ethics? There are some attempts to develop &amp;ldquo;ethical relativism&amp;rdquo;, even though it is not clear what is relativistic about them. One would be a kind of factual claim: different people, different groups, different cultures have different principles which they consider as &amp;ldquo;morally good&amp;rdquo;. This does not make for ethical relativism. The issue still remains: are these principles also ethically good? That is to say, one undertakes a &amp;rsquo;normative&amp;rsquo; enquiry in order to find out whether all these principles are also morally acceptable. The second would be to come up with a moral norm that is &amp;lsquo;relative&amp;rsquo; to some person or group. Any examination would very quickly lead to the conclusion that, in so far as it is a norm, it is universalizable even if the &lt;em&gt;domain of objects&lt;/em&gt; appears restricted. (That is because all &amp;lsquo;universal&amp;rsquo; laws specify the domain of objects, whether implicitly or explicitly, where they are applicable. The &amp;lsquo;relativistic&amp;rsquo; norms appear relativistic because they specify the domain explicitly.) In other words, no one has been able to come up with any coherent explication of what &amp;lsquo;relativistic ethics&amp;rsquo; means. (According to me, it is impossible to do so when we speak of normative ethics.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moral domain not defined by norms</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/moral-domain-not-defined-by-norms-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:33:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/moral-domain-not-defined-by-norms-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The inability of the Chinese language to express counterfactuals is even more intriguing. As you know, Confucius wrote his &amp;ldquo;Analects&amp;rdquo; in the Classical Chinese language. In order to see where I am heading, consider some of the thoughts that Rosemont, Jr. expresses. (Rosemont, Jr., H., &amp;ldquo;Against Relativism.&amp;rdquo; In Larson G. J. and E. Deutsch (eds.), &lt;em&gt;Interpreting Across Boundaries: New Essays in Comparative Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1988) Not only is there an absence of the concept of &amp;lsquo;morality&amp;rsquo; in the Classical Chinese, but also the very cluster of concepts required to speak about moral issues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Normative Ethics Richer?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-normative-ethics-richer-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:26:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-normative-ethics-richer-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Are western traditions innately richer because they have the moral ought?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My answer: No. In fact, in my book on ethics I will prove the following: the non-normative ethics are &lt;em&gt;richer:&lt;/em&gt; Under specific assumptions, in limited conditions, one can &lt;em&gt;derive&lt;/em&gt; a normative ethics from a non-normative one. The relation between non-normative ethics and normative ethics is analogous to the relation between Einsteinian theory and Newtonian theory: under specific assumptions, in limited conditions, you can derive the Newtonian theory from the Einsteinian theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative assumptions and Corruption</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-assumptions-that-make-actions-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:17:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-assumptions-that-make-actions-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that there is no distance between how we use corruption in our daily language and the way it is used in political and sociological theories of corruption. You see, the problem we (Indians) face is the asymmetry &lt;em&gt;in the way the word is used&lt;/em&gt; while talking about us and the way it is used when talking about India. I want to signal this by putting up the red flag: I want to suggest the reader not to assume the truth of these descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Ethics: Moral Dilemmas and Imperfect World</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-moral-dilemmas-and-imperfect-world-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 00:43:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-moral-dilemmas-and-imperfect-world-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us say that &amp;lsquo;X&amp;rsquo; does something which &amp;lsquo;Y&amp;rsquo; considers corrupt. To keep it simple, let us say that &amp;lsquo;Y&amp;rsquo; expresses the aforementioned judgment. In order to express it, or persuade others about the validity of this moral judgment, &amp;lsquo;Y&amp;rsquo; will have to do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Y defines &amp;lsquo;corruption&amp;rsquo;: &amp;ldquo;All actions which exhibit _______ properties are corrupt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Y&amp;rsquo;s &amp;rsquo;ethical principle&amp;rsquo; (itself justified): &amp;ldquo;All actions which satisfy ______ (the principle) are moral&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: The Logic of “India is Corrupt”</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 22:17:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(A)&lt;/strong&gt; Consider the following sequence of sentences:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are perfectly and fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are perfectly fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For sentences (1) and (2), all it takes is one instance of immorality to be proven wrong. Our proverbial municipal clerk would be immoral, and it would disprove the sentence (1). The same example could also confirm sentence (3); an instance of a moral act would also be a counter-example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Colonial Experience and the Indian Renaissance: A prolegomenon to a Project—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the striking things about the British colonial rule is its success in developing certain ways of talking about the Indian culture and society. The British criticised the Indian &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;, the Indian &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo;, the Indian education system, practices like &amp;lsquo;sati&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;untouchability&amp;rsquo;, and so on and so forth. They redrew the outlines of Indian intellectual history as indigenous responses to some of the ills they saw in the Indian society and culture: for example, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, as it emerged out of their reconstruction, was a revolt against &amp;lsquo;Brahmanism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo;. Many Indian intellectuals emphasized British criticism by making &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; in the latter their own: the Arya Samaj, the Brahmo Samaj, many Hindu &amp;lsquo;reform&amp;rsquo; movements, and so on exemplify this trend. I say &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; and place it in scare quotes because the &lt;em&gt;unbroken line of continuity&lt;/em&gt; between the colonial period and the one following the Indian independence raises two &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of questions. The first is this: would there have been such a line of continuity if there was no &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; to the British portrayal of our history, traditions, and culture? This question uses the &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; of continuity to suggest that the British descriptions &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; That is, our current experience of our culture and society appears to lend truth-value to the colonial descriptions of India. The second question transforms our &amp;lsquo;current experience&amp;rsquo; itself into a problem: does such a line of continuity indicate that our experiences themselves are still colonial in nature? This question throws doubts upon the &amp;lsquo;facticity&amp;rsquo; of the British descriptions of India, and suggests that they &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;lsquo;untrue&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; In the process, it also challenges us to look more closely and investigate our own experiences today. That is, the second question withholds assent to the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of the colonial descriptions of India and of some of the claims we make about our experiences of our culture and society today. To some extent, and only to some extent, the so-called &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; writings can be seen as attempts to make sense of the second question. Even though I do not fancy the label of being a &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; myself, I perceive a shared sense of a quest with them. &lt;em&gt;There is something deeply, deeply wrong with the line of continuity that exists between the colonial period and today&amp;rsquo;s India,&lt;/em&gt; and the challenge is to say what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Experience: Normative Ethics I</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-experience-normative-ethics-101-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:32:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-experience-normative-ethics-101-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is western normative ethics? It is a structure or style of thinking about ethics. What is its structure? It makes use of norms. What are norms? &amp;lsquo;Rules&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;principles&amp;rsquo; which have a characteristic structure that use certain concepts like the moral &amp;lsquo;ought&amp;rsquo; and moral &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo;. That is, some actions &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to be performed (i.e. they are obligatory); some actions &lt;em&gt;ought not&lt;/em&gt; to be performed (i.e. they are forbidden) and some actions are neither of the two (i.e. they are permitted). What is important to note is that these norms (i.e. for example, some action is obligatory) hold irrespective of time, place, condition or the person. In other words, norms are supposed to hold universally. From what I have said above, it logically follows that violation (or transgressing) some moral norm or the other is immoral (or unethical) and following some moral norm is moral (or ethical).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
