<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Romila Thapar on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/romila-thapar/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Romila Thapar on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/romila-thapar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf&#34;&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf&#34;&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115&#34;&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logical Acumen of Romila Thapar</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:28:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the debates in the Indian traditions is about the kind of creatures that exist in the world and about the reality of what exists. The Jains, for instance, disagreed that the &amp;ldquo;deva&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; of other traditions (with the properties they were supposed to possess) existed in this world or were real. (Their so-called &amp;lsquo;atheism&amp;rsquo; is a result of this debate.) Consequently, when they call Valmiki Ramayana false, they are making claims about the logical falsehood. They did not, on the basis of some or another empirical enquiry, establish that Ravana was a vegetarian or that Rakshasas were human beings (in fact, in many parts of India, people believe that Ravana was both a Brahmin and a rakshasa at the same time) or that Rama was different from what Valmiki said he was. The same applies to Anjaneya: the claim of some or another author that he was a human being and was married does not either &amp;lsquo;prove&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;disprove&amp;rsquo; the claim of Valmiki.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
