<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Secular on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/secular/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Secular on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 20:04:47 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/secular/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hijabs, Turbans and the Secular</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/hijabs-turbans-and-the-secular-state/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 20:04:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/hijabs-turbans-and-the-secular-state/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us suppose that some school or another in India also prescribes uniform to its students. A Sikh boy and a Muslim girl enroll. They wear the colors of the school, including the right colored turban (or, if the Sikh kid is too young, his hair tied up in a knot) and the right-colored head scarf. From what I know of the Indian schools, most schools (including the fellow-students) would let the situation stand. Assume that some school makes an issue about this. The parents do not have many choices: either the Sikh family shaves the boy (unlikely), or step to the courts (more likely today than yesterday) or look for another school (most likely) if persuading the school authorities fails. If we look at the tolerance of the school authorities, it appears to me that the following can be said: in all probability, it does not occur to them that, in keeping the turban or the head scarf on, the kids are marking themselves off or that there is discrimination involved in allowing this. The question is: how do they look at the turban (or the tied knot of hair) or at the scarf?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secular State and Hijab</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secular-state-and-hijab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 23:18:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secular-state-and-hijab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We can all accept the fact, I suppose, that some thing or another is a religious symbol to someone when s/he belongs to that religion whose symbol it is. In this sense, the Cross (for a long period of time), the figure of the Prophet Mohammed (also for a long period of time) and the star of David (in the course of this century) are symbols that carry religious significance to the Christians, Muslims and the Jews respectively. We are also agreed, I suppose, that there is no way of characterizing any of these as religious symbols in a religiously neutral way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercultural exchange of categories</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 19:42:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is wrong with the intercultural exchange of categories? Throughout one gets the impression that there is something “fundamentally wrong” with categories shifting in meaning over time or with the introduction of categories from one culture into another culture. But what is important about these shifts in meaning? What exactly is the problem in introducing the category of religion into India or among Native Americans? The category “yuppie” did not exist in the Middle Ages, while “orange” came through Arabic from Sanskrit, and “girl” used to refer to a young person of either sex. When we analyse the genetics of early modern populations, we are also introducing categories that they did not possess. Or take the word “silly,” which in Old English used to mean blessed. So what? An historical analysis of discourse and categories is significant not to identify shifts in meaning per se. Shifts in meaning become significant only against the background of a theory on the historical development of the western culture and its understanding of other cultures. Such a theory is needed to clarify as to why a shift in the meaning of “religion” or “the secular” is of crucial importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is  laukika-adhyatimika distinction same as secular-sacred distinction?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2011 22:21:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-laukika-and-adhyatimika-same-as-that-between-secular-and-religious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The theories (and discussions) about secularism constitute a test case for the claims advanced in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo; about the universalizing drive of religion. I have suggested that religion spreads by secularizing itself, and that the distinction between the secular and the religious is drawn by and within a religion. If this is the case, then it must be possible to show that the current theories of secularism are secularizations of a particular set of theological claims. (Theology draws these distinctions and defends them.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bankruptcy of postcolonial intellectuals and their defense of secularism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/bankruptcy-of-postcolonial-intellectuals-and-their-defense-of-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:47:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/bankruptcy-of-postcolonial-intellectuals-and-their-defense-of-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have developed partial explanations of why the secularism debate in India takes such peculiar forms and why otherwise intelligent people talk nonsense here. But we don&amp;rsquo;t do so by pegging our use of the word secularism &amp;ldquo;onto Balu&amp;rsquo;s theory about the nature of religion and how that entity religion behaves in the world&amp;rdquo; and then expecting that other people do the same.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let me quickly repeat our argument: Concepts like religion and secularism and principles of the secular state developed in Europe against the background of larger conceptual frameworks. Broadly speaking, one knew what &lt;code&gt;religion&#39; and &#39;the secular state&#39; referred to or what the separation of &lt;/code&gt;the religious&amp;rsquo; and `the political&amp;rsquo; amounted to, because these terms were embedded in such a common background framework. Naturally, there were many different positions and discontinuities in the debates. But disagreements about the precise meaning of terms or clashes between conflicting normative positions made sense to the participants, precisely because they occurred against the background of this type of framework. The framework put semantic limits on the potential interpretation of terms and principles, as it related concepts to each other in particular systematic ways. This background framework reflects not only generic Christian theology and political theory, but also the common cultural and historical experience of Europeans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fallacy of Equivocation: Indian Secularism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/fallacy-of-equivocation-indian-secularism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 23:03:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/fallacy-of-equivocation-indian-secularism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading Shabnum Tejani&amp;rsquo;s *Indian Secularism: A Social and Intellectual History (*2008), I ran into the same weird point that Neera Chandhoke also tried to make at the RRI platform debate on secularism. This is a combination of the old claim that &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; has acquired a different meaning in India and a general theoretical point: &amp;lsquo;secularism does not have any essence or universal meaning, but gets different meanings dependent on the historical and cultural contexts in which it has developed&amp;rsquo;. There are different variations on this formulation, but the general point is one that is becoming increasingly popular (especially among historians), because of the influence of Talal Asad and other postmodernators. Hence, I wanted to try and address the point by taking the example of Tejani&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Amartya Sen&#39;s Argumentative Indian—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:17:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, there are multiple images of India current in the West. There is the mystic India, an image that the German Romantics created and the &amp;lsquo;flower children&amp;rsquo; of the sixties made popular. There is the third world India with enormous poverty and suffering, which the developmental workers have projected. There is also the India, the centre of IT outsourcing, which the developments in the last decade have brought into existence, and so on. Amartya Sen, the Indian noble prize-winner in Economics, has written a book on &amp;ldquo;The Argumentative Indian&amp;rdquo; which speaks of an India that he wants us to consider. This India is an India with a history of toleration and pluralism, an India that has brought forth its own version of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo;, and an India that is every bit rational, discursive and analytical as the western culture itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the distinction between ‘secular’and ‘religious’ neutral? –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:30:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-distinction-between-secularand-religious-neutral-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question appears to be: need one accept certain premises of Christianity (whether Protestant or Catholic varieties) in order that the dominant understanding of, say, the secular state and the caste to make sense? That those to whom such accounts make sense do not explicitly subscribe to the premises of a specific religious appears to throw doubt on our claims.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the very distinction between &amp;rsquo;the religious&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the secular&amp;rsquo;. Historically, Christianity has drawn this line. (Theologians have spent much ink over the last two thousand years drawing, defending, and elaborating upon this distinction.) It is also the case that political thinkers in the West, some of whom were militantly atheistic, have made this distinction into a cornerstone of their theories. Further, many Indian thinkers, most of whom know very little of Christian theologies, base their arguments on these and allied distinctions. The existence of the last two groups appears to tell us that even when one rejects some or all religions, even when one is utterly oblivious to the histories and theologies of the Christianities, this distinction does make sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
