<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Law on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/law/</link><description>Recent content in Law on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/law/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Questioning the axioms</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are three ideas in the West about Law that are taken as axioms. The first: all societies are founded on Law; if they are not, they ought to be. The second is that Law teaches and educates a people. Third is their corollary: only thus do a people become a Nation. As far as I know, none has shown their empirical truth or proved that they are logically necessary. But their truth-value is undisputed. When they ruled India, the British followed these axioms: they tried to educate us through Law, interfered in our festivals and social practices and the State tried to educate a barbaric people by enacting  ‘just’ laws. Romulus gave Law and made a group into a people; Moses gave Law and made a people into a Nation; Mohammed gave Law and transformed multiple nations into a caliphate; Manu acquires the exalted status of a Law-giver for the ‘Hindus’. These ideas are not dated, apparently. Today, they enjoy the same privilege they had during the colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Indian view on Derrida and post-modernists</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/an-indian-view-on-derrida-and-post-modernists/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:43:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/an-indian-view-on-derrida-and-post-modernists/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balu&amp;rsquo;s piece on &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/17537173/An_Indian_View_on_Derrida_and_Post-modernists"&gt;Derrida&amp;rsquo;s the force of law&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Christian Attitudes and The Rule of Law as the Mechanism of Secularization</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-secularization-and-religious-attitudes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 06:22:11 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-secularization-and-religious-attitudes/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So far, our answers have always taken this form: in the moment of secularization, the formal structures or cognitive schemes of Christianity are diffused accordingly as they lose their specific doctrinal content. In this formulation, it is as though the logical form of religion is able to spread itself by disposing of its semantic content. Thus, both the common sense of the West and the scholarly consensus of the academia accept the background assumptions of Christian doctrine, while they do not adopt its specific teachings. Balu has always been somewhat unhappy about this formulation. As he argues in &lt;a href="http://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness"&gt;chapter 11 of `The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;, it is not a specific set of assumptions which spreads in society, but rather certain attitudes. The claims about the universality of religion, the meaning of life, the necessity of norms, the superiority of liberal democracy, etc. do not generally appear as explicit premises held by a group of people. Then, it seems the only explanation one can give is to ascribe them to these people as implicit assumptions. To some extent, this works: theories about the origin of religion, or the nature of morality, or human psychology all presuppose that certain assumptions are true. So if one intends to reveal the conceptual problems of these theories, it is fruitful to analyze these assumptions as the hidden premises of theorizing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when it comes to explaining how the Christian religion spreads in a secular form, these accounts are unconvincing. What happens? Do the implicit assumptions or formalized theological schemes expand their scope as a kind of unit ideas by jumping from mind to mind? In what realm do these assumptions and background frameworks exist and procreate? The problem becomes acute when we turn to the spread of secularized Christianity in pagan societies like the Indian. Do the elite of alienated intellectuals suddenly adopt these assumptions as the starting points of reasoning about politics and society? Do they spread automatically from the colonized elite to other layers of Indian society, because this is a basic dynamic of societies? Such answers would be unsatisfactory. But what then is the mechanism through which secularized religious schemes spread and structure the experience of an ever increasing number of individuals? This and other related questions have been bothering me for some time (not least because I have failed to solve any of them in my doctoral thesis).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Colonial Consciousness and Victorian Morality</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 06:13:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You suggest that calling Apsaras as &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo; is an extreme statement. Of course, you would be right if you mean that the English word does not carry all the connotations of &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; or even that our current usage of the word &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; is not as rich as the earlier uses of the same word were. You are right too when you point out that the word &amp;lsquo;Kama&amp;rsquo;, as a pursushartha, embraces a bigger set than sexual pleasure or romantic love. Perhaps, one might prefer the word &amp;lsquo;courtesan&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; but that distorts the Indian &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; too: a courtesan was either a mistress of the wealthy or a prostitute who entertained only the rich. However, I am not sure whether my claim is really that extreme (with the proviso that we keep in mind the current-day changes in the meanings of the words in both English and Indian languages). Let me explain why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we read, say, Kamasutra, we discover that prostitutes had to be cultured and learned human beings; they were supposed to be proficient in multiple arts including music, poetry, dance, handicrafts and so on. &amp;lsquo;Treating the prostitutes humanely&amp;rsquo; includes teaching these skills to them: after all, many of the arts they practiced to entertain men requires teaching and learning. This suggests that a teacher could take prostitutes as his/her students and that the society did not disapprove. Instead, it countenanced such teaching. However, this is not all there is to the story. Consider the fact that a prostitute is also called &amp;rsquo;nitya sumangali&amp;rsquo;: one who can never become a widow. As you know, the word &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; is not usedlightly in India and it carries a very positive connotation as is also indexed by the use of &amp;lsquo;su&amp;rsquo;. (Of course, one uses this term also sarcastically in colloquial language but such use does not take away the positive connotation.) Even though the prostitute never marries, our traditions did not withhold the appellation &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; from her. Consider too, in this context, the &amp;lsquo;good qualities&amp;rsquo; of a wife: &amp;lsquo;Karyeshu dasi, Karaneshu mantri&amp;hellip;.&amp;rsquo; As this verse (I have forgotten both its source and how it ends) continues, it appears that a wife should also be &amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo; (a prostitute in bed). Quite independent of the conjectures we can make about its anti-feministic character or whatever, think about what this verse is suggesting: the wife should behave like a prostitute in the bedroom. What does that mean? Whether or not it also means that she should entertain her husband through music, recitation of poetry, dance and such like, one thing is clear: she must be well-versed in sexual matters. Step back for a moment and ask yourself how any girl could be well-versed (better than her husband, in fact) in sexual matters. There are only two possibilities: either the girl had a lot of experience in sex before marriage (there goes the idea of virginity of one&amp;rsquo;s wife) or she was trained and educated in the art of sex in her family. Irrespective of which of the possibilities is true, this verse indicates at least two things: being a prostitute did not make one immoral anymore than visiting a prostitute made one immoral. The prostitute had qualities which a &amp;lsquo;good wife&amp;rsquo; should emulate. Note that these qualities are not those that prostitutes also have; the wife is supposed to have those qualities that make a woman into a prostitute (&amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo;).  Furthermore, in so far as women were taught the &amp;lsquo;art of loving&amp;rsquo; (kama-sutra) in their families, surely, it tells us that the reaction of the middle class in India today is anything but Indian: it is an inherited prudishness drawn from the Victorian morality. It is in this sense that I suggested that the Indians are not prudes in matters of sexuality. In this sense too, in this Indian sense, Apsaras, I claim, are &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Normativity as ‘parasitic’ behavior</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normativity-as-parasitic-behavior/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 22:11:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normativity-as-parasitic-behavior/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We need to tackle the following issues properly if we want to get a handle on normativity and its relation to a configuration of learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.1. Normativity cannot be the product of ethical learning. If it were that, say, by being a biological inheritance, then normative thinking would be the form of all ethics and my claim is that it is not so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.2. Nevertheless, we need to explain the success of the normative mode of thinking. That is, almost all aspects of human existence appear susceptible to the process of &amp;rsquo;norming&amp;rsquo; and this process is also capable of expressing our ethical judgments about issues. This suggests that normativity exemplifies a &amp;lsquo;parasitic&amp;rsquo; behavior: it can infect different learning process and their products. Put differently: it is capable of piggybacking upon different learning processes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Normative Ethics II</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-ii/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2011 21:36:13 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/normative-ethics-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever I discuss the absence of normative ethics in India, people, especially Indians, get agitated. They hear me say that India has no ethics. Consequently, they want to show that I could never be right in my claim. This has happened on the Abhinavagupta forum as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, I should say that the Indian understanding of ethics is different from the western understanding. While this might prevent a knee-jerk reflex, it is not quite so informative.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Moral Domains. An Essay on Selfless Morality and the Moral Self—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 21:48:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Disquieting Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
Arthur Danto, the well-known American philosopher, prefaced a book he wrote in the 70’s on oriental thought and moral philosophy titled &lt;em&gt;Mysticism and Morality&lt;/em&gt; with the following words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The factual beliefs (that the civilizations of the East) take for granted are &amp;hellip;too alien to our (the West’s) representations of the World to be grafted on to it, and &lt;em&gt;in consequence their moral systems are unavailable to us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>