<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terrorism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/terrorism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Terrorism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 21:49:46 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/terrorism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Magic of ‘Radicalization’?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-magic-of-radicalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 21:49:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-magic-of-radicalization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the Paris attacks came the questions: Is this violence caused by Islam or unrelated to religion? Are the perpetrators believers or madmen? Do they represent the extremists that we find in any ideology?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The responses were diverse: ‘Islam is a threat to free speech’. But many Muslims joined the protest marches in defence of the freedom of expression. ‘Not all Muslims are terrorists, but most terrorists are Muslims’. The statistics show otherwise. ‘Madmen have neither colour nor religion’. Yet the ‘professionals’ in Paris screamed ‘Allahu Akbar’.  And then appeared the magical word ‘radicalization’. From the mayor to the teacher, from the politician to the policeman, everyone now knows what the problem is and where we should look for solutions: strict measures against ‘radicalized Muslims’ and ‘deradicalization programmes’ developed by ‘radicalization experts’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brig SK Malik’s theory of war and terrorism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brig-sk-maliks-theory-of-war-and-justification-of-crimes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:28:21 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brig-sk-maliks-theory-of-war-and-justification-of-crimes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What Brig SK Malik says supports &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;my thesis&lt;/a&gt;about terrorism, instead of making it redundant, as one suggests. Here is how.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In war, killing the enemy is considered a moral and justifiable act, even though &amp;lsquo;killing a fellow human being&amp;rsquo; is considered immoral. (This includes many provisos, including that the war is justified.) That is to say, a theory of just war (and warfare) justifies what is actually an act of murder. This justification is moral in nature and occurs on the presupposition that &amp;lsquo;killing in a war is a good thing&amp;rsquo;. That is why we give medals to supererogatory acts in times of war, like &amp;lsquo;medals for bravery&amp;rsquo; for instance. (There are many people who do not buy this; hence they are pacifists.) Brig SK Mailk&amp;rsquo;s theory of war and warfare justifies &amp;rsquo;terror&amp;rsquo; (basically the domain of crime): it does so by (a) transforming an entire population (the Indians) into the &amp;lsquo;other&amp;rsquo; (&amp;rsquo;the enemy&amp;rsquo;); (b) justifying any and every action against everyone belonging to or supporting this (Indian) community into &amp;rsquo;the enemy&amp;rsquo;; (c) making no distinction between &amp;rsquo;the soldier&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the civilian&amp;rsquo; (whereas every theory of warfare makes this distinction, without which the notion of &amp;lsquo;war&amp;rsquo; threatens to become meaningless); and, above all, (d) by presenting it as a theory of &amp;lsquo;war&amp;rsquo;. That is to say, Brigadier SK Malik is justifying crime in the name of war.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religious intolerance and terrorism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-and-terrorism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:22:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-intolerance-and-terrorism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What is the relationship between religious intolerance and the acts committed in Mumbai?&amp;rdquo; This is an empirical question at many levels. If some or another religion is used to defend the attacks in Mumbai, then it depends very much on the kinds of justifications used; the kind of theology in question; the relationship between the belief-states of the perpetrators and their motives; the relationship between their acts and their religious beliefs; and so on. Religious intolerance might or might not lead to conversion, to persecution of those who have &amp;lsquo;other&amp;rsquo; beliefs, to playing the &amp;lsquo;priest&amp;rsquo; and so on. What cannot be said, anyway, is that religious intolerance necessarily leads to Mumbai attacks. However, religious intolerance always harbors such a possibility. Whether or not such a possibility also occurs in our world depends on many, many empirical circumstances I have no clear view of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideology of Crime</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ideology-of-crime/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:16:11 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ideology-of-crime/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice is that I use the word &amp;ldquo;ideology&amp;rdquo; in a technical sense, which is both counter-intuitive and, for the time being, idiosyncratic. It is the first, namely counter-intuitive, because, as I use it, my use of the word does not refer to any theory, or to sets of beliefs, or to what one believes in. Normally, as we use the word in English, &amp;lsquo;ideology&amp;rsquo; has multiple meanings: a false consciousness; accepting a theory known to be false; presenting the interests of a small strata of people as the universal interests of all; subscribing to premises that are either unjustified or not-examined; and so on. My use has no such connotation. It is the second, namely idiosyncratic, because I have not yet developed a hypothesis about ideology that can explain and justify my use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Saint, The Criminal and The Terrorist—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:10:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the phenomenon of terrorism has begun to occupy the media, politics, and the lives of people in different parts of the world. The more the attention, however, the less the clarity: what kind of a phenomenon is terrorism? What generates it, what sustains it, and what allows it to expand on an ever-increasing scale?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lack of clarity has to do with the fact that our ideas about terrorism appear as an incoherent set. First, terrorism horrifies most of us; the acts of terrorists are seen as monstrous in scope and size. But the number of deaths or the human suffering, even if we look at an event as momentous as 9/11, is dwarfed by what traffic accidents and smoking do in any given year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
