<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>India-Forum on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/india-forum/</link>
    <description>Recent content in India-Forum on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 17:50:55 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/india-forum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Swami, the Priest, and the Rediscovery of the Indian Traditions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-swami-the-priest-and-the-rediscovery-of-the-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 17:50:55 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-swami-the-priest-and-the-rediscovery-of-the-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will take up some of the general points, which I think are relevant to the Indian American community at large. First, let me say I am impressed by the dynamism present in this community. In spite of the demands of daily life, Indian Americans find the time and energy to engage in intellectual debates about the nature of their traditions. In spite of the discrimination and &amp;ldquo;religion oppression&amp;rdquo; [1] faced by them, there is a general sense of optimism about the future of these traditions.&#xA;It is important that this dynamism remain a positive force. Some Indian Americans have adopted the name-calling that we find among certain American academics. Whereas the latter call anyone who dares say a few positive words about the Indian traditions &amp;ldquo;a Hindutva sycophant,&amp;rdquo; the former trend to label any western intellectual who dares question the dominant representations of the Indian traditions as a &amp;ldquo;Witzellian.&amp;rdquo; The legitimate discontent about the academic representation of the Indian traditions should not lead us to a general anti-intellectual stance. Anti-intellectualism knows only one endpoint: the &lt;em&gt;Taliban&lt;/em&gt;. Now, if there is one community aware of the duty to avoid that society moves towards that point, it is the Indian American community. Since intellectuals share this sense of duty, our study of the Indian traditions should show how they can contribute to making American society a more tolerant, open-minded and happier society.&#xA;As Chitra Raman affirms, the Indian traditions have been conceptualized in an extremely impoverished manner during the last few centuries. It is the hypothesis of our research group that this is the case because they have been viewed &lt;em&gt;through a secularized biblical framework&lt;/em&gt;. [2] The same framework also puts conceptual limitations on the structure of American pluralism. This is not an assessment about the origins of this form of pluralism or a judgment about its biased nature, but rather a &lt;em&gt;cognitive&lt;/em&gt; analysis of its contemporary structure. Such an analysis cannot be challenged by a moralizing judgement (e.g., that it justifies discrimination). The only way to really challenge my hypothesis is to develop another hypothesis about the structure of American pluralism. Naturally, its purpose is to develop new ways of solving the problems of pluralism in the U.S. To do so, one should indeed strive to bring American pluralism beyond its biblical straitjacket in the near future. Perhaps, no group is as qualified to do so as the Indian Americans.&#xA;But before they can take up this task, they should understand the depth of the predicament. Even more so, they have to become aware that they have appropriated the secularized Christian conception of the Indian traditions as a self-description. The predicament we face is &lt;em&gt;cognitive&lt;/em&gt; in nature: the currently dominant conception of the Indian traditions makes sense only against the background of the biblical framework. It is cognitive in the sense that the way we currently think and talk about “Hinduism” leads to a distortion of the very nature of the Indian traditions. This dominant conception of “Hinduism” does not describe these traditions themselves, but rather &lt;em&gt;how they appear through western and Christian lenses&lt;/em&gt;. Yet many Indians and Indian Americans talk as though this conception makes eminent sense to them.&#xA;Chitra Raman develops a nice analogy: it is like using the grammar of one language to understand another. One may adopt the words of the second language, but when one embeds them in the grammatical structure of the first language, one ends up with virtual gibberish. The analogy can be taken further: today, it is as though the native speakers of the second language have accepted the grammatical structure of the first language as the only correct one and they try to speak their own language in this way. This is the nature of our predicament: many Indians and Indian Americans have adopted the conceptual framework of Christianity to talk about their own traditions. They assume the Indian traditions are a belief system or religion with its own doctrines, commandments and rules. As I will try to show, this makes about as much sense as using the grammatical structure of one language to speak another completely different language.&#xA;To avoid any misunderstanding, let it be clear that the denial that the Indian traditions are of the same nature as biblical religion does not involve any value judgement. They also have a highly-developed structure, but this is so different from Judaism, Christianity and Islam that it is impossible to maintain that the Indian traditions and the latter three are instances of the same kind. In fact, once we appreciate how different the Indian traditions are from these religions, we will rediscover how rich and valuable they really are. To return to the language analogy: if we used the grammatical structure of one language to speak another, we would not be able to understand this second language and would also ignore its rich contributions to literature, philosophy and poetry. It is only when we rediscover the structure of this second language that its treasures become available to us. Similarly, when we rediscover the nature of the Indian traditions and rescue them from being transformed into just another religion, we will be able to show how they have contributed to the pursuit of knowledge at a level undreamt of.&#xA;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Priest and the Swami&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;In &lt;em&gt;Facing the Challenge of American Pluralism&lt;/em&gt;, I argued that the Indian traditions revolve around the exploring and examining of one’s experience so as to attain perfect happiness. What does this mean? How is it different from what religions like Christianity and Islam do? As an entry point, take a Hindu swamiji and a Christian priest. The priest says “God is a Trinity.” The swamiji says “&lt;em&gt;Tat Tvam Asi&lt;/em&gt;.” What is the difference between the two?&#xA;First the priest. The sentence “God is a Trinity” is a doctrine to him; it is a proposition about the world, which he takes to be absolutely true. Because it is a doctrine, the sentence is embedded in an elaborate theological system. It is related to other sentences that explain its true meaning: theological doctrines about Jesus being the Son of God and the Father, the Son and the Spirit being one substance, but three persons. Arguments have been developed to establish the truth of the Trinitarian doctrine. Its correct formulation was discussed and fixed at the First Council of Nicea in 325 AD. The result is the Nicene Creed: a set of beliefs that are held to reflect religious truth by most Christian denominations. As a Christian believer, when the priest says “God is a Trinity,” one is expected to accept this as a true belief, a doctrine embedded in a belief system that claims the one and only religious truth. As an orthodox Christian today, one should understand this doctrine, proclaim its truth and be able to defend it against its detractors. One should not question its truth and meaning. These have been fixed for good.&#xA;Now the swamiji. When he states “&lt;em&gt;Tat Tvam Asi&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;em&gt;”&lt;/em&gt; does he expect all Hindus to accept this sentence as a true doctrine? Does he want them to take this as a true belief, whose truth they should proclaim and defend against the “false beliefs” of other religions? Does he expect them to memorize the sentence and its related doctrines and arguments, and repeat them until eternity? No, he does not. When the swamiji teaches, he takes into account the different levels and experiences of his audience. He will explain “&lt;em&gt;Tat Tvam Asi&lt;/em&gt;” in different ways according to the different experiential levels of individuals. The sentence does not have one fixed true meaning, precisely because it functions as an instruction for exploring one’s own experience. It suggests that the distinction between I and not-I is a temporary figment that results from interpreting our experience in a particular way. If we examine this experience at a deeper level, we will slowly discover that there is no such distinction there. The swamiji’s explanation of the sentence will make sense to us, according to where we are on the path towards this discovery.&#xA;Hence, neither the speech of the &lt;em&gt;swamiji&lt;/em&gt; nor the texts of the Indian traditions can be understood as belief systems or doctrines, which have a fixed meaning and claim to reflect the one religious truth. They are “heuristics” that function as instructions for action to explore our own experience. To attain the insights embodied in these sentences, one has to examine them from all sides, relate them to one’s experience and question their truth repeatedly. Only in this way can they help us become better and happier human beings. The claim of the Indian traditions is not that we should accept them as true doctrines or that such acceptance is a precondition for attaining salvation. They do not postpone perfect happiness until after death. Neither do they claim that there is only one true path to attain this state. Rather, they claim that all human beings can attain perfect happiness here on earth and that there are countless ways to achieve this goal.&#xA;Those who conceptualize the Indian traditions as “belief systems,” “doctrines” or “religion” take away the unique nature of these traditions. They make the rich storehouse of experiential knowledge embodied by these traditions inaccessible and do so by transforming them into a belief system, the Hindu equivalent of Christianity or Islam. Let it be clear that the Indian traditions are neither belief systems nor religions. They are far more fascinating than that. I refer you to the piece by my teacher S. N. Balagangadhara (soon to be published on the India Forum website) to get a glimpse of how rich these traditions are. Here, just note that it is &lt;em&gt;precisely the way in which the Indian traditions are different from belief systems, which makes them into extremely important but uncharted contributions to the human pursuit of knowledge&lt;/em&gt;.&#xA;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transforming the Swami into a Priest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;But what happens when we reduce the Indian traditions into a Hindu “religion,” “world view” or “belief system”? What are the consequences of transforming the swamiji into a priest? Why is this development so harmful?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularism, Colonialism and Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:01:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few decades, &amp;ldquo;secularism&amp;rdquo; has become the subject of caustic debate in the Indian media. The dispute about the value of this idea to contemporary India is no longer confined to the academic circles. Politicians, journalists and others have strong views on the topic. Secularism regularly surfaces in newspaper articles, speeches and public meetings. The critics of the idea, however, are not often taken seriously at the theoretical level. The proponents of secularism dismiss all objections against their pet idea as misguided. Critics are either considered to be naive obscurantists, who dream of a return to a romantic image of Indian traditional society; or they are condemned as Hindu fundamentalists, who resist modern secular values and strive for a Hindu religious state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facing the challenge of American Pluralism on the future of NRI community</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facing-the-challenge-of-american-pluralism-on-the-future-of-nri-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:29:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facing-the-challenge-of-american-pluralism-on-the-future-of-nri-community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In years to come, the Indian community in the U.S. will face a major challenge from American pluralism. This is the first time a powerful community of pagans has to be accommodated within the American society. The NRI community is well-educated, well-to-do and proud of its cultural traditions. At the same time, the representation of the Indian traditions in the U.S. educational system shows a pathetic level of understanding. I will argue that recent events like the California textbook controversy point to a profound problem: &lt;em&gt;the American model of pluralism is unable to accommodate these pagan traditions&lt;/em&gt;. This is the case, because its structure has emerged from a co-existence of Protestant denominations. Maximally, the resulting model could encompass other variants of the religions of the book: Catholicism, Judaism and Islam. Incorporating the pagan traditions of India, however, will require a fundamental rethinking of American pluralism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a positive portrayal of Hindu traditions?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/towards-a-positive-portrayal-of-hindu-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:14:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/towards-a-positive-portrayal-of-hindu-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is at stake in the California textbook controversy? Few would agree that it concerns only the image of Hinduism as offered to the pupils of the California state schools. The controversy involves much more than that alone. It is the next phase in the NRI community&amp;rsquo;s struggle for a less biased and more benign portrayal of Hinduism in the educational system and in American society in general. In the last three years many similar incidents have occurred: the acrimonious debate about &amp;lsquo;Wendy&amp;rsquo;s Child Syndrome&amp;rsquo;; the Kripal and Courtright controversies; the indignation about the depiction of Hindu deities on bikini&amp;rsquo;s, slippers and toilet seats; etc. These transient outbursts express a solid and growing concern about the derogatory conceptions of the Hindu traditions, which still dominate the western societies and academia. In very general terms, the aim of this struggle could be put as follows: to make the world aware of the positive contributions the Indian culture and its traditions have made and can make to humanity. Since this is an aim I share, I would like to assess the NRI community&amp;rsquo;s progress towards its realization. This evaluation will take the California textbook controversy as a reference point, while addressing some of the broader issues involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translations or Travesty of Traditions? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:51:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In one sense, the title of the piece captures the nature of the tasks facing the contemporary generation, whether in India or in the Diaspora. This generation, unlike many from mine, is confident and self-assured; perhaps, it is proud too about the strength of its culture and traditions. Rightly so. However, personal convictions about the value of our traditions and culture do not automatically guarantee the truth of such convictions. Not only that. It is also the case that the history of India, and that of the entire humankind, requires of us that we are able to say and show what is valuable and what is not in our traditions. This history is the history of colonialism, subservience, and is further weighed down by the scientific, technological, economic and the military weight of the western culture. Today, we need more than a mere practice and a further continuation of our traditions; we need also to examine them honestly and critically in order that we may transmit what we found valuable in them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Follow Our Forefathers: The Nature of Tradition –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:25:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading this contribution and all the others (&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;) I hope to write, we need to keep the context in mind. The context is this: many intellectuals, both in India and among the NRIs elsewhere, appear bent on transforming our multiple traditions into a single &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. The problem does not lie in the transformation of variety and diversity into a unity. Rather, it lies in trying to fit our traditions into the straightjacket of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. While calling ourselves &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; might be a convenient way of talking, the danger lies in going further and trying to develop &amp;lsquo;doctrines&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;theologies&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;catechisms&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Ten Commandments&amp;rsquo; so that those around us in the West could recognize us as followers of a religion called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. (These reflections are also applicable to &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Jainism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Saivism&amp;rsquo; and all such entities.) In the course of my future contributions, I will look at some of the compulsions that force us to manufacture &amp;lsquo;Hinduism as a religion&amp;rsquo;. In this piece, I want to focus on the nature of traditions. What is a tradition? What differentiates religions from traditions? The second question will remain implicit until the end. By that time, we should have a better understanding of what it means to speak of a tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Understand the Western Culture?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 04:53:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin this contribution, the third piece about our culture and traditions(&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;), by sharing something you are familiar with. Very often, I have heard the NRI parents in the USA making the following remark:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I came to the US so many decades ago, I knew very little about Hinduism. My ignorance was driven home when I had children and they began to ask what Hinduism was. Because I had to educate them, I ended up learning more about Hinduism in the US (thanks to this or that organization or Swami) than during all the years I spent in India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
