<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Wittgenstein on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/wittgenstein/</link><description>Recent content in Wittgenstein on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 05:33:42 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/wittgenstein/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Explanations that trivialize experiences</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/explanations-that-trivialize-experiences-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 05:33:42 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/explanations-that-trivialize-experiences-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, especially in the Indian case, it is important to understand that stories are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; explanations. They are neither true nor false because they do not describe &amp;lsquo;factual&amp;rsquo; events; they do not claim that they do either. Unlike the Bible, the Puranas do not have to be true or known to be true for them to play the role they do in the Indian culture. The Indian myths neither allegorize virtues nor are they &amp;lsquo;disguised&amp;rsquo; histories. In other words, the presuppositions of your question (common ones in the western scholarship since the Enlightenment) are &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt; and based on ignorance about the genre of the myth and the roles they play. (I can only assert these claims having argued them &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/"&gt;elsewhere.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Social sciences are not providing knowledge, including the likes of Wendy Doniger and her children?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general pattern that has come to the fore is that Wendy and her children (including Jeffrey Kripal) &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt; portray the Indian traditions in an unfavorable light, even when compared to how religions like Christianity, Islam and Judaism are portrayed. This claim is made in several articles, independent of whether these religions and the Indian traditions are true or false, whether they are irrational or rational, and so on. The discussion is not about the truth-claims of these religions and traditions but about their depictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>