<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Religion on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/religion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Religion on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 16:56:48 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s not about respect for religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/its-not-about-respect-for-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 16:56:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/its-not-about-respect-for-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sacred determines what profane is; it is not about respect for religion.&#xA;The film &lt;em&gt;Innocence of Muslims&lt;/em&gt;  has turned cities around the world upside down in the past week, and threatens to continue to do so. “We never insult other prophets”, says the tenor of several Muslims, “so why can’t we demand that Mohammed receive respect? We respect others; why do they insult us?&amp;quot; Others argued that the anger stems from a demand for “freedom”: the right of a community to be free from serious insults against its identity and values.&#xA;As with the Mohammed cartoons from a few years ago, the same cliché appears in the debates: there must be more respect for the other. Everyone also believes that he has that respect for the other. But despite all that self-proclaimed respect, the world has not become more peaceful. What is going on then?&#xA;For Muslims, it is the religious issue of ridiculing the prophet. But for whom is Mohammed a prophet? Only for those who believe in Islam. That point applies to all religious symbols. Something is always a symbol for a certain person; what is a symbol for one is not for the other. Take a heathen like me: for me, neither the cross nor the prophet Mohammed symbolizes anything. The former is one thing and the latter is a human. The Sikhs in India may consider the turban as their religious symbol, but that is neither the case for me nor for a Protestant.&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Requirement to repent&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;Something is only a religious symbol within the confines of a particular religion. Outside, it no longer has the same symbolic value. What then does it mean to demand that non-Muslims respect Mohammed? Is it a requirement to recognize him as a religious symbol or as a prophet? In that case, it comes down to a requirement to convert to Islam. Without that step, Mohammed can never become a religious symbol or a prophet to me and any other non-Muslim. What then is the significance of the complaint that the film &amp;ldquo;pokes fun at the prophet&amp;rdquo; and that one should not do that?&#xA;Muslims argue that depicting the prophet Mohammed is profane, because the prophet has forbidden depictions of himself and Allah. The answer is simple: the prophet&amp;rsquo;s words are only valid for those who accept him as a prophet. This rule has no power for non-Muslims.&#xA;But the question is: are we doing something immoral by not “respecting” their sense of profane? To answer that, we need to expand our perspective. To this day, some Protestants openly criticize Catholics by calling the Pope “the Antichrist”, portraying the Catholic Church as “the devil&amp;rsquo;s church”, and condemning Catholics as “devil worshipers”. Europe had decades of wars over it. To this day those central theses of Protestantism remain profane to the Catholics, just as the existence of Catholicism itself remains profane to many Protestants. What should we do if it is said that one group should not do what the other considers profane?&#xA;As an Indian, I look with even more amazement at the demands of the protesting Muslims. For centuries it has been at the core of Islam to describe Indian traditions (Hinduism, Jainism, Buddhism) as idolatry and false demonic religion. According to Islam, Hindus worship Satan and his companions: their elephant god Ganesha, the adulterous Krishna or the phallic Shiva. That image is still current. Are such statements about the gods of India not offensive? Can one then demand that Muslims deny their basic doctrines on idolatry, God and Satan? If Islam did that, it would end its own existence as a religion. In other words, from a pagan perspective, the existence of a religion such as Islam (or Christianity) is itself “sacrilege.” The core of these religions transforms millions of people in Asia into idol worshipers and worshipers of the devil.&#xA;Muslims must be consistent: if they don&amp;rsquo;t want people to blaspheme their religion, they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it themselves to other religions and traditions.&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Superior to all&lt;/strong&gt;&#xA;In fact, if they are not willing to accept this conclusion, then the protesting Muslims’ claim comes down to this: the world must treat them as an exceptional religious community, equal to none and superior to all. Of course they believe that is the case. That is precisely why that belief is unacceptable to the rest of the world. The whole debate is not about “respect for other religions,” or “freedom of speech.” It is about a religious group, which considers itself superior to everyone else, demanding that all the world endorse the truth of this belief. Who is willing to do that? Not me in any case.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-reflexivity of Religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 23:17:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to answer the question of whether or not The Lord of the Rings (LOTR) is a religious story by testing against &amp;lsquo;religion is an explanatorily intelligible account of the Cosmos&amp;rsquo;. Does the Lord of the Rings give an account in which the causal and intentional explanations for the happenings in Middle Earth fall together?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the problems in testing a scientific theory and of developing one, I might add, is to ask the right question. The other problem, of course, is to find the right answer. Let us first take a step back and look at the claim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Worship a Human Invention?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 01:20:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us assume that the Church Fathers (or the Apostles or whoever else) planned to introduce an eschatological doctrine and some mode of worship. (Let us further assume that their reasoning or their strategy was something analogous to your impressions: their intention was to induce a sense of urgency and guilt.) Our problem is not to explain their possible motives but to explain the &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; of these strategies. Our questions are: why do all the Semitic religions (this reference to the Semitic religions is meant only keep the discussion simple) follow these strategies? Why are these strategies successful? (You can also go further and raise questions about their relative lack of success today in the western world, but we will ignore all such complications.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the process of answering these questions, you will inevitably be forced to appeal to the nature of human psychology. This appeal will, in its turn, make assumptions about human psychology: such is human psychology that these strategies are successful. If this assumption is made, you face a very serious problem with the fact that these strategies do not seem to work with a lot of human beings (atheists, heathens &amp;hellip;). In other words, you cannot explain the success of this strategy by appealing to &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; psychology. If you were to restrict it to the psychology of the believers &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt;, you will end up providing &lt;strong&gt;a circular explanation&lt;/strong&gt;: such is the psychology of the believers that they are susceptible to this strategy. (Instead, you might as well say that the strategy works with &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;people because it works with some people.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Suppose you take the following route: religion &amp;lsquo;works&amp;rsquo; only for those people who have a specific kind of psychology, you face the almost impossible task of providing some kind of empirical data across cultures and time. Further, you will also have to explain why people who were (and are) prone to guilt cease being believers. As though this is not enough, you will also have to explain why only &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; guilt-prone individuals become believers and some others do not. In short, this is an almost impossible exercise given our state of knowledge today.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As though these problems are not enough, any psychological assumption will have to answer two other important questions.&#xA;4.1. One is the presence of a &lt;strong&gt;manifest denial&lt;/strong&gt; of these psychological assumptions in the theologies of these religions. Worship expresses your love for God. Even if the Apostles (or whoever else) was a scoundrel (and the greatest genius that mankind has ever known) who used this claim as a palliative, why do people continue to accept and believe in it? Again, you will be forced to invent another psychological explanation: the believers are mentally deficient (in some appropriate sense of the term), whereas non-believers are intelligent enough to see through the strategies. Needless to say, this is simply an &lt;strong&gt;ad hoc&lt;/strong&gt; explanation without any kind of warrant or plausibility.&#xA;4.2. The second question is about the fact that the believers genuinely love their God. One will have to deny this. One has to insist that the believers mistakenly identify their feelings of guilt with love. Needless to say, the explanatory task here is of mind-boggling complexity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is a different kind of problem concealed in your difficulty, as soon as we realise that we need to explain the success of the strategies (to induce urgency and guilt). The intention of the apostles is not sufficient to guarantee its success: something called &amp;rsquo;the world&amp;rsquo; intervenes in between. It is not sufficient that I intend doing something to reach some goal in the world. I need to take the nature of the world into account as well, if I have to succeed. In short, the worry you express is a still-born child, if the goal is to understand what religion is.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Worship and eschatology (for instance) are not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; properties of an EI account. They are &lt;em&gt;contingent&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. given assumptions about our make-up, our capacities, and so on, we need to explain why all religions have such properties. In short, what I suggest is that, if we assume the existence of religion among human beings, all empirical religions will exhibit these properties. That is to say, if we come across a religion in some part of the earth that does not speak of worshipping God, does not have an eschatology, then my hypothesis is &lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One final point. I am not saying that everything that happened in history is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;. What I do say is that given the structure of religion, some &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of events had to happen. All religions are &lt;em&gt;compelled&lt;/em&gt; to speak of worship, eschatology and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defininition vs hypothesis: religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/definition-hypothesis-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 17:30:10 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/definition-hypothesis-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One confuses between a definition and a hypothesis. Definitions tell us how we use a word and which objects it refers to. In the case of the term ‘religion’, a definition should merely address this referential task: which things are we referring to, when we use this word. It cannot give us any understanding of the structure or properties of religion and does not have empirical consequences (much as defining any other word, say ‘species’ or ‘psychosis’, does not have empirical consequences). It merely points out the phenomena that are to be theorized. The result of this second process of theorizing is a hypothesis, which characterizes the properties or structure of a phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How do we understand the concept of Communal Violence?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 05:17:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all agree that events like the Gujarat riots are tragic and terrible. But what is the role of intellectuals in avoiding similar tragedies in the future?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why can’t religion be political?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the duty of the intellectual is to try and help us understand the nature of the events and the violence involved. In India and abroad, the concepts of ‘communalism’ and ‘communal violence’ are often used to analyse these riots. These tell us that the main cause behind the Hindu-Muslim conflicts in India is the use of religion for political ends. It is often added that religion itself is not responsible for the riots, but rather its misuse by power-hungry clerics and politicians. The harm of communalism lies in its mixing of political aims and religious identities, which is taken to cause violence. Let us have a closer look at this concept of communal violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neurobiological Theory of Religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 00:05:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask whether &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; a neurobiological theory on religion could &amp;ldquo;account&amp;rdquo; for the experience of the believers. The answer depends on what kind of an account you are asking for and what you have in mind when you say &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;. If you mean by &amp;lsquo;account&amp;rsquo;, whether it could predict or even explain, I do not think so. We know that, at the least, we are made up of atoms. Your question, in terms of the kind of challenge it poses (even though the degree of complexity changes), is identical to the question: could a theory in physics, in principle, ever account for our experiences? What does &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; mean here actually? There was a period when one thought, among other things, that it was possible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; to describe mathematics in a purely logical language. That is, many thought that mathematics has a &amp;ldquo;logical structure&amp;rdquo; and that, therefore, one could reconstruct mathematics aided by a suitably powerful logic. (It is called the &amp;lsquo;Hilbert program&amp;rsquo;, named after the originator of this research program.) Then a mathematician called Kurt Gödel proved that, in principle, we cannot even prove the truth of elementary arithmetic on logical grounds: even though we can generate true statements in elementary arithmetic (and know that they are true; they are called &amp;ldquo;Gödel numbers&amp;rdquo;), we cannot prove their truth. Nor can we prove their falsity. They belong to the class of &amp;ldquo;undecidable&amp;rdquo; statements. In other words, what appears obvious to many of us today, namely, arithmetic is &amp;rsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; in nature cannot ever be &amp;ldquo;proved&amp;rdquo;. This is an impossibility theorem that Gödel proved in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s. So, what we think is possible in principle turns out to be impossible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principle of Charity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2011 04:59:24 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before deciding about whether or not Vivekananda was ethnocentric, jingoistic or even plain intolerant, one has to understand what Vivekananda was saying. In doing so, the interpretative &amp;ldquo;principle of charity&amp;rdquo; requires us to render him maximally consistent.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the title of this thread: &amp;ldquo;All religions are true&amp;rdquo;. Spelling-out Vivekananda&amp;rsquo;s stance regarding this theme presupposes the ability to provide convincing answers to questions about what Vivekananda thought &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; was, what &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; was, and how the latter relates to the former.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religion ‘sui generis’?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/religion-sui-generis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 22:24:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/religion-sui-generis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a religion claims that it is the word of God and that the word is unconditionally true; and that, further, the word is about the Cosmos: everything that was, is and shall be. So, when I say that religion is such an entity, namely, it claims that it is the word of God and that it claims to be unconditionally true and that it is about the Cosmos, I am accepting the self description of religion. (However, the hypothesis that religion is an EI account formulates it without committing itself to any ontological claims. That is, it takes no stances about what specific religions say or do not say about the existence of entities. The hypothesis does not show how, and in what sense, the Bible, say, is an EI account. It merely says that The Bible has such a status to believers. If you reread the relevant paragraphs of &amp;lsquo;The Heathen&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; where I first formulate the hypothesis, you will notice that I formulate it conditionally: &amp;ldquo;If such a being exists, if such an account is forthcoming &amp;hellip; etc then we have an EI account.&amp;rdquo;) If we do not accept the self-description of religion, The Bible becomes a mere book and we cannot study it at all to say anything about Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What exists in India,  given ‘Hinduism’, ‘Buddhism’, etc. do not exist</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/what-exists-in-india-given-hinduism-buddhism-etc-do-not-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 20:45:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/what-exists-in-india-given-hinduism-buddhism-etc-do-not-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first thing is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://colonial.consciousness.googlepages.com/HeatheninHisBlindness.pdf&#34;&gt;my book&lt;/a&gt; is about the western culture and a specific religion, which brought the former forth. It is only &lt;em&gt;indirectly&lt;/em&gt; about India because I interrogate the way India was looked at by the western culture. I proffer some hypotheses about India there by consciously remaining within the western framework.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You are right in saying that I deny that &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo; called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Jainism&amp;rsquo; exist in India. Indeed, I show why the western culture had to &lt;em&gt;necessarily&lt;/em&gt; create (for itself) such &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;. This is one half of a story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Understand the Western Culture?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 04:53:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin this contribution, the third piece about our culture and traditions(&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;), by sharing something you are familiar with. Very often, I have heard the NRI parents in the USA making the following remark:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I came to the US so many decades ago, I knew very little about Hinduism. My ignorance was driven home when I had children and they began to ask what Hinduism was. Because I had to educate them, I ended up learning more about Hinduism in the US (thanks to this or that organization or Swami) than during all the years I spent in India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Family resemblances, language games, Wittgenstein, and debates on religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/family-resemblances-language-games-wittgenstein-and-debates-on-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 18:42:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/family-resemblances-language-games-wittgenstein-and-debates-on-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Balagangadhara points out an inconsistent reasoning of  the western and westernized Scholars, as well as the last 400 years of humanities scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let me summarise the dilemma. Some properties are necessary for some traditions (Judaism, Christianity, Islam) to be religions. If one accepts this, the threat is that other cultures appear not to have religions at all. For some reason or another (I discuss the reasons in chapters 3 through 7), other cultures are said to have religions too. However, the conditions under which other cultures are to have religion are precisely those that make it impossible for the Semitic religions to be religions. That is to say, if the Semitic religions are what religions are, other cultures do not have religions. If other cultures have religions, then the Semitic religions are not religions. The inconsistency lies in insisting that both statements are true.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Heathens are blind to religion?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-heathens-are-blind-to-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:03:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-heathens-are-blind-to-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of course, the concept of explanatorily intelligible account is not easy to grasp: if it were, the &amp;lsquo;heathens&amp;rsquo; would not be &lt;em&gt;blind&lt;/em&gt; to the existence of religion. However, that does not mean we cannot grasp it either.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am glad you are beginning to see why the story about &amp;lsquo;Jesus as a Yogi&amp;rsquo; (Sankrant&amp;rsquo;s famous interpretation) is wrong; and why discussions on Sulekha drive me sometimes to despair and the believers (remember Gargoyle Minimus?) into utter rage. Why I keep saying that we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we understand Christianity (Pradip Gangopadhyay even claims that no Christian has understood the teachings of Christ, except himself), whereas we simply do not know what we are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligibility: Religion, Belief, Meaning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/intelligibility-religion-belief-meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 23:44:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/intelligibility-religion-belief-meaning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by clarifying what the notion of intelligibility says.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first thing to keep in mind is that Religion &lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. transforms, renders, or any such synonym) the Cosmos (used interchangeably with &amp;rsquo;the world&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;the Universe&amp;rsquo;, etc) into an entity that is intelligible. In the process, and by virtue of it, the explanatory account makes &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; intelligible as well. That is, Religion is an explanatory intelligible account of both itself and the Cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How religion spreads? The uselessness of reinforcers and reinforcement</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-religion-spreads-the-uselessness-of-reinforcers-and-reinforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 18:06:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-religion-spreads-the-uselessness-of-reinforcers-and-reinforcement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ideas have impact on people. Theological dilemmas have impact on those who formulate such dilemmas and on the future generations. They undertake actions (of whatever type) to solve these dilemmas, where and when these people find such dilemmas important. In this way, one can make some sense of the claim that Christological dilemma propels Christianity forward. However, this explanation cannot (at the stage our knowledge is in) be incorporated into a historical explanation: was Thomas Aquinas responding to the state of theology during his time, or was he a fame-hungry man who wrote his Summa Theologica in order to become famous, or was he afflicted by a rare disease?.? In other words, if we try to explain why St. Thomas wrote Summa, there are so many possibilities that a selection of any one possibility becomes a matter of taste and of one&amp;rsquo;s pet theory. Moreover, even then, such a selection fails to tell us much about western history. Consequently, such an explanation cannot become a part of historical explanation, if the idea is to make history intelligible and coherent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What enables religion to spread?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/what-enables-religion-to-spread/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 22:11:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/what-enables-religion-to-spread/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: why religion spreads among (some) human beings? What is it about them that enables the transmission of religion?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This issue allows multiple answers. In this post, I would like to focus on the simplest answer to the question. In my theory, I presuppose an answer to the question: I assume that there is something in our constitution that allows religion to spread among human beings. The issue now is: why do I presuppose it, i.e. assume this state of affairs as a fact?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why the question about the origin of religion is ill-formulated?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-origin-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 23:18:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-origin-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Are there accounts about the origin of religion? Yes, there are at least two kinds. One kind tries to localise the origin of religion in human beings and the other in God.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. If religion is what it also says about itself, namely, it is the word of God, what are we trying to answer when we try to answer the issue of the origin of religion? Are we trying to give a scientific answer to the question, why God gave religion to humanity or are we trying to answer the question why humankind believes in the existence of God? If the former, then this question has been answered differently by different religions, i.e., this is the theology of these different religions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Could religion be a neural disorder?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/could-religion-be-a-neural-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 22:51:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/could-religion-be-a-neural-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Religion lays claim to truth, both about itself and the Cosmos. It is true the way no other account (that we know of) is. However, religion also generates (or brings into being) a configuration of learning. That is, it enables a coordination of different learning processes into a configuration. A culture is such a configuration of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Could religion be a neural disorder? I do not see how we could say any such thing unless we already presuppose (at a minimum) what we have to prove, viz., religion is untrue. One of the difficulties involved in disproving the truth of religion has to do with the fact that religion is true in a way none of the human cognitive products are. (Remember that its truth is founded on nothing else except itself.) Of course, we are free to say that all believers have some kind of pathology. (Many accounts of religion have tended to say this as well.) But this is an assumption that will not allow us to understand religion: we will see it either as a human product or as some kind of virus that affects human brain. In both cases, it is an assumption that begs the question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
