<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hinduism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/hinduism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hinduism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/hinduism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why study the Western culture?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two substantial questions have been raised in response to &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/&#34;&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;: (a) why do we need to study and understand the Western culture in order to access our own traditions? (b) Is it my claim that Buddha and Shankara (for example) are irrelevant to us? One other sort of &amp;lsquo;objection&amp;rsquo; too has surfaced, albeit disguised as a characterization of what I have said: (c) is not my position itself illustrative of &amp;lsquo;Eurocentrism&amp;rsquo;? These issues are intertwined.  Hopefully, addressing them together will lend some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Hinduism Exist?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-hinduism-exist/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 01:05:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-hinduism-exist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) Which evidence (what kind of evidence) could prove the existence of Hinduism?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) Idem. for the non-existence of Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I think these issues are far too important to allow for their dissipation as debating points. If we could arrive at something approximating a consensus, we will have made a substantial headway. At the least, we can critically read the material on Hinduism with our answers to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I suggest we begin with (a). To start the ball rolling, I will mention some possible kinds of evidence and formulate my problems with each of these possibilities. Anyone who feels inclined is welcome to join the building of the list at any point in time and add or delete depending on the arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which facts are relevant? Hipkapi and Hinduism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-facts-are-relevant-hipkapi-and-hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 01:37:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-facts-are-relevant-hipkapi-and-hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many facts are interconnected within a culture. (The same applies to Nature too.) Some hypothesis or another notices some of these facts as facts, and it is able to provide an explanation (using the term &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; rather loosely) for them. This explanation helps us understand the phenomenon (means merely the appearance) in question because the theory or hypothesis under discussion is able to show what that interconnection between the sets of facts is. (That is, it tells us of the pattern that unifies these facts into a whole of some sort.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Hinduism’ and hipkapi: an Imaginary entity –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/hinduism-and-hipkapi-an-imaginary-entity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 04:46:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/hinduism-and-hipkapi-an-imaginary-entity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What did the theory of gravitation do? Apart from describing the fall of bodies on earth, it also tied the motion of planets and the ebb and tide in the sea to each other. This theory allowed us to predict the motion of the planets and helped us discover a new planet in the solar system. In other words, it provided a theory that unified phenomena. Until that stage, we did not know that these three phenomena were linked together, and we had independent explanations for each of them. This is one of the things that a theory does: it identifies the phenomena that belong together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ontological and epistemological commitments of ‘Hinduism’—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontological-and-epistemological-commitments-of-hinduism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 04:37:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontological-and-epistemological-commitments-of-hinduism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The English word &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; not only carries multiple meanings it also appears to refer to many different things. If the context of the discussion were to help us disambiguate the reference of this word, it might not pose many problems for a serious discussion. Unfortunately, the context itself gets muddled. Each understands the question &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-hinduism-exist/&#34;&gt;Does Hinduism Exist?&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&amp;rsquo; in a different fashion. As though this is not enough, this confusion enters into other areas as well: witness the challenge for people to prove that Sikhism does not exist. The prima facie evidence seems to be the following: the word &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; seems to carry many different kinds of (ontological) commitments (i.e. when we use the word, we seem to make assumptions about the kind of entities that exist in the world), many different epistemological positions (i.e. how can either know or not know what that word refers to).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Lorenzen’s “Who invented Hinduism?”</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-lorenzens-who-invented-hinduism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:20:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-lorenzens-who-invented-hinduism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Summary of Lorenzen&amp;rsquo;s article: &amp;ldquo;Lorenzen doesn&amp;rsquo;t only cite Jesuits and Muslims, but also &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; themselves. His main argument is that Hinduism isn&amp;rsquo;t an invention by anyone in particular. It grew out of a need to establish an identity vis-à-vis foreigners (mlecchas). In other words, an identity by contrast with the &amp;lsquo;others.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is a world of difference between what one wants to argue and what one, in fact, argues. The above (accurate) summary literally begs all the questions the article intends to solve.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
