<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Orientalism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/orientalism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Orientalism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:41:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/orientalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Long Live Edward Said?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/long-live-edward-said/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:41:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/long-live-edward-said/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.standaard.be/cnt/dss30092003_002&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original Dutch article&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; published on Sep 30, 2003; English version is due to google translate and some minor changes]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Edward Said is dead. Last Wednesday he lost his battle with cancer. The influence of this Palestinian writer in all areas of the social sciences of the last quarter century is immense. Many will remember him from Delhi to Dar Es Salaam, from Paris to Chicago; many will also write in memoriams.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing India and the West—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparing-india-and-the-west-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 10:09:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparing-india-and-the-west-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&#34;http://asianetwork.org/ane-archived-issues/2008-fall/anex2008-fall-balagangadhara.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, published in ASIANetwork Exchange &lt;strong&gt;XVI&lt;/strong&gt; (1): 57–63.]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the last two decades, I have been pursuing an unorthodox way of studying cultural differences, focusing mainly on the Indian and the western cultures. Because I believe that one can answer questions about the circumscription of the words &amp;lsquo;Indian&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;western&amp;rsquo; cultures satisfactorily (Balangangadhara, 1994), I will assume their intelligibility in what follows. In this paper, I want to raise a rather intriguing problem about comparing these two cultures. I shall do that without looking at other approaches to the issue and in the form of an argument. In order to come to the point quickly, let me make use of Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Future of the Present. Thinking Through Orientalism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:40:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Though the book was published nearly two decades ago, Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt; continues to be topical. Many have rejected the message of this work; others have attempted to develop its arguments yet further. This article will not be one more interpretation of Said&amp;rsquo;s book; after all, there are many such interpretations, including Said&amp;rsquo;s own. Instead, it probes the phenomenon of &amp;lsquo;post-Orientalism&amp;rsquo;. Even here, the intention is not to map its contours either historically or conceptually. Rather, the focus is on raising the question: what next after &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the division between the West and East Orientalist in nature?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-division-between-the-west-and-east-orientalist-in-nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 00:51:45 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-division-between-the-west-and-east-orientalist-in-nature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is the division between the West and East Orientalist in nature? Well, that is what Edward Said says in his Orientalism; that is what many writers in his wake say too. I beg to disagree. Let me make but three points. One: that there is an Indian culture and a western culture has been established in my book. (Of course, it is also an experiential given.) Consequently, I have just presumed this distinction here. Second: some distinction does not become Orientalist just because the Orientalist thinkers use the distinction. Thirdly: that there exist empirical distinctions of culture etc. is not &lt;em&gt;denied&lt;/em&gt; by Edward Said but only that speaking about these distinctions leads to violence. A rather funny stance, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of Essentialism?—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-essentialism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 03:40:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-essentialism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have had difficulties in understanding the use and meaning of some words, especially &amp;rsquo;essentialism&amp;rsquo; and its cognates. Here are some uses of &amp;ldquo;essentialism&amp;rdquo; I am familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; to designate some basic or fundamental or determining properties of an object, as in: &amp;ldquo;Water is essentially H2O&amp;rdquo;. Here the claim is that some liquid is water if and only if it has the chemical structure of containing two molecules of Hydrogen and one molecule of Oxygen for every single molecule of the liquid in question.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; in order to understand counterfactual sentences involving proper nouns, as in: &amp;ldquo;If I were George Bush, I would not have gone to war with Iraq&amp;rdquo;. This sentence is a counterfactual because it begins by assuming a non-fact (I am Balu and not George Bush); picks out a state of affairs where this is true (a possible world where &amp;lsquo;Balu&amp;rsquo; IS &amp;lsquo;George Bush&amp;rsquo;) and makes a (true or false) statement about this (I might or might not have gone to war with Iraq). Many historical claims (and many scientific laws) have the form of counterfactual statements. Here &amp;rsquo;essence&amp;rsquo; is predicated to Balu (something like &amp;ldquo;baluhood&amp;rdquo;) so that Balu remains Balu even if he were to become &amp;lsquo;George Bush&amp;rsquo; in some possible world.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; to solve the problem of providing references to proper names, as in &amp;ldquo;Socrates was not a teacher of Plato&amp;rdquo;. In many cases, we identify Socrates as that person who has the property of &amp;lsquo;being a teacher of Plato&amp;rsquo;. If it transpires that such is not the case, we will still not be in doubt about the identity of Socrates because, much like the previous case, it speaks about some &amp;rsquo;essential property&amp;rsquo; of Socrates by virtue of which he remains the same person even when he does not have some or another accidental or contingent property.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One uses &amp;rsquo;essences&amp;rsquo; while solving the puzzle of identity, as in &amp;ldquo;This is me, a photograph taken when I was three years old&amp;rdquo;. Here, &amp;lsquo;me, when I was three years old&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;me in America during the 1990 AAR conference&amp;rsquo; etc. become spatio-temporal slices of an &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;. The &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo; has indefinitely many spatio-temporal slices and these are all slices of one and the same &amp;lsquo;I&amp;rsquo;. The idea is that one does not become someone else other than who one is because of the spatio-temporal career of &amp;lsquo;oneself&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even though there are many discussions about each of these uses, there is nothing wrong or illegitimate about using the word &amp;rsquo;essence&amp;rsquo; or indeed to &amp;ldquo;talk in an essentializing way&amp;rdquo;. Quite obviously, the &amp;lsquo;subaltern&amp;rsquo; historiographers could not mean &amp;rsquo;essentialism&amp;rsquo; in any of the above senses, because they suggest that essentialism is something to avoid. I know of one such use of the word in Said&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Orientalism&amp;rdquo;, where he suggests that to correlate climatic conditions with the psychology or culture of a people (something that often happened in the eighteenth nineteenth centuries) is to commit the sin of essentialism. Clearly, this is not the kind of essentialism that is at issue here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
