<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Basics on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/basics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Basics on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 10:41:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/basics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Western intellectuals are not idiots</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/western-intellectuals-are-not-idiots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 10:41:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/western-intellectuals-are-not-idiots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He says: &amp;ldquo;Doniger translates &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;. Apparently, Indians should not criticize that because we know neither what the English word &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; means nor do we know what &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; means because neither English nor Sanskrit is our mother tongue.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;First of all I do not say or imply that Indians &lt;em&gt;should not criticize&lt;/em&gt; the translation. I merely point out that (a) there is indeterminacy in translation across two languages and &lt;em&gt;therefore&lt;/em&gt; (b) we can only make &amp;lsquo;qualitative&amp;rsquo; criticisms. That is to say, one must suggest &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; the word &amp;ldquo;Dharma&amp;rdquo; should be translated in all those different contexts that Doniger translates it as &amp;ldquo;Religion&amp;rdquo;. Otherwise, the criticism (&amp;ldquo;that it is not an &amp;lsquo;accurate&amp;rsquo; translation&amp;rdquo;) is bogus.&#xA;Secondly, I did not say nor imply that we&lt;em&gt;do not know&lt;/em&gt; the meaning of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo;. That is, I did not claim that these two words are just as intelligible to us as the words &amp;lsquo;pif-paf&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;paf-paf&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;He further says: &amp;ldquo;We may have the word dharma in Hindi but it may mean something different in Sanskrit. Besides, both these words are ambiguous &amp;ndash;another reason we can&amp;rsquo;t criticize the translation since we don&amp;rsquo;t know all the shades of meaning of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; nor of &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo;. Similarly when &amp;ldquo;brahmin&amp;rdquo; is translated as &amp;ldquo;priest.&amp;rdquo;  Of course Doniger could have translated &amp;ldquo;dharma&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;perversion&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;brahmin&amp;rdquo; as &amp;ldquo;idiot&amp;rdquo; and since we don&amp;rsquo;t know what &amp;ldquo;perversion&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;idiot&amp;rdquo; mean either, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t really criticize that as well.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Again, I did not claim nor did I imply that we must know &amp;ldquo;all shades of meaning&amp;rdquo; (whatever that means in the present context) in order to translate. Nor does it follow from anything I have said that one could then use &lt;em&gt;any word&lt;/em&gt; in one language to translate &lt;em&gt;any word&lt;/em&gt; from another language.&#xA;That there is indeterminacy of meaning in translation does not entail that one denies that words have meanings, surely. Words occur in a language and a language has rules, conventions, dictionaries, and such like. It has a syntax, semantics and pragmatics of communication. Who has denied this? Quine has not; nor have I.&#xA;It is the linguistic convention to translate &amp;lsquo;dharma&amp;rsquo; as religion and &amp;lsquo;brahmin&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;priest&amp;rsquo;. One cannot fulminate against this centuries-old practice unless one comes up with alternatives and shows why the alternative is &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; than the centuries-old practice. Until such stage is reached, wisdom counsels us to keep quiet. To reach such a stage, &lt;strong&gt;it is not Sanskrit or English that one should study&lt;/strong&gt; but the relevant phenomena in the world to build a theory about the phenomenon in question.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The subsequent paragraph simply repeats the same misunderstanding without understanding &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/&#34;&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;. Of course, to understand my post and react to that, the presupposition is that one has read what linguists and philosophers of language have written about meaning and use. If one has not done this work, and has merely some vague common-sense ideas about translation, then one should have the minimal humility to keep quiet and not attack Doniger&amp;rsquo;s translation.&#xA;This, then, is the &amp;ldquo;point of my argument&amp;rdquo;. Do not think that western intellectuals are idiots and imbeciles. Being an Indian and a native speaker of some Indian language does not give you some marvelous ability to criticize the western intellectuals based on your common-sense ideas about the world. People like Wendy have put in years of serious effort to learn languages and theories and if one wants to take them on, one must make sure that one is their intellectual match. And that requires years (if not decades) of dedicated work. That is the &amp;ldquo;point of my argument&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Narratives vs Theories</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:34:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question requires deeper handling so you will forgive me for the brevity of my response but you will get some idea of where I stand.&#xA;Regarding the first question as to whether we reject social science itself, I am aware that many people have made this suggestion. I am not so much hung up on the word &amp;lsquo;social science&amp;rsquo; but I do believe that we need to systematically reflect on our experiences in the world. A systematic reflection on experiences in the form of a theory is what we can conveniently call social science. We need theories about the world to understand the World. Systematic thinking means use of certain criteria to decide which theories are good or not, etc. and which to choose. The best thing would be to appeal to the history of the natural sciences over say four hundred years to see how they have done it, what kind of criteria they used. Thus, I belong to the group which advocates systematic reflection on experience, and in that sense, I belong to the group which says we need social science.&#xA;Your second question was about Indians having different ways of understanding experience: you spoke of narratives and the autobiography of Tulsi Ram. This raises the question of what form these reflections are going to take. To give a crude example: are they going to be mathematized? Will they take the form of scientific laws or of narratives? That is a very interesting question. But all narratives are not social science: in that case every novelist would have a scientific theory. If a text is an autobiography, it is not social science.&#xA;pp 103-4 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A priori assumptions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:13:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am going to ask for a clarification on a question which I find very troubling. Let me first read how you have formulated the problem from the text: Sanskrit scholars need modem social scientists. What disturbs me in anthropological fieldwork is that Sanskrit literature is made to play the role of native informer to social scientists, with the anthropologists asking themselves as they might with Maori culture: is there something valuable which has been lost?&#xA;Claus Oetke also makes the same point. Even if you say that the dialogue between the primitive and the anthropologist is sophisticated, native informers are not merely informants. This idea, this interaction pattern which has existed for the last forty years has a double bias&amp;ndash;that of the anthropologist and that of the native informant. They have very powerful dialogues but anthropologists fundamentally take a priori positions, assuming that Sanskritists are the only ones who hold the key: they do not really believe that non-Sanskritists could possibly have anything to contribute.&#xA;But it would be absurd to dismiss Indian culture a priori without an investigation into India&amp;rsquo;s intellectual contributions without entertaining the possibility that Indian culture and tradition might today in a very significant sense be a challenge to the Western traditions which form our intellectual background. Your question shuts it out because it comes from Sanskrit. In your story of the fieldwork model, all Indian parameters answer the sophisticated social scientists model. I am surprised because you have another strand which goes in the opposite direction. But the fundamental framework you are using suggests maximally that we might learn something like Sanskrit aesthetics, rasa theory, etc. or even something like curry. This kind of trivialization has resulted from colonialism: it has been and is, very suppressive.&#xA;pp 42-43 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:36:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are multiple kinds of interpretation. For instance, there is interpretation of symbols in a domain like Physics: μ (in elementary optics) is &amp;ldquo;interpreted&amp;rdquo; as the refraction index of a substance. We use a more or less analogous notion of &amp;ldquo;interpretation&amp;rdquo; in Chemistry, Mathematics and so on. In logic, we speak of &amp;ldquo;interpretation of variables&amp;rdquo; like &lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;, etc. Here, it means that the letters stand-in for arbitrary sentences with truth-values.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Narrowing the search space, Ill-formed questions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narrowing-the-search-space-ill-posed-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 14:22:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narrowing-the-search-space-ill-posed-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Assume that you get a Ph.D student who wants to do medical research. He comes to you and tells you that he wants to find out an answer to the burning question about why people get sick. Would you be able to guide this student in answering his question or give one answer to it? Your answer would be: it depends. You would also further say to him, ‘choose a particular disease, choose a particular domain and choose a particular approach within that domain, if you want to do research’. There is no ‘one answer’ to his question. As a research question, you would say it is ill-formed: you have to specify the disease, and choose whether you want to do, say, genetic research or epidemiological research or cell research or…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Naming a phenomenon</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:10:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) Paolo Friere, a Brazilian educationalist, has spoken about such a phenomenon at length in his &lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt;. He calls it as an ‘internalisation of the oppressor by the oppressed’. Whether we use Paolo Friere’s terminology or the much later one of ‘Stockholm Syndrome’, the problem is the same: both &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; the phenomenon without &lt;em&gt;explaining it&lt;/em&gt;. In and of itself, not such a big problem if it is not for a cognitive tendency that is &lt;strong&gt;dominant&lt;/strong&gt; in the ‘social sciences’, which brings me to the second point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heuristics: traps to avoid</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/heuristics-traps-to-avoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 12:53:02 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/heuristics-traps-to-avoid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, one of the ways to test whether your search is taking you in the right direction is by seeing whether it solves a well-known paradox, or explicates it in a novel way. If after research, your hypothesis leads you to a well-known discussion in theology (but &lt;em&gt;lacks&lt;/em&gt; the latter&amp;rsquo;s sophistication), then you could be on an uninteresting track.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In certain phases of thinking, unbridled speculations have a serious contribution to make. After some time, it teaches one that there is a very interesting difference between &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/arguments-vs-theories/&#34;&gt;disciplined speculations and speculations of other sorts&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; and that one has to learn the former. However, the only way to learn the former is through the latter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Erudition</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/erudition/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 13:28:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/erudition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I keep teaching my students the need to unlearn: unlearn the desire to &amp;lsquo;show off&amp;rsquo; their erudition; unlearn shallowness and so on. I am more than convinced that whatever we have learnt about human beings can be formulated in a jargon-free language and in a simple manner. There is no need to appear &amp;lsquo;mysterious and profound&amp;rsquo;; nor is there a need for exhibiting one&amp;rsquo;s erudition or &amp;lsquo;critical capacities&amp;rsquo;. On all these counts, most of Foucalt&amp;rsquo;s writings (and that of his commentators) can only call forth anger and irritation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Law of Excluded Middle: Christian Beliefs</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 13:09:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was expecting you to show me where &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/&#34;&gt;the reasoning I formulated goes wrong&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, but you do not do so. The analogy you draw, I am afraid, does not quite do the job you want it to.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One can easily hold the following two beliefs (your example) without any fear of contradiction:&#xA;(a) There is only one way to Bombay (this is it) and (b) There are many ways to Bombay (this is one of them).&#xA;The &amp;lsquo;how&amp;rsquo; of it must be obvious: the &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo; is an indexical. Consequently, any person can hold both these beliefs together (at the same time or about the same route) without being contradictory (depending upon what he points out using the word &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo;).&#xA;In fact, even statements like (c) &amp;ldquo;Route 19 is the only way to Bombay&amp;rdquo; and (d) &amp;ldquo;Route 24 is one of the ways to Bombay&amp;rdquo; can be held to be true by one and the same person at the same time without fear of contradiction. ( Both  statements would be true if Route 24 allows one to join Route 19 at some point or the other.) In other words, Minimus, your examples do not work the way you want them to.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Regarding my reasoning, this is what you say:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hindus may have ideas/opinions about the beliefs of the Christians but &amp;ldquo;beliefs about&amp;rdquo; cannot be compared to &amp;ldquo;beliefs&amp;rdquo; and I think that is the error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central features of studies on Caste</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/central-features-of-studies-on-caste/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 11:23:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/central-features-of-studies-on-caste/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://creative.sulekha.com/the-hindu-defeat-role-of-caste_103411_blog&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; on Sulekha says:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;ut there can be no doubt that for the past thousand years at least the caste system has been a great nightmare for the majority of our people and continues to be a great bane of hindu society as well as hinduism today.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When you write this article on the caste system, I do want you very much to make clear where your &lt;em&gt;certainty&lt;/em&gt; regarding the nature of the caste system and its baneful impact both on the hindu and the indian society comes from. There is a reason for this request. For some time, I too thought that the ‘Indian caste system’ was an abomination. In order to find out where it came from, the nature of its foundations, and the causes for its continued reproduction, I started reading and researching into the question. Normally, research renders the questions &lt;strong&gt;sharper&lt;/strong&gt;, but in this case the subject became &lt;strong&gt;vaguer!&lt;/strong&gt; The more I read, the more confusing it all became: everyone seemed to be against the caste system (with a few exceptions) but no one seemed to know what it was! While each had very clear moral opinions on the subject, none had any clear understanding of what they were for/against. Consequently, my request: in your article, please (1) do not &lt;em&gt;assume&lt;/em&gt; that the caste system is an evil, but show that it is; (2) do not just say it is &lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt;that it is a bane, but demonstrate it;  (3) do not &lt;em&gt;just affirm&lt;/em&gt; that ‘the dalits’ are victims of an immoral and unjust social organisation, but show how and why they are that. So far, I have not been able to prove any of the above claims &lt;em&gt;scientifically&lt;/em&gt; (or even unscientifically). Everyone seems to assume it, and the (literally) thousands of books and articles I have read on this score fail miserably in even saying what ‘the caste system’ is, leave alone &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; that it is the cause of many social and cultural ills in our culture and society. May I look forward to something that at least provides me with a semblance of a proof?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How would one translate the word &#39;God&#39; into, say, Sanskrit?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-would-one-translate-the-word-god-into-sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 19:14:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-would-one-translate-the-word-god-into-sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here is the question: How would one translate the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; into, say, Sanskrit? Now, the answer has to satisfy certain conditions because the question also meets certain conditions. Let me say very clearly what all these are, so that the playground and the rules are transparent and favour no one party in the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I propose we accept the best theory of meaning that exists in the market place. As far as I know, the book that plays this role most admirably, while satisfying the proponents of different theories of meaning expounded during the last century or so, is Prashant Parikh&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Language and Equilibrium&amp;rdquo; (The MIT press, 2010). His formal apparatus allows for the existence of &amp;lsquo;word meanings&amp;rsquo; without sacrificing the idea that the meaning of sentences are context-dependent and makes sense of even such statements as &amp;ldquo;the meaning of red light is&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; That is to say, it does not restrict &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; to words and sentences alone; it also allows us to deal with &amp;lsquo;word meaning&amp;rsquo; as well, as it is in our case. If my colleagues unanimously prefer another &amp;rsquo;theory of meaning&amp;rsquo;, I would like to know what it is. In all probability, I would not take issue with an alternate choice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principle of Charity and Normativity</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity-and-normativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2017 12:38:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/principle-of-charity-and-normativity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This one begins to reflect about the principle of charity in relationship to the current US President, Donald Trump (from now on, Trump).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As you might know, the principle of charity has been formulated in different ways by different people. (Even the first page of a google search of the word ‘principle of charity’ allows you to access many of these documents quickly.) This post will stick strictly to your formulation: “a principle of charity says that (like the rain dance) a long-standing  practice should not be attributed to idiocy without strong evidence”. This formulation itself will not be questioned but assumed as a given. The only evidence used in this post is an extremely fragmentary viewing of the CNN and the BBC World coverages of Trump during the last week or so. (No thorough viewing of either of the two channels is claimed; the references in this post merely pick out fragments from programs as memory ‘recalls’ them today.) Two dramatis personae: Some media coverage and the event of Trump presidency; one question: what does the principle of charity do or advocate in the following cases? Such cases can be indefinitely multiplied but it is restricted here to five. One side of the argument is presented briefly only because that side of the argument is in wide circulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truth vs Usefulness of Theories</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-vs-usefulness-of-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 01:00:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-vs-usefulness-of-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the &amp;lsquo;use&amp;rsquo; or the &amp;lsquo;results and effects&amp;rsquo; of theories has a very venerable ancestry in the western philosophy. It is called &amp;ldquo;pragmatism&amp;rdquo;, if the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; is coupled to the &amp;lsquo;uses&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;results and effects&amp;rsquo;; it becomes &amp;ldquo;instrumentalism&amp;rdquo;, if the notion of truth is dispensed with. So, it might be useful if you were to familiarize with their arguments. (There is nothing specifically &amp;lsquo;Indian&amp;rsquo; with these claims, nor is there (of course) any need for there to be something.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Causality</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/causality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:44:07 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/causality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Causality&amp;rdquo; is not a notion in physics but  comes from philosophy. Perhaps, you have forgotten that there existed (and exist) generations of scientists and philosophers of science who deny that &amp;ldquo;causality&amp;rdquo; has anything to do with sciences. Some argue this by suggesting that scientific theories do not describe the structure of the world but are merely useful instruments in prediction and control. These theories are not &amp;ldquo;useful&amp;rdquo; because they identify the causal forces in the world (and, hence,&amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; in the semantic sense) anymore than the efficacy of the igloo proves that the Eskimo&amp;rsquo;s theory about the igloo is true.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gettier Problem, Doxa, and Episteme</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/gettier-problem-doxa-and-episteme/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 01:22:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/gettier-problem-doxa-and-episteme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Ancient (and modern) philosophers make the distinction between beliefs that are merely opinions of individuals and beliefs that are knowledge claims. Today, when modern philosophers speak of ‘doxastic coherence’ about the Greek thinkers, they do not merely mean that there should be a coherence in beliefs but also that Ancient philosophers have not produced knowledge but merely express opinions. Some also believe that all philosophy is mere ‘doxa’ but not ‘episteme’. The problem is this: what distinguishes a ‘doxastic’ sentence from an ‘epistemic’ sentence? One possibility was to say that ‘episteme’ was ‘justified true belief’ and not just a ‘mere belief’. This collapsed following the Gettier paradox which shows that this definition of ‘knowledge’ does not distinguish between mere opinion and knowledge. Today, one uses ‘doxastic coherence’ not as a technical term but as a judgement either about knowledge or about Greek thinkers or both or to signal that one thinks everything is an opinion. If one does not signal any of these, it is jargon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Falsification</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/falsification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 01:17:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/falsification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine I ‘hypothesize’ that I will win the lottery. If I buy a ticket and do not win, clearly my ‘hypothesis’ is ‘falsified’. Is it, therefore, scientific? Such silly hypotheses are dime a dozen. Do you think Popper was worried about this?&#xA;How to falsify my hypothesis. The answer is very simple: the way scientific theories can be falsified. I spell out some consequences of my hypothesis in Chapter 11. Even though there are more, if these ‘evidences’ as I call them there are untrue, my hypothesis stands refuted in its present form. You can also test the hypothesis by refuting other sub-hypotheses that are partially derived from the main hypothesis: like, the pagan relationship between ‘religio’ and ‘traditio’ that I postulate. If you can show that many, many authors from Antiquity deny my postulation and see ‘religion’ as that which binds all people together into one single community (for instance), my sub-hypothesis is severely damaged. Falsification is about the phenomena that a theory forbids from occurring; it has nothing to do with how to protect a theory from falsification. You cannot take a single conjecture and speak about its falsification: even according to Popper, theories are the basic units of falsification and not individual conjectures. To Lakatos and Laudan, the units are much bigger; to Quine, it is our entire web of beliefs, and so on. That is why I took the example of the Lottery ticket, which is an individual conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence vs Consistenty</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/coherence-vs-consistenty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 21:30:56 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/coherence-vs-consistenty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You say: “As far as I know, &amp;ldquo;doxastic coherence&amp;rdquo; means consistency in beliefs and that is all that is of relevance here.” It is not. Doxastic coherence is coherence between beliefs considered as opinions; its contrast set is “epistemic coherence” i.e., coherence between beliefs as knowledge claims. Further, in some senses, while there can be no coherence if there is no (logical) consistency between sentences within a particular theory, ‘coherence’ does not mean ‘consistency of beliefs’. One could have a coherent set of beliefs even if it comprises of mutually exclusive or even (logically) inconsistent subsets of beliefs. That is because (logical) ‘consistency’ is defined within a particular meta-logic, whereas ‘coherence’ applies to discourses. They do not, therefore, mean the same. One can have a coherent discourse, where multiple logics are used in different fragments of the same discourse. While some logics could allow material implication (or some other logical connective), other logics used within the same discourse might consider material implication an invalid rule of inference. This inconsistency (one and the same rule of inference is both valid and invalid) in two different fragments of a discourse does not make the discourse incoherent. In such a context, ‘doxastic coherence’ names a coherent discourse but does not pick out a (logically) consistent set of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assumptions, Warrants, Hypotheses and Heuristics</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/assumptions-warrants-hypotheses-heuristics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 21:13:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/assumptions-warrants-hypotheses-heuristics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You say: &amp;ldquo;there seems to be an underlying assumption that all participants in the thread seem to be making. The assumption being that all these texts have the same end goal in mind, and that this end goal is enlightenment/eudaimonia/happiness. I submit that such an assumption is unwarranted.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It is not an assumption but an explicit hypothesis, as far as I am concerned, that all the Indian traditions (not just these two sets of texts, namely, Upanishads and Puranas) are concerned with the same end goal. I want to provide a description of the Indian traditions as attempts to help human beings find happiness on earth. (For the time being, in order to avoid fruitless controversies and to have a point of departure, I take Aristotelian Eudaimonia to be an explication of this notion of happiness.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Assumptions often do require warrant, but hypotheses do not. Because the truth of a conclusion depends on the truth of the premise (often, assumptions function as premises in an argument) provided valid rules of inferences are used, it makes sense to ask for the warrant of an assumption. Needless to say, this condition does not hold for hypotheses: you have to evaluate them entirely differently.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of course, in one sense, such a reconstruction would be the hypothesis I propose. Until such stage, the belief about the commonality of the goal of the Indian traditions would be an assumption. However, it is not a premise in a logical deduction but one which functions as a heuristic. Consequently, if I need to convince you to accept this assumption for the time being, I need to show you what is cognitively interesting about this assumption.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;It promises to help explain the rivalry within the Indian traditions; it sheds new light on the inter-relationship between them in a different way than as &amp;lsquo;syncretism&amp;rsquo;; it helps one look for a set of problems underlying the Indian traditions; it allows one to formulate these problems in the twenty-first century language; it helps one evaluate the answers of these traditions and even carry them forward. These are some of the cognitive benefits of this assumption.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Of course, ultimately, it might turn out to be the case that no such goal is to be found and that the Indian traditions are not each other&amp;rsquo;s rivals. I do not know. For the time being, this idea appears very productive. That is enough of a warrant.&#xA;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defininition vs hypothesis: religion</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/definition-hypothesis-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2014 17:30:10 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/definition-hypothesis-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One confuses between a definition and a hypothesis. Definitions tell us how we use a word and which objects it refers to. In the case of the term ‘religion’, a definition should merely address this referential task: which things are we referring to, when we use this word. It cannot give us any understanding of the structure or properties of religion and does not have empirical consequences (much as defining any other word, say ‘species’ or ‘psychosis’, does not have empirical consequences). It merely points out the phenomena that are to be theorized. The result of this second process of theorizing is a hypothesis, which characterizes the properties or structure of a phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ill-formed questions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ill-formed-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 23:44:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ill-formed-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Assume that you get a Ph.D student who wants to do medical research. He comes to you and tells you that he wants to find out an answer to the burning question about why people get sick. Would you be able to guide this student in answering his question or give one answer to it? Your answer would be: it depends. You would also further say to him, ‘choose a particular disease, choose a particular domain and choose a particular approach within that domain, if you want to do research’. There is no ‘one answer’ to his question. As a research question, you would say it is ill-formed: you have to specify the disease, and choose whether you want to do, say, genetic research or epidemiological research or cell research or…&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is wearing a bindi religious?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-wearing-a-bindi-religious/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 12:18:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-wearing-a-bindi-religious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Depending on the context of the discussion (say a dispute about some aspect of the Indian culture), the disputants can treat wearing the bindi or a saree as facts. However, in another context of the discussion, these facts might become theoretical claims. For instance, is the Indian woman wearing a bindi or an Indian male wearing kumkum on his forehead being religious or not? Consider, for instance, the recent French legislation about wearing religious &amp;lsquo;symbols&amp;rsquo; in the public. If someone decides to take an Indian to the court, then wearing bindi or kumkum becomes an issue of dispute. Then we will have disputes: one side will claim that it is religious, and the other will probably want to say that it is not religious. (If it happens, I suggest they use &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;!) In such a case, wearing a bindi will be described using two kinds of theories about wearing a bindi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two kinds of research in social sciences</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/two-kinds-of-research-in-social-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 22:27:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/two-kinds-of-research-in-social-sciences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is, on the one hand, the intellectual tradition of expressing opinions and points of view. Here, as it suits thoughtful minds, one tries to express ideas carefully and in a nuanced fashion. Recent peer-opinions are taken into account; generalizations are avoided; the attention is on the specific and the concrete; and, where possible, one’s ideas are either founded upon or embroidered by some or another of the many philosophical stances that are available. The goal of the discussion is to endorse these opinions, or express disagreement on the broad idea expressed by the author. Any other kind of intellectual exercise of often seen as either nit-picking or engaging in polemics. To those who have grown up in this culture, it is obvious what the sought-after intellectual virtues are and how one should cultivate it. In other words, this culture surrounds itself with meta-arguments that is either founded upon or embroidered by some or another meta-philosophy about what intellectuals are, what their role in the realm of ideas should be and how they should relate to the rest of society.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is critique?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-critique/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 12:35:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-is-critique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a very interesting notion of &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo;: it begins with Kant and stretches through Marx in the German philosophical tradition. In fact, it is most developed in Marx when he says he develops a &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo; of political economy, a &amp;ldquo;critique&amp;rdquo;, which, he says, is nonetheless a &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo;. He does not develop a &amp;ldquo;scientific critique&amp;rdquo; of political economy: he develops a critique of the science of political economy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neurobiological Theory of Religion</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 00:05:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask whether &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; a neurobiological theory on religion could &amp;ldquo;account&amp;rdquo; for the experience of the believers. The answer depends on what kind of an account you are asking for and what you have in mind when you say &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;. If you mean by &amp;lsquo;account&amp;rsquo;, whether it could predict or even explain, I do not think so. We know that, at the least, we are made up of atoms. Your question, in terms of the kind of challenge it poses (even though the degree of complexity changes), is identical to the question: could a theory in physics, in principle, ever account for our experiences? What does &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; mean here actually? There was a period when one thought, among other things, that it was possible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; to describe mathematics in a purely logical language. That is, many thought that mathematics has a &amp;ldquo;logical structure&amp;rdquo; and that, therefore, one could reconstruct mathematics aided by a suitably powerful logic. (It is called the &amp;lsquo;Hilbert program&amp;rsquo;, named after the originator of this research program.) Then a mathematician called Kurt Gödel proved that, in principle, we cannot even prove the truth of elementary arithmetic on logical grounds: even though we can generate true statements in elementary arithmetic (and know that they are true; they are called &amp;ldquo;Gödel numbers&amp;rdquo;), we cannot prove their truth. Nor can we prove their falsity. They belong to the class of &amp;ldquo;undecidable&amp;rdquo; statements. In other words, what appears obvious to many of us today, namely, arithmetic is &amp;rsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; in nature cannot ever be &amp;ldquo;proved&amp;rdquo;. This is an impossibility theorem that Gödel proved in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s. So, what we think is possible in principle turns out to be impossible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Profound criticism 1: the logic is different</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/profound-criticism-1-the-logic-is-different/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 05:23:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/profound-criticism-1-the-logic-is-different/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many come up with criticisms like &amp;lsquo;Buddhist logics are different&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;one has to follow Indian logics&amp;rsquo;. These criticisms sound profound! They are damn shallow, unless they answer the following questions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is their structure?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are their axioms?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are their rules of inferences?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are some some crucial meta-logical theorems (do they all have deduction theorems?) etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What makes one an intellectual?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 06:51:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steve Farmer is not an expert on secularism only in the sense that he has followed it from the &amp;lsquo;outside&amp;rsquo; (meaning, probably, he has not written anything about the issue himself). Apparently, the reason why he has not contributed to the debate has to do with the fact that (a) no legitimate researcher can take the debate seriously; and (b) Farmer is one such. Witness how he describes it: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched this so-called debate for nearly a decade now from the outside, and nothing whatsoever has changed. Nor have I ever met a single legitimate researcher who took it seriously.&amp;rdquo; I wish some of the Indian intellectuals who have participated in the debate would read this judgment and digest what Farmer thinks of them. They will be thrilled to know that they are &amp;lsquo;illegitimate&amp;rsquo; scholars!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Usefulness of Dictionaries</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/usefulness-of-dictionaries/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 05:52:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/usefulness-of-dictionaries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opening a dictionary to find out the meaning of an English word might indeed be an elementary student&amp;rsquo;s choice, but, if used as a methodology for settling scientific and philosophical discussions, I am afraid, it is a rather poor choice. Imagine a physicist living around the turn of the last century doing something similar when Einstein formulated his special theory of relativity. &amp;ldquo;Oh! I say,&amp;rdquo; we can imagine this physicist saying, &amp;ldquo;The New Collegiate defines &amp;lsquo;mass&amp;rsquo; as an invariable property of an object, and this chap from the Patent Office calls it a variable!&amp;rdquo; I suppose one should be grateful to Einstein that he relied less on Webster to solve scientific problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arguments vs. theories</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/arguments-vs-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2011 02:42:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/arguments-vs-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have discovered that there is a fundamental difference between arguments and theory-building. As a philosopher, I have come to think that one could argue almost any position, within reasonable limits. Mostly, they consist of putting across plausible, or even logically possible considerations in order to show that either some point is plausible or that it could be true. Up to a point, arguments have a function: they force you to reason, check for inconsistencies, train your thinking process, etc. However, you must remember that ultimately all you have done is make a sentence or a set of sentences sound plausible or shown it to be logically consistent and possible. More often than not, it has a psychological purpose as well: that of shooting down some person, demonstrate intelligence, exhibit stupidity and so on. However exhilarating it might be at times, this is a very unproductive occupation, if carried on too far: one does not advance knowledge a great deal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why people resist to think critically?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-people-resist-to-think-critically/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 06:32:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-people-resist-to-think-critically/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have also come across expressions of similar thoughts and feelings both in India and in Europe and the United States. However, I think there are multiple grounds that generate such questions. Here are some I have been able to identify.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When people hear me say that the western intellectuals of the last three hundred years or more are completely wrong, invariably people skeptically wonder whether I think I am such a genius. Anticipating this (mostly) unexpressed question, I tell them that it is not a matter of psychology; I show that my theory answers the question (without making ad hoc assumptions) why the western intellectuals have been unable to see what I see. Even though they fall silent at this point, I suspect they do so not because they are convinced but because they do not know what else to say.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the hypothesis about colonial consciousness ad hoc?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-hypothesis-about-colonial-consciousness-ad-hoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 06:10:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-hypothesis-about-colonial-consciousness-ad-hoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have come to accept that the most interesting facts that a theory explains are those of the theory itself. Furthermore, a &amp;rsquo;theory&amp;rsquo;, which collects all kinds of facts first and tries to &amp;rsquo;explain&amp;rsquo; them subsequently, is worse than having no theory. Such a theory is completely ad hoc and is cognitively uninteresting. It is pernicious too because it generates the belief that one understands such facts, when, in fact, all one has is an ad hoc explanation. In this sense, I have not collected evidence for the statement that &amp;lsquo;Indians accept European reports as descriptions of their world&amp;rsquo;; nor am I explaining these assembled facts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Brahmins ‘priests’?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 04:01:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not have a theory of meaning. I do not know which of the many fragmentary theories of meaning I should choose from and why. Even though I acknowledge the importance of the topic, I do not feel called upon to do research on it. So far, I have been able to steer clear of the topic in &lt;em&gt;an interesting way&lt;/em&gt;: I am able to show that what appears as translation problem or a meaning problem (how should Sanskrit words be translated or the definition of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, etc) is, at least in some instances, actually not that kind of a problem at all. Such an attitude has generated a psychological bonus for me: I do not go around criticizing Jeffrey Kripal for not knowing Bengali well enough, or for Wendy Doniger for not realizing that Dharma is not religion or that Brahmins are not priests, when my knowledge of either Bengali or Sanskrit does not match up to what they know.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Indian Secularists do not think but talk?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:26:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to go deeper into the claim of &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-%e2%80%93s-n-balagangadhara/&#34; title=&#34;Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara&#34;&gt;my earlier post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; that Shabnum Tejanis and Neera Chandhokes of this world do not think but merely talk. In other words, is it possible to identify the problems with their accounts (that explicates more clearly why I say that they do not think) in such a way that it is susceptible to some sort of solution? If, indeed, we can show that such people do not think and we can show that their mistakes have some cognitive roots, then we can also provide additional explanations. In such a case, our answer would be richer and more complex than any other available at the market place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contrast sets</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/contrast-sets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:03:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/contrast-sets/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Contrast sets have multiple functions depending on the contexts in which they are used. For instance, in the case of theories about some phenomena, they can be used to test the robustness of the theories: why do unsupported objects on earth fall downwards instead of floating? Why did the Primitive Man invent &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; instead of doing any number of other things he could have done? And so on. In such cases, one might be looking for reasons to accept an explanation temporarily or one might even be comparing rival explanations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does one need a theory to discuss about phenomena?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-one-need-a-theory-to-discuss-about-phenomena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 06:51:56 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-one-need-a-theory-to-discuss-about-phenomena/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: &amp;ldquo;Modern prostitution is a very specific institution with the features of pimps, forced sex, kidnapped women, drug addicted women, immigrants lured to foreign shores on false pretences, and so on. If we insist on precision in ideas, then it is counterproductive to confuse matters by calling Apsaras prostitutes without first showing that at least some of the above conditions hold true and there is some structural similarity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, &amp;lsquo;modern&amp;rsquo; prostitution is all these things and more. However, I did not claim anywhere that Apsaras are &amp;lsquo;modern&amp;rsquo; prostitutes in any sense of the word. Nor did I suggest that there was &amp;lsquo;institutionalized prostitution&amp;rsquo; in India or that our stories suggest that there is such an institution in &amp;lsquo;Swarga&amp;rsquo;. The whole discussion is about a single sentence and I responded by laying out my reasons to call Apsaras as &amp;lsquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rsquo;. To say today what I thought was evident (&amp;rsquo;evident&amp;rsquo; because that is what I learned as a child), I do not need to have any kind of a specific theory about &amp;lsquo;modern prostitution&amp;rsquo; or even one about what &amp;lsquo;prostitution&amp;rsquo; generally is about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indians’ Barren criticisms of Western translations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 22:53:16 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indians-barren-criticisms-of-western-translations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: &amp;ldquo;Wendy Doniger translates all the Sanskrit words into English and thereby ends up distorting their meaning. Dharma becomes religion, Varna becomes color, and apparently she ends up even translating the names of some tribes into English.&amp;rdquo; Assuming that this is the case (assumption is on my part because I have neither read her translation nor do I intend reading it), what is the problem? Out of the conversation, the following considerations came to the fore: (a) if she had retained some of these Sanskrit words, the Indian scholars could have made more sense of the translation; (b) Dharma and religion are not co-extensive in meaning, any more than Varna is with color; (c) consequently, there is a great distortion in translation. Underlying this discussion was a (fragmentarily explicit) view about translation that if we do not find &amp;lsquo;accurate&amp;rsquo; translations of words form one language into another, we should retain the original words, assign them the status of `technical&amp;rsquo; terms, and not translate them any further.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuss about Indic categories II</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categories-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 22:14:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categories-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Social psychology, for instance, speaks of &amp;lsquo;categorization theory&amp;rsquo;, and we do use &amp;lsquo;categorization&amp;rsquo; also in the sense of classification. However, unless one gives a technical meaning to &amp;lsquo;category&amp;rsquo; (which one can), these usages do not violate the primary distinction between a word from some natural language and its meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider a classificatory scheme, say, cubes. Here, &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; is a word, it has some meaning, and we classify (let us say) some objects together. That is, we say that some objects can be categorized as cubes. However, by saying this we do not mean that some objects (say some coloured, and some wooden objects) are instances of the English word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;. (Assume that we are teaching English to someone who does not know that language. When we classify some objects and teach him the word, we are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; teaching him how the word is written, what the constituent alphabets of that word are but its meaning. Now he understands the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;.) What we mean is that each of these objects is an instance of the category &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; (i.e. the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;). Even here, we do not mean that the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo;= some physical object. (That is, we do not suggest that &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; looks like a physical object. The physical object is not an embodiment of the meaning of a word.) What we mean is that the meaning of the word &amp;lsquo;cube&amp;rsquo; allows us to bring descriptions of some other objects together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuss about Indic categories(concepts) I</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categoriesconcepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 21:21:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/fuss-about-indic-categoriesconcepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me give the gist of the consensus and overlook philosophical nuances about categories.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following sentences: &amp;lsquo;It is raining&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;het regent&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Es Regnet&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Baarish aa raha hai&amp;rsquo;. All these sentences have the same meaning, namely that it is raining. Or it could also be said that they all express the same &amp;ldquo;proposition&amp;rdquo;. So, &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;proposition&amp;rdquo; are used as quasi-synonyms; and sentences from natural languages have meaning or express propositions. Another synonym to &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; would be the &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; of a sentence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which facts are relevant? Hipkapi and Hinduism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-facts-are-relevant-hipkapi-and-hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2011 01:37:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-facts-are-relevant-hipkapi-and-hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many facts are interconnected within a culture. (The same applies to Nature too.) Some hypothesis or another notices some of these facts as facts, and it is able to provide an explanation (using the term &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; rather loosely) for them. This explanation helps us understand the phenomenon (means merely the appearance) in question because the theory or hypothesis under discussion is able to show what that interconnection between the sets of facts is. (That is, it tells us of the pattern that unifies these facts into a whole of some sort.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundationalism and Virtuous Circularity</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 04:49:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You do not want to call our natural sciences as &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo;. I do not even mind that. (For instance, you might want to define &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; as &amp;rsquo;true and justified belief&amp;rsquo;. You might show me that our theories in natural sciences are only believed to be true and are not proved to be true. Therefore, you might want to say that our natural sciences are not &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; according to your definition. Fair enough.) Since you want to conduct a discussion about knowledge and if our sciences are not examples of knowledge, I need to know whether there are other examples of knowledge. If such an entity exists, our discussions make sense. If we have no examples of knowledge at all, according to some or another definition of the word, how could we discuss about that? I mean to say, if not even the logics we use in out argument is an example of knowledge, how could we ever have any discussion about the scope, range, etc. of knowledge? We cannot. In other words, if we want to have discussions about knowledge, we need to have examples of knowledge and need to use these examples in our discussions about their nature. So, you have to tell me: (a) whether we have examples of knowledge; (b) what they are; (c) how we should use them in our discussions; (d) show that their use does not pervert our discussions about knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are a hindutvavaadin!</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-a-hindutvavaadin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 00:14:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-a-hindutvavaadin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the following possibility: let us assume that in some of my writings, I reach the same conclusion as some or another ideologue from Hindutva. (Of course, neither Steve Farmer nor Michael Witzel shows that this is the case. But that is not the issue.) In other words, let us assume that, with respect to some or another issue, I arrive at the same conclusion as people from the Hinudtva movement do. The question is: what does that indicate, or prove or is an evidence for? After all, Witzel, Farmer and others reach the same conclusion as the Hindutva people do, when you ask them about the sum of two integers (say adding two to itself); or (assuming the presence of relevant knowledge in both) about the chemical composition of water and any number of such allied stuff. They would also (probably) agree with respect to current geography, Capitals of different nations, and so on and so forth. Why is this agreement between them and the Hindutva not suspect? Why does some or another alleged agreement that I could have with the Hindutva make me a Hindutva man?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vivekananda and Caste Discrimination: theory-ladenness</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:52:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You ask whether or not it was &amp;lsquo;factual&amp;rsquo; that a &amp;lsquo;paraiah&amp;rsquo; was not allowed on the same street as a Nair or a Brahmin. The evidence we have says that a Paraiah was not allowed to be on the same street as a Nair, but it is not clear whether it also applies to the presence of a Brahmin. First, here is some of the evidence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Portuguese traveler Duarte Barbosa was among the first to talk about it in &amp;lsquo;The Book&amp;rsquo;. Though written in 1518, it became known to the European world through the Italian translation in the book of travels edited by Gian Baptista Ramusio. In the English translation, we hear who the Nairs are: &amp;ldquo;None may become a Nayre, save only he who is of Nayre lineage. They are very free from stain in their nobility. They will not touch anyone of low caste&amp;rdquo; . You need to keep in mind that Barbosa does not speak of &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo;, as an earlier footnote by the English editor and translator, Dames, indicates: &amp;ldquo;The word used in the text in vilam (villão in modern spelling) corresponding to the English villain in its ancient sense&amp;rdquo; . In other words, Barbosa appears to have seen a distinction in lineage or a distinction between the Nobility and the Rural folk when he saw the Nairs and the &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo; people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Facts’ are facts of a theory</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:39:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Until the sixties of the previous century, there was some kind of consensus about the nature of scientific enterprise. One strand within it had to do with the nature of facts. One thought that scientists collected facts (data) and formulated hypothesis (or theories) to explain them. This distinction between theory and facts was seen as an absolute distinction: facts (or data) existed in Nature (or culture) and theories explained them. However, today, the consensus tells us that this is not the case. (This distinction has been scrutinized from many different points of view since the fifties: in terms of language, in terms of the history of the sciences, in terms of scientific revolutions, in terms of philosophy of sciences&amp;hellip;) Today, one accepts that facts are not some theory-neutral entities existing in either Nature or culture and that the distinction between them is a relative distinction. All our facts are theory-dependent; in some contexts we treat some of the claims of a background theory as facts. In another context, the same facts are discussed as theoretical claims.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For instance, in some contexts, one takes the Hindus worshipping Ganesha as a fact. (This fact, for instance, functions as evidence that Ganesha is a god and/or that Hinduism is a religion and so on.) In another context, the same fact becomes an issue of theoretical controversy: are the Hindus worshipping Ganesha or not? (I challenge that nature of this fact and suggest that some kind of theology describes our actions in these terms.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paradox of Tolerating Intolerance</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/paradox-of-tolerating-intolerance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 22:59:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/paradox-of-tolerating-intolerance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Social issues, inherently, are neither paradoxical any more than they are contradictory. It is the &lt;em&gt;formulation&lt;/em&gt; of these issues that gives birth to paradoxes, contradictions and such like. (For the simple reason that &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;contradiction&amp;rsquo;, etc. are properties of statements, not of objects and events.) If there is a &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo; of freedom, then it lies not in the situation where one tradition (or even a set of traditions) meets another: that is to say, it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the situation of Indian traditions meeting religions like Christianity and Islam that gives birth to the &amp;lsquo;paradox&amp;rsquo;. Rather, it is by describing this meeting of the Indian traditions with religions like Christianity and Islam &lt;em&gt;as an issue involving freedom&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. conceptualizing this meeting in terms of freedom) that one generates the paradox. There exist &lt;em&gt;other descriptions&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; give birth to this &amp;lsquo;paradox of freedom&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refutation</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/refutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 05:43:55 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/refutation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My book is not about India but about the western culture. It is a study of the western culture using one thread, namely, religion. To the extent I talk about India, I do so using some of the &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; that Indologists (and others) have so far used. My use of their facts (to show the opposite of what they believe they have shown) illustrates the consensus in the philosophies of sciences (of the last hundred years or more) that &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; are mostly facts of a theory.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commonalities and Similarities—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/commonalitiessimilarities-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 05:37:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/commonalitiessimilarities-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Whether or not we observe &amp;lsquo;commonalities&amp;rsquo; has to do with the descriptive framework we use. Things might share common properties in one description; at the same time, share nothing common in another description. Both could be true descriptions of the same set of objects. &amp;lsquo;Perception of similarity&amp;rsquo; is (at the moment our knowledge is in) is extremely difficult to analyze and understand. On the one hand, our perceptual abilities (as they have evolved out of a successful adaptation to the world) must tell us what is present in the world. Otherwise, we could not have evolved. (We share this with other products of evolutionary development, i.e. with other species.) On the other hand, we cannot &lt;em&gt;say&lt;/em&gt; what that similarity is without using a descriptive frame work. (When the notion of &amp;lsquo;similarity&amp;rsquo; poses such problems, the problem of &amp;lsquo;commonality&amp;rsquo; is even more difficult to solve. This is a matter of &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; philosophical debate: do two objects share the &amp;lsquo;common property&amp;rsquo; of &amp;ldquo;being blue&amp;rdquo; or are they merely similar to each other?) Even though I have no solution to this problem, I fail to see the relevance of solving it for my enterprise.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2.1. You say: &amp;ldquo;While our Western observers mistakenly saw religion in India…&amp;rdquo;. As a scientist, you should know that Nature cannot be cut at its joints because Nature does not have joints. It is our theory (or description) of the world that allows us to speak of (relatively) independent phenomena like gravitation, electrical forces, magnetism, nuclear attraction and such like. Again, it is our theories that try to unify these forces. That is to say, our theories first distinguished them, only to try and unify them at a later stage. The same applies to culture. The western observers did not &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; religion; their hypothesis about religion allowed them to construct a phenomenon (from a set of facts which their hypothesis singled out as relevant) &lt;em&gt;they&lt;/em&gt; called Hinduism &lt;em&gt;as a religion&lt;/em&gt;. So, unless you are willing to argue that cultures comprise of distinct and discrete phenomena called &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;politics&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;secular&amp;rsquo; and such like, you cannot claim that the western observers saw &amp;lsquo;something&amp;rsquo; that is discrete and that they mistakenly described it as a religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Superiority</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/cognitive-superiority/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 05:24:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/cognitive-superiority/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is partly a term of the art (in the philosophy of sciences) and partly retains the commonsense usage. When one compares theories (in order to choose the best one among the rivals), one compares them with respect to the important properties that theories should have. What these properties are depends upon the philosophy of science one subscribes to. For instance, one might think that a theory should explain phenomena. If this demand is put, then one chooses a theory that does a better job at explaining the phenomenon. One might add additional conditions to this demand in order to clarify what it means to explain &amp;lsquo;better&amp;rsquo;. For instance, one might want to say that some theory X explains a phenomenon better than theory Y if X can explain some additional things as well, or explains things that theory Y cannot explain. One might further add that the theory X should be falsifiable or that it has more facts in its favor. Or, again, one could suggest that the theory X is better than Y because X solves more problems than Y. Or again, that X is more useful in prediction than Y. And so on. In other words, what constitutes &amp;lsquo;better&amp;rsquo; (in the claim that theory X is better than theory Y) depends very much on the kind of philosophy of science that one accepts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use and Mention</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/use-and-mention/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 05:04:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/use-and-mention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;All works of Balagangadhara make use of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Use%E2%80%93mention_distinction&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;use-mention distinction&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;. Please get familiarized with this distinction.&#xA;In logic the words &amp;lsquo;use&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;mention&amp;rsquo; are sometimes used in a technical sense to mark an important distinction, which is explaind by example:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;lsquo;London&amp;rsquo; is a word six letters long.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;London is a city.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In 1 the word &amp;lsquo;London&amp;rsquo; is said to be mentioned; in 2 the word &amp;lsquo;London&amp;rsquo; is said to be &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; (and not mentioned).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Hinduism’ and hipkapi: an Imaginary entity –S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/hinduism-and-hipkapi-an-imaginary-entity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 04:46:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/hinduism-and-hipkapi-an-imaginary-entity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What did the theory of gravitation do? Apart from describing the fall of bodies on earth, it also tied the motion of planets and the ebb and tide in the sea to each other. This theory allowed us to predict the motion of the planets and helped us discover a new planet in the solar system. In other words, it provided a theory that unified phenomena. Until that stage, we did not know that these three phenomena were linked together, and we had independent explanations for each of them. This is one of the things that a theory does: it identifies the phenomena that belong together.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intentional operator and inconsistent reasoning</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 20:10:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A Christian netizen says:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;here is within exclusive religions the claim that theirs is the only way to God (that claim can be true or false). There is in inclusive religions the claim that there are several ways to God and that it is quite possible that one of the exclusive ones (or many of them) are also ways to God. Both these statements cannot be true at the same time iff the logical law of excluding the middle holds. I don&amp;rsquo;t think that I have come across a way around this except through it &amp;ndash; i.e. one of the claims must be false or worst case both are false (there is no God or there is no path yet).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whose view is better?—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/whose-view-is-better-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 03:32:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/whose-view-is-better-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Every one of us believes our own viewpoint to be the best one: such is human nature.&amp;rdquo; This is not quite how I would put it. Let me, therefore say what I think with respect to this issue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whenever I formulate a theory, I believe that my description is &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;. If I thought that it was &amp;lsquo;false&amp;rsquo;, I would not write what I write. This is a belief about the status of my description and its relationship to the part of reality I describe. Let us call this the &amp;lsquo;object-level&amp;rsquo; belief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On explanations that make people stupid—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-explanations-that-make-people-stupid-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 00:57:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-explanations-that-make-people-stupid-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not believe that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; cultural practice (i.e. a practice that has survived and been transmitted through successive generations) should be explained by attributing beliefs to its practitioners in such a way that the beliefs make the practitioners come out stupid. Why do I say this? There are primarily two reasons: our ignorance and the principle of &amp;lsquo;charity&amp;rsquo;. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) &lt;strong&gt;Our ignorance&lt;/strong&gt;. We know very little about how cultures come into being, how they reproduce themselves and how they disappear. Until such a stage, where we are able to discuss each cultural practice (like rain dance, for example) individually, we should avoid making a virtue of our ignorance. One could come up with any number of explanations today to explain a cultural practice like rain dance. Without exception, they would &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; be ad hoc in nature and, as such, the opposite of what a scientific explanation is. Therefore, my criticism of such explanations is to show their ad hoc character and, where possible, identify what makes them ad hoc. The purpose? To move forward in order to develop a science of cultures and cultural differences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Shivalinga ‘mean’ phallus? A theoretical dispute</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 18:58:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: &amp;ldquo;In the context of puja, does Shivalinga denote or connote anything other than Shiva, in particular &amp;ldquo;phallus&amp;rdquo;? A Wendy says &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;, a Balu says &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;. For some person, not on this board, there is not a dialog; it is a reading of Wendy, a reading of Balu - how to decide between the two answers, which one represents the truth about Hindus?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Depending on the patience of the visitor, a number of answers are possible including an identification of the nature of the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
