<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Reservations on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/reservations/</link><description>Recent content in Reservations on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:54:54 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/reservations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Between ignorance and deception: Satish Deshpande's idea of reservations</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:54:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Clearly, advocates of the caste-based reservation system are worried by the recent upheavals in Gujarat and beyond. In his &amp;ldquo;The Patidar idea of reservations&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt;, September 5), Delhi University sociologist Satish Deshpande attempts to ridicule the Patidars&amp;rsquo; demand for OBC status while expressing his support for the reservation system. In this piece, I do not wish to defend or attack any particular movement, such as that of the Patidars or the Gujjars, but merely draw attention to one simple point: Deshpande attempts to defend ignorance and immorality by drawing on arguments that exhibit the same properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Which intolerance is growing in India?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:42:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly loud voices are to be heard from different capital cities in India about growing intolerance in Indian society. The western press picks up echoes and magnifies them, while ridiculing Modi’s visit to Great Britain. While one can understand that Indians chant mantras, why are Europeans reproducing them? Looking from the outside, this is a very puzzling phenomenon. Because it is unclear what exactly is at stake here, I’d like to raise some questions and reflect about them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How about speaking the truth about reservations?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 12:20:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens to the future of Indian intellectual scene when most of projects driven by its intelligentsia propagate perverted truths for self-seeking purposes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Satyam Vada, Dharmam Chara”, “Satyameva Jayate”&lt;/em&gt; are but two of the well-known Sanskrit sayings that are supposed to indicate the values placed upon truth and truth-telling in Indian culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes as a surprise, therefore, to read three items in the newspaper and a comment on a blog which seem to follow ‘truth’. But in such a way that &lt;em&gt;it becomes perverse&lt;/em&gt;. Because all the four issues are important, I would like to briefly talk about each.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Caste-based reservations and 'social justice'</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/caste-based-reservations-and-social-justice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 23:52:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/caste-based-reservations-and-social-justice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s paper on &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/16478230/Caste-based_reservation_and_social_justice_in_India"&gt;Caste-based reservations and &amp;lsquo;social justice&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Indian View from Outside: Quotas, Rational &amp; Moral?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-view-from-outside-quotas-rational-moral/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 19:19:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-view-from-outside-quotas-rational-moral/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Read Jakob de Roover&amp;rsquo;s piece on &lt;a href="http://www.dailyo.in/politics/satish-deshpande-patidar-reservation-system-india-dalits-obcs-hardik-patel/story/1/6119.html"&gt;reservations on dailyon.in&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; on &lt;a href="http://swarajyamag.com/politics/counterview-ambedkar-was-wrong-about-hinduism-the-right-can-stop-trying-to-appropriate-him/"&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt;. From the perspective of constitution, constitution debates, check &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/16478230/Caste-based_reservation_and_social_justice_in_India"&gt;https://www.academia.edu/16478230/Caste-based_reservation_and_social_justice_in_India&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem that has plagued India since Independence has flared up again: caste-based reservations for education, employment and career promotions. In the last four decades of living in Europe, I have heard both sides of the debate. As an Indian living abroad, it appears to me that these debates actually raise one single question: Are Indians irrational or immoral, or both? This is the un-debated side of the reservation discourse in India. Let me explain. Is caste-based reservation a rational policy to follow? The answer to this question does not require a definition of ‘rationality.’ Instead, the issue is: does this policy eventuate in irrational consequences or effects?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>