<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Review on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Review on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:47:09 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Review of Imagining Hinduism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-imagining-hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:47:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-imagining-hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Review of &lt;em&gt;Imaging Hinduism: A Postcolonial perspective.&lt;/em&gt; By Sharada Sugirtharajah. Routledge, 2003. 164 pages&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; This book is the first of its kind to bring post-colonial perspectivesinto a study of Hinduism. Consequently, there are no conventionalreference points for the author to use to build her narrative. She has to figure out how to use the conceptual apparatus ofthe one to study the other. In this sense, although the bookis experimental in its nature, there is nothing hesitant ortentative about some of the conclusions she draws. How successfulis the author in bringing the two, the study of Hinduism anda post-colonial perspective, together? If someone is influencedby post-colonial thought, the judgment will have to be in thepositive. However, having never been enamored by this genreof thinking, I find her framework both limiting and damagingto the study of Hinduism. Before I identify some of my problems,a few words about the book are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and Imagination: A Critical Notice of Halbfass and Inden</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 07:10:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the last decade or so, a new restlessness has begun to disturb the calm facade of the social scientific academia. As yet, it has no name. Better said, it has many names: from &amp;lsquo;reflexive&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;lsquo;post-modern&amp;rsquo;. The ferment is not widespread, but the voices of discontent are coherent and articulate. The critical voices indicate the many kinds of dissatisfaction they have with the status and nature of social sciences. Even though most dissenters cannot be grouped as representatives of any one tradition, many of their writings stand out above the rest. Two such authors are Wilhelm Halbfass and Ronald Inden; each has written a book that is worthy of attention and respect.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Staal’s Rules Without Meaning –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:25:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FRITS STAAL. &lt;em&gt;Rules Without Meaning: Ritual, Mantras and the Human Sciences. Toronto Studies in Religion&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 4. New York and Bern: Peter Lang, 1989 xxii+490.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to set the tone of this review article, let me begin straightway with a confession: I have been a closet admirer of Frits Staal ever since I discovered his writings in 1987. The reasons that undergird my attitude are several: firstly, most of his writings are about a culture I am familiar with, namely, India; secondly, absent from them is the dewy-eyed romanticism that is pernicious to any serious study of cultures and people; thirdly, present in them are insights that are immensely important and extremely exciting; fourthly, the theses argued for are the results of absolutely pioneering research which fly in the face of deeply entrenched commonsense wisdom; and so on… He is my fellow-traveler on more tracks than one, and my own thinking on several subjects over the last few years carry the deep imprint of Staal&amp;rsquo;s rigorous thinking and painstaking enquiries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Amartya Sen&#39;s Argumentative Indian—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:17:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, there are multiple images of India current in the West. There is the mystic India, an image that the German Romantics created and the &amp;lsquo;flower children&amp;rsquo; of the sixties made popular. There is the third world India with enormous poverty and suffering, which the developmental workers have projected. There is also the India, the centre of IT outsourcing, which the developments in the last decade have brought into existence, and so on. Amartya Sen, the Indian noble prize-winner in Economics, has written a book on &amp;ldquo;The Argumentative Indian&amp;rdquo; which speaks of an India that he wants us to consider. This India is an India with a history of toleration and pluralism, an India that has brought forth its own version of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo;, and an India that is every bit rational, discursive and analytical as the western culture itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
