<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wendy Doniger on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/wendy-doniger/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wendy Doniger on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 07:00:40 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/wendy-doniger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Wendy Incident: A View from Europe--SN Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-wendy-incident-a-view-from-europe-sn-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 07:00:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-wendy-incident-a-view-from-europe-sn-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/TheHeathenInHisBlindness/conversations/messages/6548&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am from Bangalore, India, but work as a professor in Belgium, Europe. My name is not Batra but am known as ‘Balu’. I am not, nor have I ever been, a member of either the BJP (the nationalist party in India) or organizations collectively known as the ‘Sangh Parivar’. Even though I am born a ‘Hindu’, some of my ‘liberal’ associates are convinced that I am a ‘crypto-Christian’. So much about my credentials, which are required to make two points of some importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current state of Scholarship about India: outlook articles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/current-state-of-scholarship-about-india-outlook-articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 09:20:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/current-state-of-scholarship-about-india-outlook-articles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20140529022325/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289559&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jakob de Roover&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Untangling the knot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20140331032610/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289711&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sufiya Pathan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;No Alternative&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20140406000302/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289733&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Disturbing Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20100406044846/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?264014&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;How Free are We?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110204003153/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?237702&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Indian Jews&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110605054740/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?235020&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;What can India offer?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hindering the emergence of alternative explanations: Colonialism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/hindering-the-emergence-of-alternative-explanations-colonialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 02:40:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/hindering-the-emergence-of-alternative-explanations-colonialism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I suggested that the psychoanalytical explanations (like the transformation of Linga into a penis as a fertility symbol etc.) not only trivialize and distort but also deny access to our own experience. In this post, I want to highlight &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of the consequences of transforming our experiences in this fashion. In at least two different ways, &lt;em&gt;these explanations hinder the emergence of alternative or different explanations of our experiences&lt;/em&gt;. This is relevant to both of us. That is why, when confronted with such explanations, we do not know &lt;em&gt;what to say&lt;/em&gt;. These explanations rob us not only of our experience; while doing so, they shut us up as well. As far as you are concerned, while rendering you deaf to the silence from our end, it further &lt;em&gt;blinds&lt;/em&gt; you. If this is the case, one might as well ask oneself what you describe. Are you describing what you &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; in the mystical Ramakrishna? You could not: after all, what can you see, when you are blind? Nor it could be that you describe what you hear: you have become deaf to us. What, then, are you describing when you describe &lt;em&gt;your experience&lt;/em&gt;? This issue is what this post will be about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Patrick Hogan’s &#39;Why Hindus should be grateful to Wendy Doniger&#39;—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:04:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Patrick Hogan,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is jolly good of you, as the British say, to contribute to the &amp;rsquo;literary landscapes&amp;rsquo; column in Sulekha at this particular juncture. I am glad too that you put across some thoughtful considerations without being polemical, and that can only help generate a stimulating discussion among all the concerned parties. However, the way you frame your points make the task an exercise in walking on a tight rope.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about people and their cultures?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:53:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us begin in a very intuitive way and ask ourselves this question: where do we encounter &amp;lsquo;cultural differences&amp;rsquo;? In human contacts, of course. What kind of human contacts? &lt;em&gt;In inter-individual contacts&lt;/em&gt;. That is, we see (or sense, or intuit or whatever) cultural differences in our contacts with &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; human beings. You do not meet &amp;rsquo;the western culture&amp;rsquo; but individual Americans, Germans, French, etc. Neither do these individuals meet &amp;rsquo;the Indian culture&amp;rsquo;: they meet individual Indians (or, even better, a &amp;lsquo;Madrasi Brahmin&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;lsquo;Gujerati Baniya&amp;rsquo; - even these are general categories but I use them just to get the point across.) And yet, we appear to see cultural differences in these contacts. How to make &amp;lsquo;sense&amp;rsquo; of &lt;em&gt;this experience&lt;/em&gt;? Let us first see what is partially involved to truly appreciate the complexity of our &amp;lsquo;perception&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Each individual human being is a complex combination of at least four aspects. There is his biological (or genetic) inheritance; there is his &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; inheritance (whether he is from the Middle Ages or from a capitalist society); there is his psychological makeup (let us say his &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;); and there is his cultural upbringing (whether he is a Madhva Brahmin or a Lingayat, say). When we meet individuals, in many different ways we notice these &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt;: the biological, the psychological and, after some time perhaps, &amp;rsquo;the social&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the cultural&amp;rsquo;. Let us bracket the biological away so that the situation becomes deliciously complex. Let us agree to use the following &amp;lsquo;words&amp;rsquo; (they are just words for now) in order to go ahead and raise the problem. Let us call the &amp;lsquo;social aspects&amp;rsquo; of a person the &amp;lsquo;sociality&amp;rsquo; of the person; the psychological aspects the &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo; of the person; and the &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; aspects the &amp;lsquo;culturality&amp;rsquo; of the person. Thus we meet individual human beings and see the differences between ourselves and the other human beings. What kinds of differences do we see?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Social sciences are not providing knowledge, including the likes of Wendy Doniger and her children?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The general pattern that has come to the fore is that Wendy and her children (including Jeffrey Kripal) &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt; portray the Indian traditions in an unfavorable light, even when compared to how religions like Christianity, Islam and Judaism are portrayed. This claim is made in several articles, independent of whether these religions and the Indian traditions are true or false, whether they are irrational or rational, and so on. The discussion is not about the truth-claims of these religions and traditions but about their depictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denying Experience: Do Hindus ‘worship’? Do they do Pooja to phallus (linga)?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 20:46:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone, let&amp;rsquo;s say her name is Wendy Doniger, comes along and sniggers &amp;lsquo;when you worship the lingam, you worship a phallus&amp;rsquo;. I do not identify Wendy&amp;rsquo;s statement as an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation. I say that it trivializes what I am doing by providing a distorted description of what I do. Here is what I say: &amp;ldquo;I am doing Puja to Shiva.&amp;rdquo; No discussion about &amp;lsquo;Lingam&amp;rsquo; or its many meanings. This is a &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; way of conducting a discussion. She cannot, therefore, argue that I am giving an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation because I am not giving an &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of what I am doing but merely describing it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Shivalinga ‘mean’ phallus? A theoretical dispute</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 18:58:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/does-shivalinga-mean-phallus-a-theoretical-dispute-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Question: &amp;ldquo;In the context of puja, does Shivalinga denote or connote anything other than Shiva, in particular &amp;ldquo;phallus&amp;rdquo;? A Wendy says &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;, a Balu says &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;. For some person, not on this board, there is not a dialog; it is a reading of Wendy, a reading of Balu - how to decide between the two answers, which one represents the truth about Hindus?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Depending on the patience of the visitor, a number of answers are possible including an identification of the nature of the dispute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Negative portrayals of non-Western Cultures like Indian: Secularization of Christianity – S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 04:59:02 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to raise three issues: (a) how to analyze what Rajiv portrays about Wendy and her children in the field of religious studies; (b) depending on that, what an adequate response consists of. Before we do either (this is one of the things I have discovered through my own research during the last two decades), we need to be clear about (c) how we &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; analyze this situation. Given that all three (in their general form) have been my obsessions, I have been reflecting on them deeply, seriously and systematically for some time now. I would like to share some of the results of this reflection. In the first part, I will take a (rather slow) run up to tackling the third issue first. And even here, I look at RISA &lt;em&gt;lila&lt;/em&gt; as an exemplification of a more general issue or as an expression of a much broader tendency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
