<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>History on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/history/</link><description>Recent content in History on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 10:11:17 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ontology of Jain authors: Ramayana</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontology-of-jain-authors-ramayana/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 10:11:17 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ontology-of-jain-authors-ramayana/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure what the discussions are about. Here are some of the problems that have surfaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do (did) people in India believe that Ramayana is (was) a narration of &amp;lsquo;what really happened&amp;rsquo;? Even without specifying the &amp;lsquo;when&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;lsquo;where&amp;rsquo;, the answer is obvious: some (did) do; some (did) do not; some are agnostic. The question, however, is: What is the question about? What problem is it meant to solve? Does the answer I give solve any problem? If it does not, that shows that this is not the issue at stake. So, what is the issue then?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we talk about truth in Fiction? (The example of Holmes.) Yes, we can and do so very regularly, not only in common parlance but also in literary studies. However, the issues are: how should we understand this way of talking (there is controversy about it) and why is this relevant to Ramayana?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did some Indians begin a discussion about the existence of Ramasethu and the temple of Rama in Ayodhya (of today) only relatively recently? Yes, I think so. I do not know of any discussion that occurred on this issue, say, a thousand years ago. Again, what is the problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did Indians have no notion of the &amp;rsquo;truth of Ramayana&amp;rsquo; before their contact with non-heathen cultures? This is an ill-formed question, as far as I am concerned, because it is unclear what counts as an answer. Equally, it is unclear what the question is about: (a) is it about the Indian notions of &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo;? (b) is it about the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; of historiography? (c) Is it about the relation between &amp;lsquo;belief about the truth of historiography&amp;rsquo; and the &amp;rsquo;truth of historiography&amp;rsquo; independent of people&amp;rsquo;s beliefs about its truth?
These are merely some of the questions that have surfaced. May I request that we resume the threads with clear problem statements so that we can make some headway?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;II&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Historiography and Myths</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historiography-and-myths/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 23:29:48 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historiography-and-myths/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The western intellectual tradition has bemoaned the fact that the Indians never indulged in history-writing (or historiography). In this tradition, there is an obsessive need for collecting &amp;ldquo;facts&amp;rdquo; about the past. This is partly the result of how Judaism, Christianity and Islam (the three Semitic religions) look at themselves and their own past: everything they claim about their past (the Flood, the temple of Solomon, the coming of Christ, etc.) should not only be true but proven so beyond all doubt. They have to be true (in the sense that their recounting of the past should also be confirmed by research) because these religions live or die accordingly as whether it is also true what they say effectively happened on earth. These facts (like the existence of, say, the Temple of Solomon in the Israel of today and the Judea of yesterday or the existence of Jesus of Nazareth), in their turn, prove the truth about Moses and his tablet and the truth of the promise of God to the children of Israel. If the recounting of their past turns out to be false (like, say, the absence of any of the above two) would destroy their existence: if there was never a historical Jesus of Nazareth, Christianity would collapse like a house of cards. (In fact, Julian the Apostate, the nephew of the Emperor Constantine, set out to rebuild the Temple of Solomon at its original site precisely in order to do this. His early death, viewed both by the Jews and the Christians as an act of God, put an end to this project.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Blind men and an Elephant: Historicity of Rama</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/blind-men-and-an-elephant-historicity-of-rama/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:12:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/blind-men-and-an-elephant-historicity-of-rama/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin with the following dialogue between a Swiss-German and a young Balinese (from Bichsel, Peter, &lt;em&gt;Der Leser, Das Erzählen: Frankfurter Poetik-Vorlesungen&lt;/em&gt;, 1982, Darmstadt und Neuwied: Hermann Luchterhand Verlag. Pp. 13-14, my translation and italics):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I discovered, or when it was explained to me, that Hinduism is a pedagogical religion, namely, that in so far as the best “good deed” of a Hindu consisted of explaining something or the other, I lost my inhibitions and began with questions&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href="http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf"&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href="http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf"&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115"&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Vibrancy of Indian traditions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:21:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The discussion about re-accessing the vibrancy of the Indian culture and the question whether or not to legislate against conversion, are best treated separately. An answer to the latter does not necessarily count as an answer to the first. In fact, the tendency to counter the proselytising drive of Christianity and Islam by voting laws against conversion is itself an &lt;em&gt;indication&lt;/em&gt; of India’s cultural weakness. Hence, it cannot be a means to re-kindle the flame of India’s pluralistic tradition. &lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Historicity of Rama, Krishna, Anjaneya</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historicity-of-rama-krishna-anjaneya-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:38:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historicity-of-rama-krishna-anjaneya-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the questions that has come up in this discussion is the following: are we logically forced to assume the &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo; of, say, Rama or Krishna, when we &amp;lsquo;believe&amp;rsquo; in them? This question has partly been responsible for the discussion about the &amp;lsquo;historicity&amp;rsquo; of Ramayana. Here is my answer as I see the situation today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some sense, we all work with some notions (however vague they might be) of &amp;lsquo;belief&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo;. These have at least two origins: (a) the western philosophical and scientific discourses about them, the way these have percolated into our common-sense; (b) their reinforcement by our day-to-day experiences in the world. That is to say, we have some conceptions of what human beings are (however vague or even incoherent these may be), what their properties are and so on. In other words, this notion of human beings tells us that (a) we are creatures who can form beliefs about some things (this &amp;lsquo;aboutness&amp;rsquo; is called intentionality in the relevant literatures); (b) that these beliefs could be about the world, about language, about ourselves, about what exists in the world and so on; (c) that some of these beliefs are about existent objects, whereas other beliefs are about non-existent objects; (d) and that to &amp;lsquo;believe in&amp;rsquo;, logically speaking, either entails or presupposes (it is irrelevant for now whether it is a presupposition or an entailment) that the entity we &amp;lsquo;believe in&amp;rsquo; is believed to exist. And so on. If we assume this picture of human beings to be true, then it follows that &amp;ldquo;believing in Rama or Krishna&amp;rdquo; has the same force as &amp;ldquo;believing in Christ or God&amp;rdquo;. Thus, one has to ascribe the logical truth about their existence to those who &amp;ldquo;believe in&amp;rdquo; these figures. In simple terms, if you &amp;ldquo;believe in&amp;rdquo; Rama or Krishna, then you are logically compelled to believe in their existence as well, just in case you endorse this picture about human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Logical Acumen of Romila Thapar</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:28:45 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the debates in the Indian traditions is about the kind of creatures that exist in the world and about the reality of what exists. The Jains, for instance, disagreed that the &amp;ldquo;deva&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; of other traditions (with the properties they were supposed to possess) existed in this world or were real. (Their so-called &amp;lsquo;atheism&amp;rsquo; is a result of this debate.) Consequently, when they call Valmiki Ramayana false, they are making claims about the logical falsehood. They did not, on the basis of some or another empirical enquiry, establish that Ravana was a vegetarian or that Rakshasas were human beings (in fact, in many parts of India, people believe that Ravana was both a Brahmin and a rakshasa at the same time) or that Rama was different from what Valmiki said he was. The same applies to Anjaneya: the claim of some or another author that he was a human being and was married does not either &amp;lsquo;prove&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;disprove&amp;rsquo; the claim of Valmiki.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What do Indians Need: A History or the Past--S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-do-indians-need-a-history-or-the-past-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 22:55:47 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-do-indians-need-a-history-or-the-past-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, both in India and abroad, we see the emergence of a new intellectual trend: based on painstaking research, to write an accurate history of India. What is &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; about this approach? In one sense, as I shall explain in this article, this attempt is not novel; in another sense, which too shall be explained, there is something very new in it. I shall talk about both in the course of answering the question raised in the title, which contrasts ‘the past’ with ‘a history’. This contrast needs explication because historiography is seen as an ‘accurate recording of the past’. Yet, I am going to contrast the product of historiography, ‘a history’, with something called ‘the past’.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The past and ways of talking about it</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-past-and-ways-of-talking-about-it/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 19:42:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-past-and-ways-of-talking-about-it/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is history? In the first place, it is the subject matter of historiography, which is what historians write. What does historiography talk about? The human past. In other words, there is a distinction to be made between &amp;rsquo;the past&amp;rsquo; and ways of talking about this past.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If this distinction (between &amp;rsquo;the past&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;ways of talking about it&amp;rsquo;) is accepted, then we can answer the question about what history is thus: it is a way of talking about the past&amp;ndash;a &amp;lsquo;scientific&amp;rsquo; way. That is, the truths of historiography are established using the methods and techniques widely accepted in that domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The past can be talked about not only by using historiographical methods, but also in different ways: the way stories, legends, drama, poetry, etc do. These are also ways of talking of the past but they lay no claims to being histories (or they do not claim to be &amp;lsquo;historiographies&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the status of the Bible? According to the Semitic religions, not only is it the word of God, but it also aspires to being &amp;lsquo;historiography&amp;rsquo;. Events like the revelation of the Biblical god, the covenant this god made with the people of Israel, the existence of Jesus of Nazareth, his claims to being the Christ, and such like are claimed to be not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; events in the human past but, above all, as &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; events. That is, they claim to be &lt;em&gt;historical events&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>