<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Published on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/published/</link><description>Recent content in Published on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 20:37:20 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/published/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What happened in Ayodhya?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-happened-in-ayodhya/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 20:37:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-happened-in-ayodhya/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A three-part series by SN Balagangadhara&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/commentary/what-happened-in-ayodhya-a-pran-prathistha-a-consecration-something-else"&gt;What happened in Ayodhya: a pran prathistha, a consecration, or something else?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/commentary/what-happened-in-ayodhya-mehtas-heroics-varshneys-warning-and-palshikars-guilt"&gt;What happened in Ayodhya: Mehta&amp;rsquo;s heroics, Varshney&amp;rsquo;s warning, and Palshikar&amp;rsquo;s guilt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/commentary/what-happened-in-ayodhya-what-our-intellectuals-saw-and-yet-did-not-know-what-they-saw"&gt;What happened in Ayodhya: what our intellectuals saw and yet did not know what they saw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combined version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Academia.edu: &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/118044160/What_Happened_in_Ayodhya"&gt;The Ayodhya Event: A Response to Some Newspaper Columns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Researchgate: &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Balagangadhara-Sn/publication/379544697_The_Ayodhya_Event_A_Response_to_Some_Newspaper_Columns/links/660ea20cb839e05a20bd46a6/The-Ayodhya-Event-A-Response-to-Some-Newspaper-Columns.pdf"&gt;The Ayodhya Event: A response to some newspaper columns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Balagangadhara's interview with Swarajya</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/balu-interview-with-swarajya/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 09:08:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/balu-interview-with-swarajya/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/books/what-we-lost-under-islamic-and-british-colonialism-a-conversation-with-s-n-balagangadhara"&gt;Part I,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/books/s-n-balagangadhara-interview-part-ii-brahminism-and-other-isms-are-inventions-of-western-indology"&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/books/s-n-balagangadhara-interview-part-iii-gandhis-experiments-with-truth-are-linked-to-his-colonial-and-christian-experiential-background"&gt;Part III&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/books/s-n-balagangadhara-interview-part-iv-there-is-intellectual-poverty-in-islamised-regions-india-may-be-headed-the-same-way-if-it-does-not-watch-out"&gt;Part IV&lt;/a&gt; (Appeared on 04/13/2022 through 04/15/2022)
S.N. Balagangadhara, emeritus professor at Ghent University, Belgium, has spent more than 40 years studying the science of cultures, especially Western culture, which was deeply influenced by Christianity, and how this framework was used to understand Indian culture, where it was a colonising power. In the process, our British colonial masters’ understanding of Indian traditions, religion and the ‘caste system’ impacted how we, the colonised, began to see ourselves even after 1947.
His latest book, &lt;em&gt;What Does It Mean To Be ‘Indian’?&lt;/em&gt;, written in collaboration with Sarika Rao, examines how the Islamic and British colonialisms interfered with our understanding of the world and experiences, thus leaving us with several unanswered questions on what it really means to be Indian in the twenty-first century.
S.N. Balagangadhara’s books and essays include &lt;em&gt;Cultures Differ Differently, Reconceptualizing Indian Studies&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Do All Roads Lead to Jerusalem? The Making of Indian Religions&lt;/em&gt;(co-authored with Divya Jhingran), and &lt;em&gt;The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, The West, and the Dynamic of Religion&lt;/em&gt;. His students have explored his themes in another book, &lt;em&gt;Western Foundations of The Caste System&lt;/em&gt;(edited by Martin Farek, Dunkin Jalki, Sufiya Pathan, and Prakash Shah).
In a conversation with Dr Balagangadhara, both over email and in a face-to-face discussion over Zoom, &lt;em&gt;Swarajya&lt;/em&gt;’s R Jagannathan discussed his book &lt;em&gt;What does it mean to be ‘Indian’?&lt;/em&gt;, including the ideas contained in it, and areas for future research. The following is the first part of the Q&amp;amp;A with S.N. Balagangadhara.
&lt;strong&gt;Swarajya: Does your book &lt;em&gt;‘What Does It mean to Be ‘Indian’?’&lt;/em&gt; seek answers to the question “Who were we as a people before Islamic and British colonialism entered the picture?”&lt;/strong&gt;
**S N Balagangadhara:**No. *What Does It Mean to Be ‘Indian’?*does not speak of some pre-colonial, ‘pristine’ Indian culture. *What Does It Mean to Be ‘Indian’?*is about what it means to be a part of Indian culture in the twenty-first century. The two colonialisms are parts of our past; they cannot be undone or erased. Colonialisms happened and they impacted us. The goal is to understand how they did so and find ways of dealing with them. That is the reason I spend much time on issues like colonialism, culture, and experience.
However, what the impacts of colonialisms were and how we responded to them are dependent on how we were as a culture. How the two colonialisms changed us depended on who we were (as a culture) before they colonised us. What Islam did to us is partially how we were before that event and British colonialism’s impact depended on what we had become before they colonised us. We were never passive victims; our culture defined (partially) what the colonisers were able to do.
There is more research to be done, but thus far we know that colonialism creates colonial consciousness which impedes our access to experiences — not at a generic, abstract level but at an individual level. It is something that you and I, our parents, and our children have.
It is important to reiterate that this book is not peddling cheap identity politics. As I explicitly say:
“I do not plot cultural differences along geographical, or linguistic or religious lines. Thus, belonging to Indian culture is how we use or deal with the resources of socialization in India. This would mean that belonging to this or that religion does not differentiate people as members of a culture: one could belong to Indian culture whether a Jain, Buddhist, or a Hindu in exactly the same way a Christian or a Muslim is Indian. This accords with what we see in India: a Konkani-speaking Muslim in Mumbai is as much an Indian as a Kannada-speaking Christian in Mangalore, and as a Tamil-speaking Brahmin in Bangalore.”
&lt;strong&gt;2: You state that colonialism, apart from violence and subjugation, does things to your mind whereby you no longer have access to your own way of experiencing life through your own learnt cultural interpretations. You see everything through the lens provided by the coloniser. My question is: this seems to matter only if the process of colonisation is incomplete, that is we have been outwardly colonised and alienated from our culturally-embedded instincts, but still know that something is amiss about ourselves. But what if we were, say, fully colonised like the pagans of Europe by Christianity? Today’s Christians are all descendants of those early pagan communities, who now fully see their identities as Christian, not pagan. I mean: does colonisation and self-alienation matter only if we are half-colonised, where we still have memories of what we were earlier?&lt;/strong&gt;
The claim is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;that we are not accessing our own way of experience. Rather, we are not accessing our experience. Period. (Read the chapter “India and her Traditions: An Open letter to Jeffrey Kripal”, in my 2012 book, &lt;em&gt;Reconceptualizing Indian Studies,&lt;em&gt;to understand in an abbreviated form what it means to speak of accessing our experience.)
Also, it is not true to say that we “see everything through the lens provided by the coloniser”. The lens that Indians use(d) is different from what the Africans or the Native Americans use(d), even though these people were also colonised. The lens we ‘use’ is ‘made in India’, even if the ‘technology’ is western.
Further, the two processes, Christianisation and colonisation, should not get mixed up. Christianisation is the process of converting populations into Christianity. It is a massive socio-cultural process. The British colonised us but did not Christianise us. In fact, though some missionaries wanted it, the British did not even try to do this. According to some estimates, the Christianisation of Europe itself was only completed by the fifteenth century. In fact, according to me, the Protestant Reformation signaled that the Christianisation of Europe was completed by then.
And we still don’t know why the Roman Empire fell, what happened to the pagans in Rome when Christianity emerged. I develop a partial hypothesis in the second chapter of my first book &lt;em&gt;The Heathen in his Blindness&lt;/em&gt;… (1994).
Other than that, here are some further thoughts: I think India was already a mature culture when it was colonised. Perhaps, a passing thought is required to say what I mean by a ‘mature’ culture here. The successful and complete Christianisation of (western) Europe can at least partially be connected to the native cultures that Christianity encountered when it went west of Rome to proselytise. In India, there was very little Semitic religions could offer that would trump what was already present: from the abstract Parabrahma to sophisticated literature, arts, and philosophy; from various types of rituals and traditions to a plurality of routes to ‘spirituality’. Such a culture could tame and absorb some of the tendencies of Semitic religions without being overwhelmed.
Colonialism damaged our culture in the sense that it damaged the &lt;em&gt;transmission&lt;/em&gt; of Indian culture and the formation of our intellectuals. Even in this process, Indian culture didn’t passively undergo the damage. In turn, it also impacted and changed those that entered it. Indian Islam and Indian Christianity are different from what they are in their native soil. Evangelical Christians and madrassas are trying to change this Christianity and Islam in India into something which they believe is ‘the template’ for these religions.
Finally. At the stage our knowledge is in, we cannot speak of complete or incomplete colonialism because we have no metric using which we can measure either the degrees or the extent of colonialism. Conversion to Christianity did not make Indians either partially or completely colonial: The Church of South India (including the other dioceses that are conglomerated there) is not a colonising institution, even if colonialism established it (in some sense). Madras Christians are not really all that different &lt;em&gt;culturally&lt;/em&gt; from Mudaliyars or other similar groups in Tamil Nadu.
&lt;strong&gt;3: Can you explain your statement that India was colonised first by a religion (Islam) and later by the British (but not Christianity). The latter is easily understood, since it involved subjugation and direct intervention in our civil and social lives, but how does one explain colonisation by a religion? Or is it that Islam first colonises the minds of its own faithful and then they do the rest?&lt;/strong&gt;
I have not gone into this question in the book because it requires that one understands my theory of religion and &lt;em&gt;how a religion secularises itself&lt;/em&gt;. This is a very long topic. Thus, I can only say in this answer that the claim that Islam colonised us can be made intelligible and is defensible. It is not ‘easy’ to understand it because religion is not an easy phenomenon for us to understand. All you need to know at this stage is that while it is true that people subjugate people, so does a religion. The latter’s colonisation is an entirely different process from conversion into a religion.
Colonising India is the secularising moment of Islam as a religion, but not in its phase of religious conversion. The British colonised us but not their Christianity (i.e., British colonialism was &lt;em&gt;not a&lt;/em&gt;process of &lt;em&gt;Christianisation&lt;/em&gt;), whereas it was not the Arabs or Persians who colonised us but Islam. The &lt;em&gt;process of Islamification&lt;/em&gt;was carried out by a very weakly secularised religion. (Or) Islam secularises itself through Islamification whereas Christianity secularises itself in a de-Christianised form. These two processes, Christianisation and Islamification, are different in kind and these do not qualify as a process of &lt;em&gt;religious conversion&lt;/em&gt;into these religions.
Superficially speaking, Islamification looks very much like religious conversion, but it is not. The violent subduing of socio-cultural phenomena and attempts to deform them make this phase (or aspect) of Islam different from religious conversion. Conversion is an individual religious process, whereas Islamification is a secularisation process at a social scale driven by violence. (&lt;em&gt;I cannot explain these distinctions and thoughts here, in this answer, because it requires a very long explanation&lt;/em&gt;).
&lt;strong&gt;4: My own hunch is that British colonisation was built on top of Islam’s brutal and contemptuous regard for Indian culture. Thus, when the British came, many Indians were willing to see them as saviors from Islam’s brutalities. This made it easy for us to think that the way forward is to think like them. Raja Ram Mohan Roy, for example, wanted to model his Brahmo Samaj more or less like a Hindu version of Christianity…Your comment.&lt;/strong&gt;
My previous answer hints at a possible explanation of your hunch, viz., “Islam’s brutal and contemptuous regard for Indian culture”. Surely, we must explain this phenomenon: why should Islam, or any religion for that matter, regard a culture (any culture) brutally and contemptuously? Even the most ‘other-worldly’ orientation seeks music, hymns, and ennobling visualisations. That being the case, how to understand your hunch? Since you are not alone in thinking this, as scientists, we must come up with a plausible (and hopefully true) solution to the problem. Currently, I think I am very close to a satisfactory solution, which I have only hinted at in my previous answer.
Many things emerge at the crossover points where religion and tradition meet and impact each other. Movements such as the Arya Samaj or Prarthana Samaj are some such. They modelled themselves on the Protestant Reformation (as Indians understood ‘reformation’, of course) with a goal to ‘reform’ Hinduism. The nature and tenor of the Protestant theologies which they encountered defined their themes and determined their responses. However, I do not think that Raja Ram Mohan Roy (and others) wanted to be like the Protestants because the British fought Islamic rulers. The reasons must be sought elsewhere and not in their possible individual psychologies, because it fails to explain why many other and different psychologies followed these movements. Surely, we cannot explain or understand the ‘popularity’ of Arya Samaj today by appealing to this psychological explanation.
No matter how Indians looked at the British (as saviors or whatever), this attitude does not explain colonialism. In the South, for instance, Tipu Sultan, the ‘Tiger of Mysore’, is praised because he fought the British. Tipu was known as a very cruel king, but he is celebrated as the hero who resisted the British invasion. There is a ‘Tipu Sultan’ day, a festival day, that the Congress party introduced into the state.
&lt;strong&gt;5: You say that there is no such thing as Hinduism, but we can accept that there are Hindus of various kinds. In short, we are Hindus in a geographical-cultural sense, but there is no religion called Hinduism, which was the result of colonial understanding and interventions. Is this what you want to say?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Balagangadhara:&lt;/strong&gt; Science develops because it tries to understand phenomena in the world. Scientific progress happens when old theories are superseded by better theories. That is how we gain knowledge. Just because new scientific theories develop, it doesn’t mean that the phenomenon that they are talking about disappears. For example, the miasma theory of disease which was believed to be true for more than a millennium was superseded by the germ theory of disease. This does not mean that diseases or their causes disappeared. We just developed a better understanding of the phenomenon.
‘India has a native religion, and that religion is called Hinduism’ is one story about India and her culture. This story is 400 years old. I challenge that claim and show through scientific research that it is not correct. But because one hypothesis about India is replaced by another, it does not mean that Indians don’t exist or that Indian culture disappears.
Do Hindus (as cultural groups) exist? Yes, and they are not geographical groups: Hindus exist as a group in many geographies and not only in what we call India. This is not a modern-day phenomenon: Hindus were known to exist in Jambudweepa, Gandhara, Khambhoja, etc., for instance. Are they Hindus because they are a part of Hinduism &lt;em&gt;as a religion&lt;/em&gt;? My answer is no. This answer has nothing to do with how the Semitic religions ‘define’ religion. The question is: does Hinduism as a religion exist as a phenomenon in the world? My answer is no. However, whether Hinduism is a phenomenon in the world or not, this ‘fact’ is independent of the question what the word ‘religion’ means in our languages.
&lt;strong&gt;6: So, similarly, we can say that castes (or &lt;em&gt;jatis&lt;/em&gt;) exist, but not a caste system. That there may be Brahmins, but Brahminism is a concoction.&lt;/strong&gt;
Absolutely. &lt;em&gt;Jatis&lt;/em&gt; are social groups in Indian society. Social groups exist in all societies and in India these social groups are called ‘&lt;em&gt;jatis&lt;/em&gt;’. &lt;em&gt;Similar&lt;/em&gt; social groups that exist in societies are called differently in different parts of the world. It is as sensible to speak of ‘the caste system’ in India as it is to say that there is ‘the social group system’ in societies. Further, yes, Brahminism is an invention of western Indology. Indology which is fond of ‘-isms’ has created quite a few: Brahminism, Vedism, Hinduism, Buddhism, and so on.
&lt;strong&gt;7: Religion is difficult to define, but traditions, rituals and practices are clearer to acknowledge. Tradition needs no justification, unless it offends basic human good sense in this day and age. But is there a danger in reducing all of Indian knowledge, metaphysics, philosophy, spiritualism, even science, to just tradition and not call it a religion? After all, isn’t Hinduism partly a religion even as defined by the West?&lt;/strong&gt;
I will start with the simplest point first. As far the West is concerned, Hinduism is not ‘partly’ a religion: according to them, Hinduism is &lt;em&gt;fully&lt;/em&gt; a religion. Period. The West is not denying that Hinduism is a religion. In fact, they have always claimed that it is. So, when Indians jump up and down and claim that they too have religion and that it is called ‘Hinduism’, Western commonsense and academia are in complete agreement. They don’t understand why Indians are proclaiming this very old consensus as though it is a revolutionary new discovery.
Now, the second part of the answer. You say that “there is a danger of reducing” everything to “just tradition”. And that, surely, Hinduism is “at least partly a religion”. This issue is worth focusing on.
The first thing to notice is that there is an anxiety involved in trying to identify Hinduism as a ‘religion’. The anxiety is not about understanding religion. The concern is also not to understand what ‘Hinduism’ is. The anxiety is in gaining agreement with the opinion that ‘Hinduism’ is a ‘religion’— at least ‘partly’. People don’t know why, but they are convinced that it is bad if someone says Hinduism is not a religion. Why? Where did this conviction come from that all human cultures must have religion, whether in primitive or in an advanced form, whether as a ‘natural religion’ or as ‘sophisticated spirituality’? One might tweak the definitions in any which way, but one wants to make sure that the result is that ‘all human cultures have religion’. This is something we must pause and look at.
The idea that ‘religion is a cultural universal’ is a belief in Christianity and Islam. With the process of secularisation, this belief has spread into commonsense and social science. This belief has become so ‘obvious’ that we have an entire cottage industry studying the ‘evolutionary biological explanation for religion’. Therefore, I say that many social scientific insights are simply universalisations of the experiences of one culture, namely that of the West.
The idea that ‘religion is universal’ is not only an obvious unquestioned ‘fact’ but to question it is also considered offensive. My first book (1994) looks at European culture, and the phenomenon of religion, and I develop a theory of religion. I show that what we do not have is a definitional problem. It is about developing a scientific theory of a phenomenon X and seeing whether other phenomena like H or P are also the same or not. The book also explains why the West thinks that religion is a cultural universal.
The other thing to notice is that by identifying one phenomenon, we do not ‘reduce’ any other thing. Just because I say that the water you see in a desert is a ‘mirage’ and ‘not photosynthesis’, it does not mean that all kinds of other things ‘get reduced’ to mirage. Why would they? Likewise, just because I say that we have ‘tradition’ and ‘not religion’, everything cannot ‘get reduced’ to tradition. Philosophy, linguistics, grammar, psychology, science, medicine, etc. are other things and they don’t get reduced to religion or tradition.
Religion is difficult to define as a word only when there is no theory of religion. The word is defined satisfactorily in a scientific theory of religion. Recognising some practices as ‘traditions’ (or as belonging to a tradition) does not make defining ‘tradition’ any less difficult. For that too, we need a good theory.
&lt;strong&gt;8: Would you call Buddhism or Jainism or Sikhism also traditions? Or do they pass muster as religions since they do have founders and a set of holy texts like Abrahamic religions? Is it the lack of a founder or “fundamentals” that provides a line separating a religion from just a tradition?&lt;/strong&gt;
I do not say that any phenomenon that has a founder and a set of holy texts is a religion. I do not say this because it is a &lt;em&gt;bad argument&lt;/em&gt;: when we say that ‘Hinduism’ does not have holy books, a founder, etc., the only thing we can say is that ‘Hinduism’ is different from the Semitic religions &lt;em&gt;in this respect&lt;/em&gt;. We cannot say that, &lt;em&gt;therefore&lt;/em&gt;, it is not a religion. I have a hypothesis on what religion is (as a phenomenon in the world) and that is explained in my first book, &lt;em&gt;The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, the West and the Dynamic of Religion’&lt;/em&gt;. In one sentence, which is difficult to understand in such a brief form, “religion is an ‘explanatory intelligible account’ of the Cosmos and itself”. &lt;em&gt;(This sentence can be read as a definition of religion, but it does not speak about churches, holy books, founders, dogmas, beliefs, etc.)&lt;/em&gt;
‘Buddhism’ was a discovery (actually, an &lt;em&gt;invention&lt;/em&gt;) of the British. Sikhism is an emergence from the interaction of Indian traditions with Islam. Neither exists in the world as religions. These are Indian traditions.
I have written on the difference between religion and tradition in my writings. One must understand these two phenomena separately to understand their relationship with each other.
&lt;strong&gt;9: You seem to want to give our colonisers the benefit of the doubt in terms of intentions. You broadly suggest that they defined us based on their own experiences with the way European Christian history evolved. So, it was natural for them to analyse us in the way they understood reality. But is this the whole story? Didn’t coloniality need them to actively promote internal antagonisms and widen the fault-lines inside India, so that they could rule us with very few people? Didn’t Pakistan, and the widening of the &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt; divide, serve their interests?&lt;/strong&gt;
The first sentence in the question captures a prevalent misunderstanding. It says that I speak of the ‘intentions’ of the colonisers. That is not the case. I am not interested in the intentions or the motivations of individual or even groups of Europeans. The reason I do not do that is because: (1) it is not correct to say intentions guide actions. Take the incessant excuse that people give of intended actions and their unintended consequences. I have different ideas about that, but I won’t go into that now. I tackle this issue a bit deeper in chapter 4 of the book &lt;em&gt;Cultures Differ Differently&lt;/em&gt; (2022) or in the book &lt;em&gt;‘The Heathen&amp;hellip;’&lt;/em&gt;. (2) It is very difficult to find out the reasons for an action by a person. Most of the time, individuals themselves don’t know what their reasons are, or why they act the way they do. (3) One of the problems in tightly linking intentions to action is the fact that one and the same action (even a trivial action like opening a door) can be the result of many kinds of intentions (maybe the room is too cold or too warm, maybe I thought someone is standing at the door, maybe I think spies are listening in to my conversation, maybe there is too much cigarette smoke in the room…)
Like with any person or group, multiple motivations and intentions in a mixed form are present at any given time. To try to crawl into the heads of earlier generations, especially centuries later, to find that which is inscrutable to themselves is to set myself to fail. Or worse, that is to present ignorance as knowledge which I call ‘bullshit’.
What I do is to make intelligible the consistency and thus the pattern of what the Europeans said about us and how they behaved. My hypothesis is independent of individual psychological differences (because we speak of hundreds of thousands of different people); it does not change with the passage of time (because we speak of a time span of centuries); it does not depend on national borders or geography (after all, the Portuguese, the Dutch and the English belong to different countries); it does not depend on their political inclinations (Liberal or Conservative) or religious proclivities (whether Anglican, Protestant, Catholic). That is, I put the constraints and demands of science on the hypotheses that I formulate. If I do not do this, I am simply one more person expressing one more opinion.
Discussing motivations, intentions and opinions is an endless process. Look at the number of books produced on colonialism. They have not helped us gain much of an understanding of the phenomenon of colonialism or its effects.
A scientific hypothesis must make sense of a canonised Catholic priest like (Francis) Xavier and the low-life thugs who made up the mercenaries of the East India Company, as well as bureaucrats like Warren Hastings and Orientalists like William Jones. I find that my hypothesis does it. Whether they abhorred the Savages and wanted to convert them, or whether they were rapine looters who wanted to make money or power-hungry imperialists, their cultural background and their shared Christian framework provided them with certain ideas about human beings, the natural world, and the social world. They used these ideas to make sense of what they went through and encountered in their lives.
This is what all human beings do. We use our repertoire to make sense of and deal with what we encounter. When Europeans landed on the coasts of Malabar and met Indians, their framework (their culture) provided them with ideas (resources) to make sense of what they saw. One example is the idea that ‘all cultures have religion’. This notion is never questioned, but different possible explanations are given to justify it. ‘False religion’, ‘primitive religion’, ‘magical thinking’, ‘a different kind of religion’, etc., are just the different forms that a justification takes depending on the fashions of the time. But the notion that is never questioned is whether ‘all cultures have religion’.
I also don’t use words like coloniality and decoloniality in my book. That is another reason for confusion. These words are obfuscating jargon from post-colonialism and post-modernism. These are the worst intellectual products of the twentieth century. In intellectual circles, post-colonials are described as &lt;em&gt;Jammergemeinschaft (&lt;em&gt;in German&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;: a community of whiners who do not contribute to knowledge. Post-modernism goes further and is openly inimical to knowledge. Unfortunately, both have become very widespread and influential. Thus, it is wise not to speak of ‘coloniality’ and ‘decoloniality’.
To give a short answer: no, I am not giving our colonisers any benefit of doubt, nor am I being soft or apologetic about them. The only focus of my work is to develop scientific knowledge about human beings, culture, and society. A true science of the social.
Of course, colonialism used many strategies to subjugate a people. This includes the ‘divide and rule’ policy, ‘exacerbating existing fault lines’ and so on. To speak of something (Pakistan, the &lt;em&gt;jati&lt;/em&gt; divide, etc.) as furthering their ‘interests’, we first need to be able to say what those interests are: are we talking about interests (in the plural?) of the British people (of which period?), of the British Anglican Church, of the British Empire, of the East India Company, of the White Race…? Was this plurality of ‘interests’ ever in conflict with one another? If they were, whose or which ‘interests’ did the conflict serve? Which became victorious and why?
You know, ‘interests’ is such a silly all-encompassing word that we can even say that everything the British did was in their ‘interest’. I would suggest that you think of an Indian linguistic equivalent for this word ‘interest’. You will then see how silly it is to speak of ‘interests’. ‘National security interests’, ‘national interests’, etc., are weasel words with no boundaries.
Finally, let me formulate a question. True, the British came “with very few people”. We were servile: there too I agree. No question that we behaved like menial servants. But did the British ever “&lt;em&gt;rule&lt;/em&gt;” us? Do we know what either the word means or what it indicates in the real world? This is a teasing question based on the results of my ongoing research. I hope to publish them soon.
&lt;strong&gt;10: Regarding &lt;em&gt;itihasa&lt;/em&gt; and history, you clearly warn us not to take &lt;em&gt;itihasa,&lt;/em&gt; which is about stories that may or may not have some history attached to them, as history. &lt;em&gt;Itihasa&lt;/em&gt; is about our way of passing on cultural information as stories and may not be history. But why do you suggest that the absence of history writing in India and using &lt;em&gt;itihasa&lt;/em&gt; as history are both colonialisms. After all, don’t we try to understand or deduce history from holy texts like the &lt;em&gt;Rg Veda&lt;/em&gt; or even epics like the &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt;? How is this colonialism?&lt;/strong&gt;
I have written articles on the subject where this question is tackled. (I suggest using my academia.edu website page, which contains most of my writings.) However, I do not say that we can learn nothing about &lt;em&gt;our past&lt;/em&gt; by studying the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Puranas&lt;/em&gt;. But I do say that historiography (the &lt;em&gt;graphein&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;historia&lt;/em&gt;) is not our way of talking about the past. &lt;em&gt;Itihasa&lt;/em&gt; does this job without being history. Using &lt;em&gt;itihasa&lt;/em&gt; to understand our past is not an expression of a colonial attitude. &lt;em&gt;Using itihasa as history is&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;11: You make a very bold — even controversial — claim about truth and knowledge. That “knowledge trumps truth” in our culture. We have a goddess for knowledge, but not truth. For the Abrahamics, truth is revealed by their one and only ‘true God;, and hence they are more obsessed by truth than us. But our national motto says, “Satyamev Jayate” and Gandhi said his whole life was about experiments with truth. How do you explain this contradiction between what we really revere (knowledge) and what we have adopted as national mottos?&lt;/strong&gt;
My answer is colonial consciousness. We learn a way of talking and we use it. This way of talking is unconnected to our experience. We have adopted many things in the formation of the Indian nation-state which are strange. The entire Indian Constitution is an expression of that strangeness.
A couple of other things. In Christianity, God &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the truth; He does not merely reveal something called ‘the truth’. This truth is an ontological notion (i.e., it is about what there is or exists in the world), whereas the ‘truth’ as we use the word in India is semantic in nature. It is a linguistic property of sentences, mostly. I do not say that the true sentences that we talk and write are unimportant to us; I say that this truth-telling is subordinated to knowledge.
Gandhi titles his book without knowing what he was talking about. &lt;em&gt;(We must understand his educational and experiential backgrounds, both of which were colonial and Christian, to understand his obsession with ‘the’ truth.)&lt;/em&gt; How does one experiment with truth, or how many &lt;em&gt;kinds of&lt;/em&gt; experiments can we do with it? What does such a formulation or such an activity mean? What kind of experiments can we indulge in? For instance, is lying an ‘experiment with truth’ or is it the opposite of truth-telling? Silly slogans should not replace serious thinking. About ‘Satyameva Jayate’: what does the ‘victory’ of truth mean? Against what? Lies? Why should truth-telling and lying be each other’s enemies? Have we not been taught by our mothers, grandparents, and friends to know how and when to lie? Are we ‘experimenting’ with ‘truth’ in such cases?
If we were members of Semitic religions, we could make sense of the victory of ‘the truth’, viz, of God. If ‘satya’ were to mean ‘the good’, we can understand the victory of ‘the good’ against evil. What would this mean if truth is a linguistic property of sentences? Of course, ‘Satyamev Jayate’ is a native Indian motto. Here and there, Indian writings hint at the existence of an ontological notion of truth but they became popular only during the British colonialism and under the influence of Protestant Christianity. (&lt;/em&gt;“Ekam Sat…”&lt;/em&gt; is about &lt;em&gt;Sat&lt;/em&gt; but not about &lt;em&gt;satya&lt;/em&gt;, whereas &lt;em&gt;“bahudavadanti”&lt;/em&gt; is about truth-telling.) Thus, the point is that we cannot explain or understand what the victory of &lt;em&gt;satya&lt;/em&gt; is without appealing to Semitic religions today. Do we really need to have a national motto incomprehensible to most of us Indians?
&lt;strong&gt;12: You define “culture” as combining two things, language, and actions. These exist not only as resources for enabling socialisation, but contain knowledge on how to use and experience these resources. You also say that in Western culture, religion plays an important role and in Indian culture it is rituals and practices. Can you expand on this idea with examples?&lt;/strong&gt;
I have put this across as a possible hypothesis of a phenomenon in chapter 3 of the book ‘&lt;em&gt;What does it mean to be Indian?&lt;/em&gt;’ I have said more in &lt;em&gt;‘The Heathen…’&lt;/em&gt;, and in ‘&lt;em&gt;Reconceptualizing India Studies&lt;/em&gt;’, and in many other articles. I suggest reading them to know more.
&lt;strong&gt;13: I wonder why you say that Islam and Christianity have adapted to the Indian configurations of learning despite differing belief systems. But you also state that &lt;em&gt;madrassas&lt;/em&gt; and evangelical groups resist this adaptation to Indian cultural configurations. Can you explain this conflict, and why it is so important to understand in the Indian context?&lt;/strong&gt;
All things are influenced by the environment of which they are a part. Religion is no exception. The way Semitic religions evolved in a religious environment like Europe or in the Middle East is different from how the Semitic religions evolved in a non-religious environment like India. Europe or America today are ‘secular’ worlds; a ‘secular’ world in a religious culture is a secularised religious environment.
Both religions and traditions face different challenges in different environments. Take, for example, the kind of problems faced by NRI Hindus: they are suddenly confronted with new questions and novel situations. So, they adapt to survive in that environment. Or take the Jews: European and Middle Eastern Jews who were victims of relentless persecution evolved differently compared to the Jews who lived peacefully in a non-religious environment like India.
Thus, Islam and Christianity also changed in India. Today, there is also the growing impact of evangelical Christianity or Wahabism on them. It is a very complex issue with multiple threads, but I think that the increasing hostility and friction between communities in India has to do with the changing nature of these religions. But because we don’t have many intellectuals in India, we don’t have the resources to understand what is happening there. It is one of the biggest tragedies of India: not only do we not have many intellectuals, but we also do not appear to care about producing more of them.
Your main concern is about the modern-day interaction between Indian culture and these two groups of militant evangelising Christians and the equally militant &lt;em&gt;madrassas&lt;/em&gt;. Note that they are taking place against an India whose culture is losing its vibrancy. To understand this complex pattern of interaction and make a prognosis requires research of a kind that is totally non-existent in India. A moralising talk about the persecution of minority groups in India is the language of the current crop of Jawaharlal Nehru University, Delhi University and Asoka University people. It gives them ‘fame’ but produces no knowledge.
&lt;strong&gt;14: It seems likely that colonisation is not always a well-thought-out conspiracy by the coloniser. It is the product of the colonial powers using their own historical lenses to define or describe the colonised, but, at the same time, it also involves a long-term process whereby the colonised people develop a “colonial consciousness”. Why and how did India’s intellectuals start believing that their rulers understood them better than they themselves did? What could have been the triggers for this process?&lt;/strong&gt;
Colonialism is not a conspiracy: no massive social phenomenon is a conspiracy, well thought-out or otherwise.
I speak about these two questions very briefly in my book, because much of the work on these issues belongs to ongoing research. I am one of the few who have identified and raised this as a question. There is a lot more work to be done before we can answer these questions. In my book, I say:
“So, we can ask: what made Indians think that the British experience of India describes India the way it is? This issue becomes even more acute because of another claim that I have been developing: one of the characteristic aspects of Indian culture has been its continuous emphasis on reflecting on experience. Thus, Indian intellectuals must have been able to see that what the British were saying about them did not match their own experience. Yet, instead of disagreeing, they acquiesced. What made the Indian intellectuals blind to the nature of their own experience? If we assume that events that occurred in the world are responsible for this, what happened in the past that made the intellectuals of India lose their grip on an essential element of their culture? How could Indian culture have failed in accessing its own experience, when its internal focus was precisely on reflecting on experience?&amp;quot; (p. 84)
The indicative hypothesis is that Indian culture &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; losing its vibrancy and the nature of her intellectuals must have changed their shape and form during this time. For now, what I say in the book is all I can say. When I die, I can leave behind what I have worked on for 40 years. After all, I am one man (and an old one at that) and the questions are many. There are no easy fruits to pluck, we must plant the trees and tend to them with the hope that our posterity can pluck the fruits.
Our culture has always placed a huge premium on knowledge. &lt;em&gt;Jnana&lt;/em&gt; and Saraswati are not easily acquired. You ask for examples of the resources of socialisation: our intuitive relationship to Saraswati, &lt;em&gt;vidya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;jnana&lt;/em&gt; are excellent examples. In any case, a very brief answer can be given. Indians succumbed to the descriptions of the colonisers because Indians were unable to counter them with their native descriptions. The crises in Indian society that preceded Islamic colonialism had weakened the Indian intellectual traditions. The Muslims damaged this weakened culture so that when the British came, our resources were almost exhausted due to a millennium of lack of use and quite some abuse.
&lt;strong&gt;15: Regarding Islamic colonisation, you say that it enabled the penetration of Islamic themes using Indian terms and concepts. This happened because Indian culture was already losing its vibrancy when Islam came to India… Can you speculate on why we were already losing vibrancy at that time, so that we became easy fodder for Islamic themes to enter our consciousness? How did Islam prevent us from accessing our own experiences?&lt;/strong&gt;
I am still trying to understand this phenomenon fully. This requires research which is still ongoing. It would not be correct to speculate about such serious matters now. As it is, disciplines which claim to study India are full of speculations, conjectures, and pernicious nonsense. I would be very irresponsible (and unethical, to be honest) to add to that.
However, the following can be safely said. There must have been a huge crisis (maybe, there were many crises) in our culture because of which certain kinds of enquiries died. Certain ‘developments’ in Indian culture about 1,000 years ago were probably responses to crises that we could not adequately meet. That is, not everything that emerged in our culture, even centuries before the Islamic colonialism, indexes our strength; some of these developments could well be expressions of weaknesses. This is a call to seriously study the Indian past, not the way JNU and Delhi University scholars have done until now, but in a scientific manner.
&lt;strong&gt;16: You make a statement that there is intellectual poverty in already Islamised regions on the Indian sub-continent, in places like Pakistan, Bangladesh and Kashmir. Why do you say this?&lt;/strong&gt;
I say this because it is visible, isn’t it? These regions have not produced any great intellectuals in the last centuries and the environment in these regions is hostile to intellectual development. While people of Pakistan and Bangladesh do flourish and grow when they go to study in other countries, there are no noticeable native intellectuals in these regions.
In fact, India is heading in the same direction: we don’t have intellectuals and we are not creating them. Irrespective of whether the decline will take the form of economic poverty or not, if things don’t change, the intellectual poverty in India will reach the same level as Pakistan or Bangladesh. For instance, if things in education (both secondary and higher) do not drastically change in the next 15 years, the educational landscape in India will soon resemble that of Black Africa in the 1930s. We simply do have less and less competent teachers in our educational landscape.
Take the example of the reaction of most Indian intellectuals to the movie &lt;em&gt;The Kashmir Files&lt;/em&gt; and the massive response of ordinary people. If the first aspect demonstrates anything, it lays bare the absolute barrenness of Indian intellectual landscape. I have not read a single reflection or review that even minimally tries to understand what people are responding to when they respond to the movie. Like everything else, this too is another occasion for moralising lectures about communalism, posturing against the imputed hatred the movie apparently propagates combined with expressions of pseudo-horror about an allegedly partial portrayal.
Very few things can move the entire population like this movie did and I am still thinking about it. And perhaps will also write on the movie. Tragedies or violence are not new, especially when they are in the news every day. So, it cannot be that the overwhelming response of people had only to do with the horrors faced by the Pandits in Kashmir or the treachery of our ruling classes (politicians, intellectuals, and media). Shortly after the movie came out, I saw it in Belgium, I remember telling my daughter that this movie would enter the national consciousness of India.
I have a feeling that &lt;em&gt;one of the reasons&lt;/em&gt; why this movie has had the kind of impact it has is because it addresses our deeply held intuitions about our culture regarding knowledge, Saraswati, learning and the destructions wrought on it. One of the horrors we experience is to the rape of “&lt;em&gt;Kashimra Puravasini&lt;/em&gt;” there and to her becoming a total alien in her hometown. (One of the first &lt;em&gt;shlokas&lt;/em&gt; we learn as very young children goes thus: &lt;em&gt;Namaste Sharade Devi, Kashimrapuravasini&lt;/em&gt;…)
&lt;strong&gt;17: Religion expands in two ways: through conversions, and then later by expanding the same ideas through a secularisation of theology. Christianity expands by de-Christianising its format… And this secularisation is brought about by violence. Religion, whether it remains religion of gets secularised, is about “othering” someone or something… Is this what you are trying to say?&lt;/strong&gt;
I don’t speak of ‘othering’. It is a jargon which doesn’t explain anything. To treat someone as ‘the other’ might be bad if they are the same as you and you don’t treat them that way. For example, if one is a Christian, and Christianity says, “we are all children of God”, to treat some people as the ‘other’ might be wrong. But if someone is different from you, your refusal to see and acknowledge that difference is wrong, isn’t it?
In fact, I say that when the West looks at other cultures, it does not see them as ‘the other’. It sees and thus transforms them into a &lt;em&gt;pale erring variant&lt;/em&gt; of itself. &lt;em&gt;The other becomes another&lt;/em&gt;.
I do not say that Judaism and Christianity also &lt;em&gt;secularise&lt;/em&gt; themselves through violence. The emphasis on &lt;em&gt;secularising violence&lt;/em&gt; seems truer of Islam. The Semitic religions see ‘Hinduism’ as another religion: false, to boot, but a religion, nevertheless. They see each other as the ‘other’, i.e., as deficient, or defective religions (or heresies).
&lt;strong&gt;18: You broadly seem to suggest that colonialism seems to have made us strangers to our own access to culture, and also that we simply have not made enough efforts to understand Western culture. Thus, we don’t know how we must respond to colonial ideas when they come back to bite us without our knowledge of it. We say and speak words that display our colonial consciousness. If Western efforts to understand us through their lenses did not bring us much good, why is the reverse process, of our understanding Western culture, going to do us much good? Should we not focus on understanding ourselves first?&lt;/strong&gt;
Today, the ways and means that we possess to understand ourselves, the intellectual frameworks, the concepts, the interconnections between them, the social scientific theories are all entirely built by Europeans. I have shown in my work that they are based much more on &lt;em&gt;their experience&lt;/em&gt; of the world than on how the world is. There are any number of examples: the idea that ‘all cultures have religion’; the idea of a ‘unique self (soul) which all human beings have’; the notion that ‘the caste system characterises Indian society,’ etc.
So, if we must understand ourselves, we must study the Europeans in very concrete ways. Of course, we will study and understand them as Indians. That is precisely the point. To recognise, first and foremost, that there are cultural differences between us. We must study these to understand the theories we have about human beings. To understand what we say about ourselves when we claim that we too have a religion or pontificate that one must be true to oneself, and that the caste system must be eradicated, we must study the West.
We must understand the intellectual frameworks and their implications to understand our laws and to learn how to make laws which don’t make a travesty of everything good and just. To understand ourselves, we must understand western culture. Whether we like it or not, colonialism happened, and colonial consciousness exists. The question is how we can get out of it and regain access to our experience. My research programme, “Comparative Science of Cultures”, formulates one way of doing it. We cannot return to a pristine past of pre-colonialism. The question facing us today is ‘what does it mean to be Indian in the 21st century?’
To know more about the methodology of this approach, which the question raises, the second and third chapter in ‘&lt;em&gt;Reconceptualizing India Studies&lt;/em&gt;’ might help. They explicate my answers and their justifications.
&lt;strong&gt;19: In a country where “freedom of religion” is written into the constitution, how do we defend Indian/Hindu rights if you do not even define it as a religion? How can law makers even begin to understand the difference between religion and tradition, or the need to protect “majority” rights that are not religious in nature?&lt;/strong&gt;
This is one of the big problems in India. We have no investments in research and development in social sciences. (The UGC does massively fund ideological propaganda by calling it ‘funding social research’.) There are also no institutions (political, legal, educational, or even charitable) which are interested in stimulating novel social scientific research.
If Hinduism is not a religion and current legal frameworks are primarily structured by Semitic religions, how can non-religious traditions hope to have the protections of law? This is not just a question for ‘Hindus’, but one that is also of crucial importance to other traditions like the native American or African. What would the frameworks or even minimal formulation of law look like which is not Semitic in nature but one which makes space for traditions too?
To get an idea of enormity of the question: despite decades of experience and knowledge, even a group of gifted intellectuals will have to do four to five years of full-time research to begin answering this question. There have been barely any attempts by Hindus to try and understand themselves, their social and institutional world, and their implications. Even to this day, people think that it is a definitional problem or a semantic discussion. (‘According to us religion is…’ or ‘Abrahamic definition of religion is…’). Our Supreme Court routinely cites the US juridical definitions to decide about cases involving religious disputes in India.
So, to answer the question about how lawyers can understand and argue about the difference between religion and tradition, first, social scientists must develop at least the beginnings of an alternative legal framework, legal definitions, etc. Second, it is a collaborative research project with people who specialise in the comparative science of cultures, religion and constitutional law and Indian law. Third, out of such a long-term collaborative project, some tangible results like providing a skeletal legal framework for traditions which can be integrated into existing legal structures could emerge. Such a project does not exist.
Further, to understand our ‘laws’, we must look at who the ‘lawmakers’ are. Could it be seriously suggested that our current crop of MPs and MLAs even understand what they are legislating? Laws are written (the way the Indian Constitution got written) by third-rate bureaucrats in capital cities: neither they nor the ‘legislators’ know what they are doing.
&lt;strong&gt;20: The need to defend Hindu rights (we don’t even get to run our own temples) have led to a political platform broadly called Hindutva, but social justice warriors want to pit Hinduism against Hindutva and there was even a global conference called to “dismantle Hindutva”. What should our reasoned stand on these issues be, if Hinduism is not even a religion?&lt;/strong&gt;
Those defending Hindutva and those attacking it are both using the same intellectual framework. I have spoken of it in different places, including in “&lt;em&gt;What does it mean to be ‘Indian’?&lt;/em&gt;” (Page 25). If Hinduism does not exist and India has no religion, what does it mean to speak of (Hindu) religious fundamentalism? How then do we understand the phenomenon of Hindutva? (See also my preface in &lt;em&gt;Cultures Differ Differently&lt;/em&gt;.) None of the so-called India-scholars is raising these questions.
The conference you speak of was a marginal event, organised by academically fringe groups. But it gained wide-spread recognition because of the attention given to it by the people who got attacked by it. It surprises me that the so-called right-wing, in so far as it can be considered a coherent entity, has not realised that it now &lt;em&gt;embodies and implements&lt;/em&gt; the PR strategy of these fringe ‘scholars’: bait ‘Hindutva’ if you want to gain academic approval and social recognition.
There are two problems in the way the question is asked: (1) One is that there is a “need to defend Hindu rights” which led to the political platform of Hindutva. Yet the ruling party, which is considered Hindutva, has gone much further than the Congress in the appeasement of minorities and instituting welfare schemes. (2) The suggestion is that “social justice warriors want to pit Hinduism against Hindutva”. But the Hindutva, whether in the form of civil organisations or as a political party, has completely bought into social justice ideology. (When people claim that the victory of the BJP in the recent elections is the result of a “pro-poor” policy of the government, or that BJP wants to win the elections to promote ‘socially just’ policies, one is enthusiastically espousing social justice slogans. Such people are also the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; social justice &lt;em&gt;warriors&lt;/em&gt; in India.)
The growth of social justice ideology and its conflation with political correctness is relatively new in the West. But the poisonous combination of identity politics, social justice and political correctness has existed in India for decades. The reservation system which has ballooned out-of-control, the atrocities act, etc., are expressions of social justice ideology promoted and encouraged also by the current ruling party. Hindutva is doing more to promote ‘social justice’ warriors than Congress and its allies ever did. And yet, academic fringe groups sell the idea (which the Right strengthens) that there is ‘caste atrocity’ and ‘minority insecurity’ in India under the BJP, while the current ruling party is the best defender and protector of the so-called ‘Dalits’ and ‘minority religious groups’.
It might be interesting to note that the notion of ‘social justice’ is of Christian (Roman Catholic) origin, best formulated by their Pope in the twentieth century. Without a Christian framework within which to understand and endorse it, the entire ‘social justice’ idea dissolves into incoherence. Leo Shields, commissioned as a Lieutenant in the US army and dies fighting in France in 1945, received a doctorate from the University of Notre Dame in 1941 for his dissertation on “&lt;em&gt;The History and Meaning of the Term Social Justice&lt;/em&gt;”. There, he summarises it as follows:
“The … message of social justice is written in sharp relief against…(the) background of individualist thought in all its forms — romantic, rationalistic, humanitarian, totalitarian. It is the key to the reintegration of social life that must be inspired by Christian faith and charity and supported by grace. But it is a key which even this pagan society can turn if it is shown how. The realization of the idea of social justice is the unity of social peace.”
(I have written on this issue: see the article “Caste-based reservation and ‘social justice’ in India”. It is published in the book &lt;em&gt;Western Foundations of the Caste System&lt;/em&gt;, 2017, and is also available on my &lt;em&gt;academia.edu&lt;/em&gt; page.)
The current ruling party bends over backwards to appease ‘oppressed’ groups because it has bought into the image sold by others that it is a ‘religious fundamentalist party’ or that it is a ‘majoritarian party’ and that it would be against ‘social justice’ to do otherwise, etc. I do not think that the BJP (and the Sangh Parivar) are religious fundamentalists. This way of characterising and demonising them is the favorite pastime of the intellectually weak. But the BJP buys into its hook, line and sinker and is constantly busy ‘defending’ itself from these pseudo-attacks.
&lt;strong&gt;21: Islam has 200 million adherents in India, and Christianity is expanding fast through conversions in many states. There are non-Hindu majorities in seven states/Union Territories, and even states like Kerala may soon have fewer than 50 per cent who call themselves Hindu (it is 54 per cent now, but in 20 years, it could fall below 50 per cent). How do we apply your theories and postulates to defend the ideas that are truly Indian, especially when radical Islam and Evangelical Christianity are seeking to differentiate and dissociate from Indian cultural ethos, aided by global social justice warriors?&lt;/strong&gt;
I have spoken about how religion spreads in two ways: secularisation and proselytisation. Secularisation is more dangerous of the two. Strangely, Indians are more worried about proselytisation than they are about secularisation, which spreads Christian ideas in a de-Christianised form. Indian culture was not threatened by these religions, and it was able to deal with their proselytising drive. It did so without persecuting them or banning them. A vibrant Indian culture can handle religion in such a way that religion itself changes to adapt itself into the non-religious environment it finds itself in.
But the impact of colonialism, the enduring colonial consciousness and secularisation of religious ideas have consistently reduced the vibrancy of our culture. Post-Independence has seen an acceleration of this loss-of-vibrancy. The process of secularisation transforms ‘the other’, in our case the Indian traditions, into pale and erring variants of religion. We Indians swallow this silly idea hook, line, and sinker. One of the reasons why Indian culture is losing its vibrancy is because we are busy transforming it into something it is not. We are unable to transmit the culture we received from our ancestors to posterity because we have taken over the language and framework of the West (from Indology and other social sciences).
It is not a question of practical problems like how to argue in a court of law, but a question of how you look at yourself, your life, and your experiences. What is breathtaking is the combination of ignorance and complacency of Indians. We don’t understand English, but we are certain that we are experts there. We very easily pick up words and sentences and use them without any reflection or self-reflection and even write on our ‘experiments with truth’. We don’t ask if those words make sense of our experience. This did not create huge problems to the generation that grew up in the 1950s because they were schooled in regional languages and used English in addition to it. But that is no longer the case; it has progressively become worse with every generation. Thus, we have today’s generation which only learns English (that too badly) and as a result cannot speak, think, or write coherently in any language. Not in English and not in any regional language.
Regional languages have provided protection against colonial consciousness. I often tell my Indian students to think in their native languages, as though they are speaking to their grandmothers. The result is striking: the amount of nonsense that comes out of their mouths gets reduced drastically. It is much harder to speak in slogans, jargon and produce verbiage if you must explain it in Kannada or Marathi to your grandmother. Then you are forced to interrogate what you are saying. You are forced to think. (You cannot explain to your grandmother what ‘coloniality’ or ‘decoloniality’ is even if someone has coined a regional language word to translate these words.) But unfortunately, regional languages are on the decline. The millennials were already severely handicapped and now their children will be even more stunted: incoherent, confused, and unhappy personalities who speak broken English with pseudo-American accents.
We can improve this sorry situation by promoting regional languages in India. One way to do it would be to combine the strengths of the twentieth century with the strengths of our culture (its &lt;em&gt;orality&lt;/em&gt;) by creating and promoting audio books of some of the great literature written in Indian regional languages.
Because the millennial and post-millennial generations cannot read or write in regional languages, they have a very limited access to language and culture. The scope of their language is limited to conversations with friends and TV series. Without access to the richness of ideas through language, they have no way of evolving. So, they lose access to one of the most important resources of a culture: its literature, art, and ideas. And without these resources, they cannot aspire to become anything more than two-dimensional uncultured boors. Therefore, by making the literature in regional languages available as audio books, we can partially restore their access to regional languages and thus to Indian culture and ideas.
What I hope will happen in India is that a generation will come which can look at the ravages wrought by colonialism and the post-independence institutions and start dismantling the useless and dangerous structures and start building anew. They will have to be intellectuals and builders, formed and shaped by the consequences of the current generation’s failures. Perhaps the grandchildren of the millennials. They will need intellectual tools and frameworks. It is for that posterity that I write.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Colonial Consciousness and Servitude</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 14:41:17 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;[ Published on &lt;a href="https://swarajyamag.com/politics/prime-ministers-panch-pran-and-decoloniality-indian-servility-may-have-roots-in-secularised-islam"&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt; Aug 26, 2022]
Let me recollect the question we agreed upon: &lt;em&gt;how does the combined phrase (colonial mindset and servitude) make sense within the framework of my research programme?&lt;/em&gt;
My hypothesis on religion includes characterizing the dynamics of its expansion. As I see it, such a dynamic includes (a) conversion and (b) secularization. The first side of the dynamic, ‘conversion’, is well-known to most of us: here, some or another religion &lt;em&gt;inducts&lt;/em&gt; ‘non-believers’ into its fold or into its community of believers and practitioners. (I also called it ‘proselytization’, a term that notices how Judaism and Christianity use ‘proselyte’.) The second side of the dynamic, ‘secularization’, is known to us only very partially.
Made popular since the Enlightenment period in Europe, this partial description identifies an &lt;em&gt;antithetical movement&lt;/em&gt; where an individual religion begins to lose its earlier influence on its spheres of influence: the civil organizations and the civil authorities. This classical story is about the withdrawal of religion from various domains in society: politics, law, judiciary, and so on. In this ‘age of reason’, it is suggested that human reason begins to govern these institutions and provide their foundations instead of religious opinions and dogmas. One of its consequences is the loss of the power and control of the Church on the State. Called ‘secularism’, this process indicates the waning power of religion on people and their imaginations especially by freeing the civil, the social, and the psychological spheres of human beings and society. The freedom from those shackles that enslaved them over the millennia made human beings and their societies grow and expand. ‘Indian Secularism’ (both as a vacuous doctrine and in the threadbare ‘foundation’ it received in the Indian constitution) expresses this faith and this conviction in an extremely pathetic form ever since (or even decades before) the Indian independence 75 years ago.
My story, while giving credence to the hostility it expresses, locates the ‘secularization process’ as another side in the expansion of religion. Secularization is antithetical to the expansion of &lt;em&gt;some or another&lt;/em&gt; religion, but it expands religion itself as a phenomenon in a culture or society. As we know, each religion (I have the Semitic religions in mind here) is always &lt;em&gt;a specific religion:&lt;/em&gt; it emerged at some time, in a specific region, among a specific people, in a specific language, embodying specific doctrines, and specific practices. Thus, every religion (even where it aspires to be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; religion for the entire humankind) is always a specific religion. These very specificities that lend identity to some or another religion act as constraints on &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt;, which is, as I characterize it, the explanatory intelligible account of the Cosmos and itself. This account is &lt;em&gt;the truth&lt;/em&gt; about all that was, is and shall be. This truth is not only in the world but religion, as such an account, exhibits that truth. Thus, religion, &lt;em&gt;as religion&lt;/em&gt;, expands itself while this or that specific religion expands through conversion. Both, taken together, are moments in the expansion of religion.
Even though secularization of religion is a general process, how this process occurs is determined by the conditions of emergence of a specific religion and how that religion converts. That is, how religion secularizes itself is subject to the nature and constraints that the specific religions face. Thus, the secularization of Judaism, Christianity and Islam occur &lt;em&gt;differently&lt;/em&gt; even where each of them undergoes secularization as a moment in its expansion. In each of these religions, secularization is inimical and hostile to a particular religion because of the specificities that give us an individual religion.
In ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ I said that Indians were children of two colonialisms: one colonizer was Islam and the other was the British. This means that &lt;em&gt;religions too colonize&lt;/em&gt;. I did not expand on the idea in that book (you must wait for the upcoming works to grasp the idea more fully), but I will briefly outline only one element of this colonizing event. It is true that Islam tried to convert Indians and it is also true that it did so violently. While Islam launched many waves of destructive attacks on Indian traditions, their temples, and practices, etc., we were not colonized by this aspect or phase of Islamic expansion. (It is in the nature of religions, Christianity and Islam, to convert through extremely violent means when conversion is directed towards larger populations and established cultures. Judaism, after around 5th century C.E., almost stopped conversion. There are various reasons for this cessation, none of which is relevant for my story here.) &lt;em&gt;We were colonized by secularized Islam&lt;/em&gt;. That is, conversion into Islam did not colonize us; the secularized Islam did.
I have already noted that secularization is inimical and hostile to religion. What does it mean in our case? It means that the secularized Islam that colonized us was hostile to &lt;em&gt;Islam as a religion&lt;/em&gt;. Among other things, it means that it is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to Islamic doctrines as well. How? In very simple religious terms: &lt;em&gt;secularized Islam is blasphemy&lt;/em&gt; (within the framework of Islam as a religion). What does this mean?
According to Islam, Allah is the Lord and the Ruler of the Universe. As the word ‘Islam’ indicates, it demands an attitude of absolute submission and total surrender to Allah and His will. It requires a complete obedience to Him; human beings must follow His rules and Laws unconditionally. In its phase of conversion into a religion, Islam tried to inculcate this reverential attitude and habit towards Allah among the converted. In its secularizing moment, Secularized Islam reversed this thought and attitude entirely and gave it &lt;em&gt;a blasphemous form&lt;/em&gt;: among Indians, it inculcated and induced such a habit and attitude, &lt;em&gt;not towards Allah&lt;/em&gt;, but towards human rulers. &lt;em&gt;Secularized Islam put human Muslim rulers of India above the Prophet Mohammed and placed the same rulers as Allah’s equals&lt;/em&gt;. This is how secularized Islam expressed its antithetical attitude to Islam as a religion and expressed its hostility towards Islam.
I have claimed that colonialism transforms the experience of people and prevents the colonial subjects from accessing it in any form other than how the colonizer defines it. This inability to access our experience is what I call ‘colonial consciousness’. This is what secularized Islam also did: it introduced slavishness and servitude into Indian psychology. Centuries of this colonization made a &lt;em&gt;slavish submission to civil authorities&lt;/em&gt; the hallmark and an important trait of Indian cultural psychology. In very simple terms: &lt;em&gt;Indians became slavish, submissive, and servile to civil (i.e., human) authorities&lt;/em&gt;.
The British noticed this psychological trait of Indians and said that Indians were ‘effeminate’ and had ‘no backbone’. Though this is what all the Bengalis were in their eyes, after all, Bengal was one of first important ports of call to the British; very soon, all Indians joined the group of a servile people. That is why they went in search of ‘military’ castes in their attempts to recruit Indians to the British army. They found such ‘castes’ among the Sikhs and the Marathas (both of whom fought the Muslim rulers over long periods) and the Gurkhas (who were least subject to secularized Islamic rule). They found it among some ‘sub-castes’ as well: the Coorgis in Karnataka belonged to the ‘martial type’. The rest of India was too effeminate to be of much use except to slavishly obey the British authorities and lick their boots. How Indian child-rearing practices and the socialization processes in India succumbed to cultivating servility in Indian children because of Islamic colonization has not been understood yet. But that is not relevant to this story now.
When British ‘gave’ India her independence, the Indian servility did not disappear. It continues to be produced and reproduced even today. If we look at how Indians relate to &lt;em&gt;civil authorities&lt;/em&gt;, we see this servitude everywhere. The bureaucracy, the police, the ministers receive obsequiousness without demanding it. They punish those who dare ‘defy’ them. This is not merely how ordinary Indians relate to political and administrative authorities: this is institutionalized within these organizations too. How a peon responds to the boss; how a junior secretary bows down to the Deputy secretary; how the Chief secretary deals with Principal secretaries; how the chief minister treats the principal and the chief secretaries, how the circle inspector treats the local constable and is treated in turn by the assistant commissioner of police… This servitude, often called sycophancy, goes all the way to the very top.
This is how Indians are seen abroad: whether by the Chinese or in the West. Obsequious, eager to please and servile. This cultural psychology expresses our colonial consciousness as induced by Islamic colonization. Very recently, a few weeks ago, I read somewhere that Rahul Gandhi fulminated against the Indian foreign service officials thus: Indian diplomats are seen to have become &lt;em&gt;arrogant&lt;/em&gt; by others elsewhere in the world (due to Modi’s government). This perception makes sense: Indian diplomats are not any more as servile as they were in the last sixty years. They continue to have this psychology, but they do not express it as ‘the normal’ anymore.
There is much, much more to say than what I have. The story is bigger, broader, and richer than what I have penned so far. But I will round-off here. The phrase that combines ‘colonial mindset’ and ‘servitude’ makes sense within my research programme this way. It tells me how one colonialism has generated one aspect of our psychology. This attitude and orientation are in us and with us even now and will have their own poisonous and deleterious impacts on the development of the amritkaal that the PM spoke about. As I told you in an earlier mail, I have no clue what the PM intended or meant. This post is merely an attempt to see whether the combination makes sense within my research programme. It does. However, the implications are &lt;em&gt;gigantic&lt;/em&gt;: both for pursuing the pledge (the pran) and to fulfill it in the amritkaal that the PM seeks. They have their own pernicious effects on the current programmes of the government and all its future policies.
I must apologize for the brevity. You must wait for the upcoming works to understand this story properly. But I do hope this post will have done enough to keep the promise that I made in my earlier post.
Clarifications:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to understand corruption?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 09:21:28 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let us take the word ‘duty’ for the moment. Conflict in duties does not give you a moral dilemma. For a moral dilemma to occur two necessary conditions must exist: the prescribed set of duties must be logically consistent by virtue of which one is obliged to perform them all.  A dilemma pertains to a situation where one has an obligation to do A and an obligation to do B; but can in fact do only one. It is the perfect consistency of the system of duty that gives rise to the dilemma: a choice between A and B, between a banana and an orange is not a dilemma. It becomes a dilemma when you want both and can have only one. So, a moral dilemma cannot possibly describe a conflict of duties if one uses the word ‘duty’ here.  A conflict of &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; is not a dilemma at all.
What I mean by decolonizing social Sciences is very simple thing. There are many domains today: sociology, political science, psychology, and anthropology that call themselves social sciences as distinct from humanities. So, I am not talking about decolonizing science in the specific sense given by Mohini Mullick. I do not consider the theories in these domains which call themselves social sciences to be science at all. Today, I see all of them without exception as ideologies. I call my project ‘Comparative Science of Culture’ because existing theories are not social sciences.
For instance: political corruption refers to the act of an individual public servant who is part of a state or a government and who acts against the public interest of the people or the interest of the state. Because state has an interest which coincides with the interest of the society, then any action that supports an individual’s interest is morally wrong. This is the meaning of political corruption.
I am very conservative. I want a scientific hypothesis in the sense that it solves a problem, has an explanatory potential and there is some way to test it. In this sense, political theory is completely bankrupt. I proffer two hypotheses which at least minimally do what you expect a hypothesis to do.
The first is purely historical in nature. You raised a question about the moral evaluations which comes from a completely Western ethics and is not Indian at all. We in India had our own forms of social organization. We had certain indigenous ways of governing, of organizing production. But with colonization came industrialization, bringing with it management institutions from the West; structures were imposed on native Indian industries, on native structures, which today are taught in MBA courses all over India. The result is institutional distortion, so that you come across extraordinary things that baffle management theorists.
More concretely: how were questions asked about tradition? Can we use the resources of our ancient Indian literature to tackle and explain this problem? I find the Indian tradition powerful because it can help generate scientific hypotheses beyond the reach of Western social scientists. That’s why I am against the latter, not because they are Western. I am not against everything Western: Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics, Biology come from the Western tradition.
(pp 206-8 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Descriptions about the world vs. Manuals for action</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 19:59:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It is broadly accepted that one of the most important functions of language is to describe the world outside it. Could it be the case that when it comes to the Indian systems, they all (whether it is Advaita vedanta, Yoga vasistha, visista advaita) are teaching one to act, to live in a particular way? In other words, they are not saying what there is in the world but are manuals in a manner of speaking. Of course, in order to understand a manual you need reference points in the world. So when they say for example that when the Buddha argued for &lt;em&gt;anatman&lt;/em&gt; or Sankara spoke about &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt;, one way of interpreting, which is what most Indian philosophers have done, is that they attribute doctrines to them and say this is a description of the world. But actually they were not describing the world. Buddha does not say atman exists or does not exist or whatever. Sankara is not saying &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt; exists because that would be a description of our world. So what a guru does in our tradition, which is what the upadesa is, is to teach one to not look at these as descriptions of the world; he teaches one how to transform them into a way of living. So Yoga vasistha does not tell you what the world is like. That can be said in one sentence. Why then does this man have to write so much? It is to help you go on in a certain way and then say that this is not a description of the world.
(p. 308 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Truth, belief, intentionality, eudaimonia, ought</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:15:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I want to respond to three of your points Claus. First you are not talking only about the Greeks and the Romans because all the problems arising with respect to the phenomena of non-Western societies and culture are/were equally the problems in the frameworks of different varieties of culture. You not only talk about the Greeks and the Romans, you gave examples about the French and the English as well.
The second point is: you talk about the fact that people face the same problem in Europe of today when they talk about the Greeks and the Romans. You are absolutely right. But that confirms my point, namely, that the Greeks and the Romans had no religion. They were Pagan cultures and this is exactly the problem with India. The Christian culture doesn’t understand Greek — the whole of Heidegger’s philosophy is an example of that. He says we cannot think Greek. And his whole attempt to speak about what thinking is, what truth is, etc. — is an attempt to rescue the Greek language from what he called the Christianization of Latin. I am aware that contemporary European languages and modern Europe do have problems with the Greeks and Romans. But just because of the fact that Ancient Greece and Rome are located in the Western hemisphere does not make them part of Western culture. In an earlier publication, I showed that neither Greece nor Rome were cradles of Western civilization. Western Civilization is Christian Civilization, although you might not agree with that. Greece and Rome do not belong to it. That is why we Indians can understand them. Let me give you a small example — One of the most fundamental notions of Aristotle is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, which gets translated with great difficulty as ‘well-being’, ‘feeling good’, ‘happiness’ and so on. It is a very difficult word to translate. This is not merely a translation problem because I have had discussions with Greek scholars. Aristotle asks: what is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;? It is very difficult to achieve of course but he says once you have it you cannot lose it. I told a Greek Specialist once ‘you know nothing about Greek language’, He responded: ‘how dare you say that’! So, I said: ‘here is a simple thing, forget the translation of &lt;em&gt;eudaimoni&lt;/em&gt;a, give me one example of a human  property which once you possess, you do not lose.’ I said: ‘I do not have to understand Greek to understand what &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; means.’ And of course to this day, no Greek scholar could help me in giving one example of one human property which if once you possess you do not lose&amp;ndash;this is a fundamental property of &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;. For the Indians here is my answer. &lt;em&gt;Eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;aananda.&lt;/em&gt; Once you have &lt;em&gt;aananda&lt;/em&gt; you do not lose it. It is equivalent in some conditions to &lt;em&gt;brahma-gyaana.&lt;/em&gt; And that is happiness indeed, beyond &lt;em&gt;sukha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;duhkha&lt;/em&gt;. So when Aristotle is talking about &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; I understand him and I read him carefully. Of course, there is no translation equivalent of eudaimonia in any of the European languages but that is because they have no access to that world, that conceptual framework like we Indians have. So indeed, I understand you have a problem with Greece and Rome: we understand them much better.
Two other points &amp;ndash; one on Galileo. I am not conflating the community of Christians with a community of non-Christians because one of the claims I have substantiated to which in the last fifteen years I have found no counter argument, is the following: My claim is that free thinkers and atheists, even the Communists of Europe, are actually disguised theists. That is to say that Christianity has secularized itself in political theory, in social theory, in rational choice theory; a number of theories. I can show you how assumptions from the Bible have taken secular forms. So by saying for instance, ‘look I don’t have a religious background’, it makes no difference. I know people, who do not have a religious background for generations, are atheists but they continue to have the same excuse for speaking as Christians do. For example, your ethics will be absolutely no different from Christian ethics because there is no such thing as non-Christian secular ethics present today. ‘You ought not to kill’. Don’t tell me that is an example of secular ethics. Even the notion of ‘ought not’, the normative notion itself, does not come from English: it comes from Christianity, from the Bible.
Aristotle, for example, does not have an ‘ought’. Indian languages do not have a ‘moral ought’ nor do the Chinese in their language in which Confucius wrote. These are not linguistic issues, Claus, these are problems of conceptual apparatuses that are culturally developed. So, it is in that sense that I speak about Galileo and say he made sense to the Europeans. They used his findings to investigate nature because they believed fundamentally that nature has a structure and pattern and a law which has to be discovered by human investigation. They would say that without such a structure the universe should be chaos. The whole of 2,000 years of European culture believes that, and that was Galileo’s idea as well. It is a background belief, of course, but it is a background belief of that culture and we are talking about difference between cultures. Translation is always a translation between people who use sentences, who use natural languages. So, I am shifting the level of the problem.
Last point, there is something to be said for your claim regarding the notion of belief&amp;ndash;that you can have a concept, but do not have a word&amp;ndash;that is absolutely true. That is our daily experience. I feel like saying something but I don’t know how to say it. So, you can have some sense of a concept but defined psychologically not linguistically or so cognitively. I do not know how to put it in a natural sentence. Right. But you are making out of it logical and philosophical points.
Let me put it very sharply. The notion of having a belief and the belief is always about something; this is a specific conception of man, of human beings&amp;ndash;there is philosophical anthropology which attributes some notion of intention to human beings. One of the extraordinary things about the Indian tradition is the absence of this notion of intentionality:  &lt;em&gt;agyana&lt;/em&gt;. They call it &lt;em&gt;maaya&lt;/em&gt; and many different things. So the nature of human being in the Indian tradition is that we are non-intentional creatures, which is completely incomprehensible within the framework of Christian culture. So, entertaining having a belief is not a linguistic, psychological, epistemological fact which is applicable to all human beings but is a specific assumption about the nature of human beings that comes from the Bible. So when saying that Indians have beliefs, you are not making use of any understanding of language – you are making use of a religious concept/understanding of man and saying that is what Indians have. Of course, you can say that; people have been saying that for 500 years. That is not the issue.
The issue is: is this how Indians understand themselves? In fact, if you look at the languages you find there is greater affinity when you talk of using work-words. They do not say ‘I got angry’ but ‘anger came upon me’ &amp;ndash; this is a very typical old classical Greek way of talking. ‘Why did you say that?’ ‘I do not know, my tongue moved that way’. I am literally translating local Indian languages into English&amp;ndash;this is the way we talk. In fact, even the subject notion, is not simply a linguistic subject or verb subject in action, the fundamental ontological notion of subject itself is missing in India as also the notion of agency.
Take the problem about truth: the notion of truth for applying to sentences, to propositions by some other philosophers is a very philosophical disease. If you look at the middle-ages, take Aquinas for example, he had two notions of truth: &lt;em&gt;adeequatio re&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;. One is which is adequate to the object; the other which is adequate to thoughts. Hegel used the same notion. Tarski also says there are multiple notions of truth. That notion of truth — &lt;em&gt;adaquatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt; as it prevailed for 1,900 years in Western culture referred to the fact that objects are adequate to how God conceives them. That is &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;adequate not to human intellects, to God’s intellect. &lt;em&gt;Adequatio re&lt;/em&gt; had to do with how one related the word to both these notions and emerged, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; from any understanding of language, truth, philosophy, or logic, it arose from commenting on theologies and commenting the Bible.  (pp 162-166 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Narratives vs Theories</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:34:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The question requires deeper handling so you will forgive me for the brevity of my response but you will get some idea of where I stand.
Regarding the first question as to whether we reject social science itself, I am aware that many people have made this suggestion. I am not so much hung up on the word &amp;lsquo;social science&amp;rsquo; but I do believe that we need to systematically reflect on our experiences in the world. A systematic reflection on experiences in the form of a theory is what we can conveniently call social science. We need theories about the world to understand the World. Systematic thinking means use of certain criteria to decide which theories are good or not, etc. and which to choose. The best thing would be to appeal to the history of the natural sciences over say four hundred years to see how they have done it, what kind of criteria they used. Thus, I belong to the group which advocates systematic reflection on experience, and in that sense, I belong to the group which says we need social science.
Your second question was about Indians having different ways of understanding experience: you spoke of narratives and the autobiography of Tulsi Ram. This raises the question of what form these reflections are going to take. To give a crude example: are they going to be mathematized? Will they take the form of scientific laws or of narratives? That is a very interesting question. But all narratives are not social science: in that case every novelist would have a scientific theory. If a text is an autobiography, it is not social science.
pp 103-4 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A priori assumptions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:13:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I am going to ask for a clarification on a question which I find very troubling. Let me first read how you have formulated the problem from the text: Sanskrit scholars need modem social scientists. What disturbs me in anthropological fieldwork is that Sanskrit literature is made to play the role of native informer to social scientists, with the anthropologists asking themselves as they might with Maori culture: is there something valuable which has been lost?
Claus Oetke also makes the same point. Even if you say that the dialogue between the primitive and the anthropologist is sophisticated, native informers are not merely informants. This idea, this interaction pattern which has existed for the last forty years has a double bias&amp;ndash;that of the anthropologist and that of the native informant. They have very powerful dialogues but anthropologists fundamentally take a priori positions, assuming that Sanskritists are the only ones who hold the key: they do not really believe that non-Sanskritists could possibly have anything to contribute.
But it would be absurd to dismiss Indian culture a priori without an investigation into India&amp;rsquo;s intellectual contributions without entertaining the possibility that Indian culture and tradition might today in a very significant sense be a challenge to the Western traditions which form our intellectual background. Your question shuts it out because it comes from Sanskrit. In your story of the fieldwork model, all Indian parameters answer the sophisticated social scientists model. I am surprised because you have another strand which goes in the opposite direction. But the fundamental framework you are using suggests maximally that we might learn something like Sanskrit aesthetics, rasa theory, etc. or even something like curry. This kind of trivialization has resulted from colonialism: it has been and is, very suppressive.
pp 42-43 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>It's not about respect for religion</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/its-not-about-respect-for-religion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 16:56:48 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/its-not-about-respect-for-religion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sacred determines what profane is; it is not about respect for religion.
The film &lt;em&gt;Innocence of Muslims&lt;/em&gt;  has turned cities around the world upside down in the past week, and threatens to continue to do so. “We never insult other prophets”, says the tenor of several Muslims, “so why can’t we demand that Mohammed receive respect? We respect others; why do they insult us?&amp;quot; Others argued that the anger stems from a demand for “freedom”: the right of a community to be free from serious insults against its identity and values.
As with the Mohammed cartoons from a few years ago, the same cliché appears in the debates: there must be more respect for the other. Everyone also believes that he has that respect for the other. But despite all that self-proclaimed respect, the world has not become more peaceful. What is going on then?
For Muslims, it is the religious issue of ridiculing the prophet. But for whom is Mohammed a prophet? Only for those who believe in Islam. That point applies to all religious symbols. Something is always a symbol for a certain person; what is a symbol for one is not for the other. Take a heathen like me: for me, neither the cross nor the prophet Mohammed symbolizes anything. The former is one thing and the latter is a human. The Sikhs in India may consider the turban as their religious symbol, but that is neither the case for me nor for a Protestant.
&lt;strong&gt;Requirement to repent&lt;/strong&gt;
Something is only a religious symbol within the confines of a particular religion. Outside, it no longer has the same symbolic value. What then does it mean to demand that non-Muslims respect Mohammed? Is it a requirement to recognize him as a religious symbol or as a prophet? In that case, it comes down to a requirement to convert to Islam. Without that step, Mohammed can never become a religious symbol or a prophet to me and any other non-Muslim. What then is the significance of the complaint that the film &amp;ldquo;pokes fun at the prophet&amp;rdquo; and that one should not do that?
Muslims argue that depicting the prophet Mohammed is profane, because the prophet has forbidden depictions of himself and Allah. The answer is simple: the prophet&amp;rsquo;s words are only valid for those who accept him as a prophet. This rule has no power for non-Muslims.
But the question is: are we doing something immoral by not “respecting” their sense of profane? To answer that, we need to expand our perspective. To this day, some Protestants openly criticize Catholics by calling the Pope “the Antichrist”, portraying the Catholic Church as “the devil&amp;rsquo;s church”, and condemning Catholics as “devil worshipers”. Europe had decades of wars over it. To this day those central theses of Protestantism remain profane to the Catholics, just as the existence of Catholicism itself remains profane to many Protestants. What should we do if it is said that one group should not do what the other considers profane?
As an Indian, I look with even more amazement at the demands of the protesting Muslims. For centuries it has been at the core of Islam to describe Indian traditions (Hinduism, Jainism, Buddhism) as idolatry and false demonic religion. According to Islam, Hindus worship Satan and his companions: their elephant god Ganesha, the adulterous Krishna or the phallic Shiva. That image is still current. Are such statements about the gods of India not offensive? Can one then demand that Muslims deny their basic doctrines on idolatry, God and Satan? If Islam did that, it would end its own existence as a religion. In other words, from a pagan perspective, the existence of a religion such as Islam (or Christianity) is itself “sacrilege.” The core of these religions transforms millions of people in Asia into idol worshipers and worshipers of the devil.
Muslims must be consistent: if they don&amp;rsquo;t want people to blaspheme their religion, they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it themselves to other religions and traditions.
&lt;strong&gt;Superior to all&lt;/strong&gt;
In fact, if they are not willing to accept this conclusion, then the protesting Muslims’ claim comes down to this: the world must treat them as an exceptional religious community, equal to none and superior to all. Of course they believe that is the case. That is precisely why that belief is unacceptable to the rest of the world. The whole debate is not about “respect for other religions,” or “freedom of speech.” It is about a religious group, which considers itself superior to everyone else, demanding that all the world endorse the truth of this belief. Who is willing to do that? Not me in any case.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ancient Roman Culture and Early Christianity: A Pagan Perspective from India</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ancient-roman-culture-and-early-christianity-a-pagan-perspective-from-india/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 18:58:06 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ancient-roman-culture-and-early-christianity-a-pagan-perspective-from-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/5497450/A_Pagan_Perspective_on_Early_Christianity_and_Ancient_Rome"&gt;Original.&lt;/a&gt;  [ Appeared in  &lt;a href="https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/4259026"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christendom en filosofie : opstellen over wijsbegeerte, wereldbeeld en wetenschappen van het antieke christendom over Nietzsche tot fundamentalisme vandaag&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; p.51-82]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, we would like to reflect upon the contemporary relevance of the encounter between ancient Roman culture and Early Christianity. There is a reason for choosing this theme. Today, a few heathen cultures (for instance, those of India and China) have become important once again to the history of mankind. Irrespective of what else is said about the cultures of India or China, in the course of this millennium, these two are going to have a significant impact in the world. In the renewed meeting between India and China on the one hand and the western culture on the other, two issues are going to become central once again: (a) how they look at Christianity and Christian cultures and (b) how the western culture has learnt to look at them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Between ignorance and deception: Satish Deshpande's idea of reservations</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:54:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Clearly, advocates of the caste-based reservation system are worried by the recent upheavals in Gujarat and beyond. In his &amp;ldquo;The Patidar idea of reservations&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt;, September 5), Delhi University sociologist Satish Deshpande attempts to ridicule the Patidars&amp;rsquo; demand for OBC status while expressing his support for the reservation system. In this piece, I do not wish to defend or attack any particular movement, such as that of the Patidars or the Gujjars, but merely draw attention to one simple point: Deshpande attempts to defend ignorance and immorality by drawing on arguments that exhibit the same properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Which intolerance is growing in India?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:42:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly loud voices are to be heard from different capital cities in India about growing intolerance in Indian society. The western press picks up echoes and magnifies them, while ridiculing Modi’s visit to Great Britain. While one can understand that Indians chant mantras, why are Europeans reproducing them? Looking from the outside, this is a very puzzling phenomenon. Because it is unclear what exactly is at stake here, I’d like to raise some questions and reflect about them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Smriti Irani will destroy Indian education for good</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/smriti-irani-will-destroy-indian-education-for-good/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:40:04 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/smriti-irani-will-destroy-indian-education-for-good/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/"&gt;recent piece&lt;/a&gt; on the valedictory speech of the minister of HRD at a Kolkata workshop elicited many replies from the readers. Some found that we indulged in a personal attack, our piece lacked &amp;ldquo;logic&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;argumentation&amp;rdquo; and one of her secret admirers, in her defence, even sent us a link to a report by Saptadwipa Ghosal in &lt;em&gt;The Echo of India&lt;/em&gt;. Such responses demand an adequate reply. Actually, we wanted to show how profound her new education policy is and we failed in demonstrating it. In this piece, through the use of sophisticated hermeneutics, we shall make our mistake good.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Smriti Irani as HRD minister was a terrible choice</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:30:57 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;From the mouth of some babes, pearls of wisdom and truth fall like gentle rain from heaven. From the mouth of others, idiocies pour in a torrent and are considered truth only because they occupy positions of power. We leave it to the reader to decide to which group our minister of human resource development Smriti Irani belongs. Keep in mind that she determines to a large extent the course of education, including higher education policies in India. Irani&amp;rsquo;s comments on education at the conclusion of the National Seminar on the New Education Policy in Kolkata would be shocking if they were made by a mature and intelligent human being. But, as is said, from the mouth of the babes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Questioning the axioms</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are three ideas in the West about Law that are taken as axioms. The first: all societies are founded on Law; if they are not, they ought to be. The second is that Law teaches and educates a people. Third is their corollary: only thus do a people become a Nation. As far as I know, none has shown their empirical truth or proved that they are logically necessary. But their truth-value is undisputed. When they ruled India, the British followed these axioms: they tried to educate us through Law, interfered in our festivals and social practices and the State tried to educate a barbaric people by enacting  ‘just’ laws. Romulus gave Law and made a group into a people; Moses gave Law and made a people into a Nation; Mohammed gave Law and transformed multiple nations into a caliphate; Manu acquires the exalted status of a Law-giver for the ‘Hindus’. These ideas are not dated, apparently. Today, they enjoy the same privilege they had during the colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How about speaking the truth about reservations?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 12:20:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens to the future of Indian intellectual scene when most of projects driven by its intelligentsia propagate perverted truths for self-seeking purposes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Satyam Vada, Dharmam Chara”, “Satyameva Jayate”&lt;/em&gt; are but two of the well-known Sanskrit sayings that are supposed to indicate the values placed upon truth and truth-telling in Indian culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes as a surprise, therefore, to read three items in the newspaper and a comment on a blog which seem to follow ‘truth’. But in such a way that &lt;em&gt;it becomes perverse&lt;/em&gt;. Because all the four issues are important, I would like to briefly talk about each.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Indian Jews</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-indian-jews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 23:19:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-indian-jews/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;social science debate in India has been hijacked by the struggle between secularism and&lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; for decades now. usually the &lt;em&gt;Sangh Parivar&lt;/em&gt; is blamed for this turn of events. However, it could well be argued that the &lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; ideologues simply adopted the stance of the secularists.  Perhaps the best illustration is the case of anti-Brahminism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be against &amp;ldquo;Brahminism&amp;rdquo; is part and parcel of the political correctness of progressive scholars in twenty-first-century India, much like being against Muslims is part of the message of their &lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; colleagues. This indicates that something is very wrong with the Indian academic debate. Promotion of animosity towards a religious tradition or its followers is not acceptable today, but it becomes truly perverse when the intelligentsia endorses it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How free are we?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-free-are-we/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 23:15:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-free-are-we/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This has been a tumultuous decade for the academic study of India. In his recent &lt;em&gt;Offence: The Hindu Case&lt;/em&gt; (2009), Salil Tripathi provides a timely overview of the growing censorship and harassment that scholars working on India have faced. Not a pretty sight to behold: people have felt the need to ban books and terrorize authors, hassle teachers and disrupt classes, toss eggs at some and blacken others’ faces. Academics now run the risk of smear campaigns, court cases and physical intimidation; all because certain groups feel offended by what they write about the Indian past or the Hindu traditions. The facts are difficult to miss. Hence, the threat that Hindu nationalism poses to academic freedom has caused commotion around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What can India offer?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 23:26:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, India has become a global player of significant political and economical impact. Europe and India are facing each other as equal partners in pursuit of greater economic and political co-operation. This confronts both India and Europe with a challenge. The intelligentsia, the business world, politicians, educators and others, will have to answer the following question: What can India offer to the world of today and tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not tackle this problem directly but instead take up one of its sub-questions: to whom is this problem important and why? I believe it is important to both Indians and Europeans but for different reasons. In this article, I will spell out and reflect upon some of these reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Indian View from Outside: Quotas, Rational &amp; Moral?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-view-from-outside-quotas-rational-moral/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 19:19:36 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-view-from-outside-quotas-rational-moral/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Read Jakob de Roover&amp;rsquo;s piece on &lt;a href="http://www.dailyo.in/politics/satish-deshpande-patidar-reservation-system-india-dalits-obcs-hardik-patel/story/1/6119.html"&gt;reservations on dailyon.in&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; on &lt;a href="http://swarajyamag.com/politics/counterview-ambedkar-was-wrong-about-hinduism-the-right-can-stop-trying-to-appropriate-him/"&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt;. From the perspective of constitution, constitution debates, check &lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/16478230/Caste-based_reservation_and_social_justice_in_India"&gt;https://www.academia.edu/16478230/Caste-based_reservation_and_social_justice_in_India&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem that has plagued India since Independence has flared up again: caste-based reservations for education, employment and career promotions. In the last four decades of living in Europe, I have heard both sides of the debate. As an Indian living abroad, it appears to me that these debates actually raise one single question: Are Indians irrational or immoral, or both? This is the un-debated side of the reservation discourse in India. Let me explain. Is caste-based reservation a rational policy to follow? The answer to this question does not require a definition of ‘rationality.’ Instead, the issue is: does this policy eventuate in irrational consequences or effects?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dark Hour of Secularism: Hindu Fundamentalism and Colonial Liberalism in India</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dark-hour-of-secularism-hindu-fundamentalism-colonial-liberalism-in-india/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2015 18:26:26 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dark-hour-of-secularism-hindu-fundamentalism-colonial-liberalism-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The relation between religion and politics remains one of the important issues of our time. The discussions on this relation swing between two extremes: religious fundamentalism and liberal secularism. These are regarded as opposites. As the liberal perspective sees it, the secular state and its principles of neutrality and toleration are antidotes to religious fundamentalism[1]. Recently, this view has been challenged. Several authors point out that fundamentalism and secularism are not self-contained opposites, but are intertwined in significant ways[2].&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>US Commission for International Christian Freedom</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/us-commission-for-international-religious-freedom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 09:26:07 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/us-commission-for-international-religious-freedom/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The annual reports of the US Commission for International Religious Freedom (USCIRF) have long irked politicians and citizens from countries placed on its ‘watch list’. This is no different in India. In the 2015 report released about a fortnight ago, the country again occupies an unenviable spot in Tier 2, which includes countries where the religious freedom violations engaged in or tolerated by the government are serious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Striking about this year’s report, however, is its claim that incidents of religiously-motivated and communal violence have ‘reportedly’ increased for three consecutive years in India. “According to Muslim and Christian NGOs that track communal incidents,” it adds, “2014 statistics, yet to be released by the ministry, will be likely higher” than the 823 incidents recorded in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rape of a Country -- Jakob de Roover</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/rape-of-a-country-jakob-de-roover/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 21:05:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/rape-of-a-country-jakob-de-roover/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rape of a Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jakob De Roover&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Imagine. A filmmaker travels to Belgium because she has heard about the pedophilia scandals in the country. She directs a documentary film including an interview with an infamous pedophile, who says that the girls he raped had actually seduced him and that they really enjoyed it. The filmmaker then comments that Belgian society is responsible for creating such pedophiles by teaching them what to think. Most men in this country are programmed in this way, she insists. In fact, this is all part of a larger disease and culture, which is also reflected in Belgian cinema. How would we Belgians react? We would find this shocking and infuriating. It is as though pedophilia is an expression of the core of our culture, as though we are programmed for child abuse.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Magic of ‘Radicalization’?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-magic-of-radicalization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 21:49:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-magic-of-radicalization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;After the Paris attacks came the questions: Is this violence caused by Islam or unrelated to religion? Are the perpetrators believers or madmen? Do they represent the extremists that we find in any ideology?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses were diverse: ‘Islam is a threat to free speech’. But many Muslims joined the protest marches in defence of the freedom of expression. ‘Not all Muslims are terrorists, but most terrorists are Muslims’. The statistics show otherwise. ‘Madmen have neither colour nor religion’. Yet the ‘professionals’ in Paris screamed ‘Allahu Akbar’.  And then appeared the magical word ‘radicalization’. From the mayor to the teacher, from the politician to the policeman, everyone now knows what the problem is and where we should look for solutions: strict measures against ‘radicalized Muslims’ and ‘deradicalization programmes’ developed by ‘radicalization experts’.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Translation, Interpretation and Culture: On the disingenuity of a comparative theology</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 00:42:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balu&amp;rsquo;s paper on comparative theology, and in particular Francis Clooney&amp;rsquo;s:
&lt;a href="https://www.academia.edu/5497443/On_the_Disingenuity_of_a_Comparative_Theology"&gt;Translation, interpretration and culture: on the disingenuity of a comparative theology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Secular State and Religious Conflict: Liberal Neutrality and the Indian Case of Pluralism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 08:27:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-secular-state-and-religious-conflict-liberal-neutrality-and-the-indian-case-of-pluralism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s Note: This article appeared in the Journal of Political Philosophy. Authored by SN Balagangadhara and Jakob De Roover. For an alternative research programme (paradigm)  for studying India, Indian culture and Indian culture, study Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Reconceptualizing Indian Studies&lt;/strong&gt;, published by OUP, India.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are few places in the contemporary world where the problems of cultural pluralism are as acute as they are in India. The Indian case poses fundamental challenges to the political theory of toleration. By tackling the problem of religious conversion, our analysis shows that the dominant way of conceiving state neutrality becomes untenable in the Indian context. The Indian state, modelled after the liberal democracies in the West, is the harbinger of religious conflict in India because of its conception of toleration and state neutrality. More of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; in India will end up feeding what it fights: the so-called &amp;lsquo;Hindu fundamentalism&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to speak for the Indian traditions: an agenda for the future--SN Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-speak-for-the-indian-traditions-an-agenda-for-the-future/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 05:56:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-speak-for-the-indian-traditions-an-agenda-for-the-future/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: This article appeared in the Journal of American Academy of Religion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper attempts a contrast between the process and the structure of the Christian and the Indian spirituality. Drawing attention to their dissimilarities, it attempts to reformulate the differences among the Indian traditions in a novel way. It argues that cultures and traditions are not just different; but that they differ from each other in different ways as well. The future of religious studies, it is suggested, is dependent on developing the ability to develop new ways of describing the differences between cultures and traditions. This is the agenda for the future. As a correlate to this task, the paper suggests that we replace the question &amp;ldquo;who speaks &amp;lsquo;for&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;about&amp;rsquo; a religion?&amp;rdquo; with a more pregnant and a more accurate reformulation: &amp;ldquo;how to speak for a religion in the Academy?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How do we understand the concept of Communal Violence?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 05:17:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-do-we-understand-the-concept-of-communal-violence/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We all agree that events like the Gujarat riots are tragic and terrible. But what is the role of intellectuals in avoiding similar tragedies in the future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why can’t religion be political?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the duty of the intellectual is to try and help us understand the nature of the events and the violence involved. In India and abroad, the concepts of ‘communalism’ and ‘communal violence’ are often used to analyse these riots. These tell us that the main cause behind the Hindu-Muslim conflicts in India is the use of religion for political ends. It is often added that religion itself is not responsible for the riots, but rather its misuse by power-hungry clerics and politicians. The harm of communalism lies in its mixing of political aims and religious identities, which is taken to cause violence. Let us have a closer look at this concept of communal violence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reconceptualizing India Studies by Balagangadhara--a new book</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/reconceptualizing-india-studies-by-balagangadhara-a-new-book/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2012 06:25:24 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/reconceptualizing-india-studies-by-balagangadhara-a-new-book/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to be an Indian in this time and age? What does India have to give to the contemporary world? These overarching questions that echo in the mind of the post-colonial Indian cannot be truly answered by Western frameworks instituted at the behest of colonialism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book sets the stage for a reconceptualization of India studies. Clearing away intellectual deadwood, it initiates a process of comparative study of cultures. The volume scrutinizes the Western studies on India, including contemporary writings on Hinduism, the nature of inter-cultural dialogues, and their implications for normative political philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparing India and the West—S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparing-india-and-the-west-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 10:09:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparing-india-and-the-west-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href="http://asianetwork.org/ane-archived-issues/2008-fall/anex2008-fall-balagangadhara.pdf"&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;, published in ASIANetwork Exchange &lt;strong&gt;XVI&lt;/strong&gt; (1): 57–63.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the last two decades, I have been pursuing an unorthodox way of studying cultural differences, focusing mainly on the Indian and the western cultures. Because I believe that one can answer questions about the circumscription of the words &amp;lsquo;Indian&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;western&amp;rsquo; cultures satisfactorily (Balangangadhara, 1994), I will assume their intelligibility in what follows. In this paper, I want to raise a rather intriguing problem about comparing these two cultures. I shall do that without looking at other approaches to the issue and in the form of an argument. In order to come to the point quickly, let me make use of Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Courting controversy in the West</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:28:31 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sustained efforts by certain Hindu groups in the west to redefine and &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; long existing Hindu traditions are perhaps reflective of their desire to put in place a cogent and structured religious system that is able to hold its own against other scripture-based religions. Concomitantly, American identity politics and European political correctness is also &amp;ldquo;forcing&amp;rdquo; minority communities to assert their separate &amp;ldquo;churches&amp;rdquo;, as a way of emphasising their own distinct religious or ethnic identity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secularism and Absence of Theory</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:23:55 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularism-and-absence-of-theory/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A text like &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/" title="The Vacuity of Secularism"&gt;my article on the secularism debate&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;EPW&lt;/em&gt;, September 28, 2002), is something more than a sequence of sentences. This is a scientific text, which builds an argument. Therefore, the different sentences have different status according to their function in the argument. Some are premises, and others state the conclusions that follow from these. Some sentences illustrate the point made, yet others provide evidence. To understand such a text, one has to grasp the logical relations between these different sentences.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Vacuity of Secularism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:20:34 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-vacuity-of-secularism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the Indian Debate and Its Western Origins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The rise of Hindutva has often been interpreted as a threat to the secular state. Similarly, the recent outbursts of Hindu-Muslim conflict are said to be related to the decay of secularism. The author argues that the concept of secularism is fundamentally obscure, since it is founded upon an arbitrary distinction between the religious and the secular. The belief that religion should be separated from politics is a normative dogma that precedes all theoretical analysis of the Indian situation. Therefore, this concept of secularism prevents us from understanding the problems of pluralism in contemporary India, instead of helping us to solve them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Question of Conversion in India</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:14:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian debate on religious conversion has been an ongoing one for a few centuries now. However, the mutual understanding between the advocates and the adversaries of conversion has not advanced much. This paper suggests that this is due to the fact that Hindus and Christians refer to two different objects when they discuss &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. The traits which the Christians ascribe to religion account for the premium they put on the right to convert, while the traits of the Hindu view of religion explain the opposition to conversion. As the two parties attribute mutually exclusive properties to religion, they encounter difficulties while seeking to make sense of each other&amp;rsquo;s claims about religion and conversion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Review of Imagining Hinduism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-imagining-hinduism/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:47:09 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-imagining-hinduism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Review of &lt;em&gt;Imaging Hinduism: A Postcolonial perspective.&lt;/em&gt; By Sharada Sugirtharajah. Routledge, 2003. 164 pages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; This book is the first of its kind to bring post-colonial perspectivesinto a study of Hinduism. Consequently, there are no conventionalreference points for the author to use to build her narrative. She has to figure out how to use the conceptual apparatus ofthe one to study the other. In this sense, although the bookis experimental in its nature, there is nothing hesitant ortentative about some of the conclusions she draws. How successfulis the author in bringing the two, the study of Hinduism anda post-colonial perspective, together? If someone is influencedby post-colonial thought, the judgment will have to be in thepositive. However, having never been enamored by this genreof thinking, I find her framework both limiting and damagingto the study of Hinduism. Before I identify some of my problems,a few words about the book are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Moral Domains. An Essay on Selfless Morality and the Moral Self—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 21:48:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Disquieting Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
Arthur Danto, the well-known American philosopher, prefaced a book he wrote in the 70’s on oriental thought and moral philosophy titled &lt;em&gt;Mysticism and Morality&lt;/em&gt; with the following words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The factual beliefs (that the civilizations of the East) take for granted are &amp;hellip;too alien to our (the West’s) representations of the World to be grafted on to it, and &lt;em&gt;in consequence their moral systems are unavailable to us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Action Sciences. An Essay on Knowing to Act and Acting to Know—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:48:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;a href="https://www.philosophica.ugent.be/article/82484/galley/202298/view/"&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;, published  &lt;em&gt;Philosophica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;40&lt;/strong&gt; (2): 77–107]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should action sciences exist, it is obvious what they would have to study; the nature of human action, the kind of knowledge that actions generate, the process of learning to perform different types of action and so forth. Comparative anthropology, as a discipline, studies and contrasts, where such contrasts are possible, the different ways in which human beings organize their lives, think about and experience both themselves and world around them. A culture is a form of life and, as such, it is a way of going about the world. One would therefore expect to find a deep and intimate relation between action sciences on the one hand, and studies of culture on the other. A perusal of literature, however, shows the fact of the matter to be different.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Future of the Present. Thinking Through Orientalism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:40:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-future-of-the-present-thinking-through-orientalism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Though the book was published nearly two decades ago, Said&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt; continues to be topical. Many have rejected the message of this work; others have attempted to develop its arguments yet further. This article will not be one more interpretation of Said&amp;rsquo;s book; after all, there are many such interpretations, including Said&amp;rsquo;s own. Instead, it probes the phenomenon of &amp;lsquo;post-Orientalism&amp;rsquo;. Even here, the intention is not to map its contours either historically or conceptually. Rather, the focus is on raising the question: what next after &lt;em&gt;Orientalism&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Rhetorics in Cultures.</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-rhetorics-in-cultures/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:27:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-rhetorics-in-cultures/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is best that we begin on a personal note. Neither of the two authors of this article is a &amp;lsquo;specialist&amp;rsquo; in the domain of argumentation theory. Even though we have picked up smatterings of logic, we are not professionals working on either informal or formal logic. One of us is a practicing anthropologist, while the other is oriented towards comparative anthropology. And yet, we are invited to speak to an audience comprising of people specializing in dialogue logics, argumentation theory, psychology and such like. If the invitation to present a paper is not mistake or an oversight on the part of the organizers of this colloquium, then it could only mean that there is an expectation regarding our contributions: anthropologists have something to say about rhetorics, argumentations and their norms, which is of relevance to specialists like you.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The reality of elusive man? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-reality-of-elusive-man-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 09:22:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-reality-of-elusive-man-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &amp;rsquo;the greatest mystery of our humanness&amp;rsquo;, Sinari raises the following questions: &amp;ldquo;Why are we present in the world rather than not being there at all? Why are we present to ourselves as world-experiencers and world-explorers rather than being simply there as perhaps animals are&amp;rdquo; (p.1) In brief reply to his provocative paper, I would like to reflect on the nature of these queries and with the issue: what would count as an answer to these questions&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Understanding and Imagination: A Critical Notice of Halbfass and Inden</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 07:10:42 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/understanding-and-imagination-a-critical-notice-of-halbfass-and-inden-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the last decade or so, a new restlessness has begun to disturb the calm facade of the social scientific academia. As yet, it has no name. Better said, it has many names: from &amp;lsquo;reflexive&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;lsquo;post-modern&amp;rsquo;. The ferment is not widespread, but the voices of discontent are coherent and articulate. The critical voices indicate the many kinds of dissatisfaction they have with the status and nature of social sciences. Even though most dissenters cannot be grouped as representatives of any one tradition, many of their writings stand out above the rest. Two such authors are Wilhelm Halbfass and Ronald Inden; each has written a book that is worthy of attention and respect.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Review of Staal’s Rules Without Meaning –S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:25:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;FRITS STAAL. &lt;em&gt;Rules Without Meaning: Ritual, Mantras and the Human Sciences. Toronto Studies in Religion&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 4. New York and Bern: Peter Lang, 1989 xxii+490.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to set the tone of this review article, let me begin straightway with a confession: I have been a closet admirer of Frits Staal ever since I discovered his writings in 1987. The reasons that undergird my attitude are several: firstly, most of his writings are about a culture I am familiar with, namely, India; secondly, absent from them is the dewy-eyed romanticism that is pernicious to any serious study of cultures and people; thirdly, present in them are insights that are immensely important and extremely exciting; fourthly, the theses argued for are the results of absolutely pioneering research which fly in the face of deeply entrenched commonsense wisdom; and so on… He is my fellow-traveler on more tracks than one, and my own thinking on several subjects over the last few years carry the deep imprint of Staal&amp;rsquo;s rigorous thinking and painstaking enquiries.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Review of Amartya Sen's Argumentative Indian—S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:17:06 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/review-of-argumentative-indian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, there are multiple images of India current in the West. There is the mystic India, an image that the German Romantics created and the &amp;lsquo;flower children&amp;rsquo; of the sixties made popular. There is the third world India with enormous poverty and suffering, which the developmental workers have projected. There is also the India, the centre of IT outsourcing, which the developments in the last decade have brought into existence, and so on. Amartya Sen, the Indian noble prize-winner in Economics, has written a book on &amp;ldquo;The Argumentative Indian&amp;rdquo; which speaks of an India that he wants us to consider. This India is an India with a history of toleration and pluralism, an India that has brought forth its own version of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo;, and an India that is every bit rational, discursive and analytical as the western culture itself.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>On Colonial Experience and the Indian Renaissance: A prolegomenon to a Project—S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the striking things about the British colonial rule is its success in developing certain ways of talking about the Indian culture and society. The British criticised the Indian &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;, the Indian &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo;, the Indian education system, practices like &amp;lsquo;sati&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;untouchability&amp;rsquo;, and so on and so forth. They redrew the outlines of Indian intellectual history as indigenous responses to some of the ills they saw in the Indian society and culture: for example, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, as it emerged out of their reconstruction, was a revolt against &amp;lsquo;Brahmanism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo;. Many Indian intellectuals emphasized British criticism by making &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; in the latter their own: the Arya Samaj, the Brahmo Samaj, many Hindu &amp;lsquo;reform&amp;rsquo; movements, and so on exemplify this trend. I say &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; and place it in scare quotes because the &lt;em&gt;unbroken line of continuity&lt;/em&gt; between the colonial period and the one following the Indian independence raises two &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of questions. The first is this: would there have been such a line of continuity if there was no &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; to the British portrayal of our history, traditions, and culture? This question uses the &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; of continuity to suggest that the British descriptions &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; That is, our current experience of our culture and society appears to lend truth-value to the colonial descriptions of India. The second question transforms our &amp;lsquo;current experience&amp;rsquo; itself into a problem: does such a line of continuity indicate that our experiences themselves are still colonial in nature? This question throws doubts upon the &amp;lsquo;facticity&amp;rsquo; of the British descriptions of India, and suggests that they &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;lsquo;untrue&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; In the process, it also challenges us to look more closely and investigate our own experiences today. That is, the second question withholds assent to the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of the colonial descriptions of India and of some of the claims we make about our experiences of our culture and society today. To some extent, and only to some extent, the so-called &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; writings can be seen as attempts to make sense of the second question. Even though I do not fancy the label of being a &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; myself, I perceive a shared sense of a quest with them. &lt;em&gt;There is something deeply, deeply wrong with the line of continuity that exists between the colonial period and today&amp;rsquo;s India,&lt;/em&gt; and the challenge is to say what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>India and Her traditions: A Reply to Jeffrey Kripal – S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/india-and-her-traditions-a-reply-to-jeffrey-kripal-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 19:16:44 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/india-and-her-traditions-a-reply-to-jeffrey-kripal-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before addressing this writing to Jeffrey Kripal, I would like to very clearly stipulate some of my basic stances so that the discussion does not get derailed into these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A) Even though the communication will be directed to the person of Jeffrey Kripal, it is not &lt;em&gt;ad hominem&lt;/em&gt; but issue-oriented. However, I will eschew making some &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of qualifications academics are prone to make, so that any intelligent, but layperson can not only follow the discussion but also &lt;em&gt;evaluate&lt;/em&gt; what is being said.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>