<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Worship on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/worship/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Worship on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 13:52:54 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/worship/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Translation or Random Substitution: Worship and Puja</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 13:52:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translation-or-random-substitution-worship-and-puja/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Firstly, you want to know whether there is anything intrinsically  wrong with performing idol worship the way it is with robbery.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let us assume that we agree we know what robbery is and that it is intrinsically wrong. We need to make these assumptions because (a) in all probability, the robbers do not see anything intrinsically wrong in the act of robbing; (b) even then, some of us might not be willing to call a &amp;lsquo;Robin hood&amp;rsquo; (who robs only the rich and passes on the spoils to the poor, retaining a modest &amp;lsquo;commission&amp;rsquo; for himself and fellow robbers) an immoral person; (c) to most of us, it is unclear whether the windfall profits that oil corporations have made in the last years constitute robbery or not and so on. Under these assumptions, you are drawing an analogy between idol worship and an act that a human being performs with respect to fellow-human beings. This analogy breaks down because idol worship is not a relation between human beings but between a particular act of a human being (called &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;) and the entity worshipped.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Worship a Human Invention?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 01:20:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us assume that the Church Fathers (or the Apostles or whoever else) planned to introduce an eschatological doctrine and some mode of worship. (Let us further assume that their reasoning or their strategy was something analogous to your impressions: their intention was to induce a sense of urgency and guilt.) Our problem is not to explain their possible motives but to explain the &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; of these strategies. Our questions are: why do all the Semitic religions (this reference to the Semitic religions is meant only keep the discussion simple) follow these strategies? Why are these strategies successful? (You can also go further and raise questions about their relative lack of success today in the western world, but we will ignore all such complications.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the process of answering these questions, you will inevitably be forced to appeal to the nature of human psychology. This appeal will, in its turn, make assumptions about human psychology: such is human psychology that these strategies are successful. If this assumption is made, you face a very serious problem with the fact that these strategies do not seem to work with a lot of human beings (atheists, heathens &amp;hellip;). In other words, you cannot explain the success of this strategy by appealing to &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; psychology. If you were to restrict it to the psychology of the believers &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt;, you will end up providing &lt;strong&gt;a circular explanation&lt;/strong&gt;: such is the psychology of the believers that they are susceptible to this strategy. (Instead, you might as well say that the strategy works with &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;people because it works with some people.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Suppose you take the following route: religion &amp;lsquo;works&amp;rsquo; only for those people who have a specific kind of psychology, you face the almost impossible task of providing some kind of empirical data across cultures and time. Further, you will also have to explain why people who were (and are) prone to guilt cease being believers. As though this is not enough, you will also have to explain why only &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; guilt-prone individuals become believers and some others do not. In short, this is an almost impossible exercise given our state of knowledge today.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As though these problems are not enough, any psychological assumption will have to answer two other important questions.&#xA;4.1. One is the presence of a &lt;strong&gt;manifest denial&lt;/strong&gt; of these psychological assumptions in the theologies of these religions. Worship expresses your love for God. Even if the Apostles (or whoever else) was a scoundrel (and the greatest genius that mankind has ever known) who used this claim as a palliative, why do people continue to accept and believe in it? Again, you will be forced to invent another psychological explanation: the believers are mentally deficient (in some appropriate sense of the term), whereas non-believers are intelligent enough to see through the strategies. Needless to say, this is simply an &lt;strong&gt;ad hoc&lt;/strong&gt; explanation without any kind of warrant or plausibility.&#xA;4.2. The second question is about the fact that the believers genuinely love their God. One will have to deny this. One has to insist that the believers mistakenly identify their feelings of guilt with love. Needless to say, the explanatory task here is of mind-boggling complexity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is a different kind of problem concealed in your difficulty, as soon as we realise that we need to explain the success of the strategies (to induce urgency and guilt). The intention of the apostles is not sufficient to guarantee its success: something called &amp;rsquo;the world&amp;rsquo; intervenes in between. It is not sufficient that I intend doing something to reach some goal in the world. I need to take the nature of the world into account as well, if I have to succeed. In short, the worry you express is a still-born child, if the goal is to understand what religion is.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Worship and eschatology (for instance) are not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; properties of an EI account. They are &lt;em&gt;contingent&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. given assumptions about our make-up, our capacities, and so on, we need to explain why all religions have such properties. In short, what I suggest is that, if we assume the existence of religion among human beings, all empirical religions will exhibit these properties. That is to say, if we come across a religion in some part of the earth that does not speak of worshipping God, does not have an eschatology, then my hypothesis is &lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One final point. I am not saying that everything that happened in history is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;. What I do say is that given the structure of religion, some &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of events had to happen. All religions are &lt;em&gt;compelled&lt;/em&gt; to speak of worship, eschatology and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why study the Western culture?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two substantial questions have been raised in response to &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/&#34;&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;: (a) why do we need to study and understand the Western culture in order to access our own traditions? (b) Is it my claim that Buddha and Shankara (for example) are irrelevant to us? One other sort of &amp;lsquo;objection&amp;rsquo; too has surfaced, albeit disguised as a characterization of what I have said: (c) is not my position itself illustrative of &amp;lsquo;Eurocentrism&amp;rsquo;? These issues are intertwined.  Hopefully, addressing them together will lend some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Puja and Worship</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:59:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/puja-and-worship-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says: if &amp;ldquo;pujya&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;worthy of worship&amp;rdquo;, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;puja&amp;rdquo; mean worship?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Pujya&amp;rsquo; means &amp;ldquo;deserving of &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. If &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo; translated as &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;, quite obviously one translates &amp;lsquo;pujya&amp;rsquo; as you do.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You see, what is at stake is not a mere &amp;rsquo;translation&amp;rsquo; problem.  It has to do with how the Indian culture (and not merely this one culture, I might add) has been, and continues to be, represented not just by Western intellectuals but also by the Indian intellectuals themselves. Let me give you an example, which should give you a sense of the nature of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>God, Devil (Satan), and Polytheism</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/god-devilsatan-and-polytheism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 02:47:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/god-devilsatan-and-polytheism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is true that the modern Jewish thought, which is more influenced by the Rabbinic than by apocalyptic or Qumranic literature, places less emphasis on the Devil. Rabbinic Judaism was less interested in building a demonology than others. It is one thing to say this, but quite another to say that the Judaic tradition knows of the Devil only in terms of the psychological &amp;lsquo;inclinations&amp;rsquo; in man. (It is equivalent to suggesting that there is no demonology in Judaic thought, a preposterous suggestion on any count.) Belial, Mastema, Azazel, Satanail, Sammael, Semyzza, or Satan do not name either psychological or spiritual &amp;lsquo;inclinations&amp;rsquo;, surely. (Think further of what Behemoth, Leviathan, etc. are). The Satan in the Book of Job is already an emissary of God (though not yet the personification of evil), and not a mere &amp;lsquo;inclination&amp;rsquo;. The Testaments of the Twelve Patriarchs name Belial or Satan as Chief of evil angels commanding the spirits of wrath, hatred, etc. and as lord of war, fornication, bloodshed, destruction, etc. He tempts and seduces humankind to error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple meanings: puja, thondam—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/multiple-meanings-puja-thondam-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 23:09:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/multiple-meanings-puja-thondam-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the multiple meanings for the Puja of Ganesha. Of course, there is no one &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo; to this act either now, or before, or in the future, as far as Indians (and the Westerners) are concerned. But that is not being disputed. The dispute arises when some meaning is alleged to portray the &amp;rsquo;experience&amp;rsquo; of a culture, when all it does is distort and deny the experience it is said to portray. However, there is an interesting question here, which is best illustrated using a contrast. In the Catholic Mass, there are &lt;em&gt;limits&lt;/em&gt; on what it could be said to mean to a believer. These limits are set by the Catholic theology and belief. (For instance, to a believer, it &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; mean celebrating the Devil.) The puja of Ganesha does not set any such limits to the person who does this puja. (But if someone comes and tells me that I cook sweets on Ganesha Chaturthi because it expresses my &amp;lsquo;subconscious&amp;rsquo; desire for Oral Sex, I am justified in challenging this claim as an &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of my cooking the sweets.) Here is the question: what is puja in the Indian traditions, if it does not have a particular meaning, and there are no limits on what it means? One thing is already clear: it cannot mean &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo;! These are the kind of questions I would like to ask; not what &amp;lsquo;interpretation&amp;rsquo; one gives to some action or the other. The answer I give should be capable of being &amp;rsquo;tested&amp;rsquo; in the Indian culture. Then, I will have begun producing an &amp;lsquo;objective&amp;rsquo; theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
