<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Indexical on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/indexical/</link><description>Recent content in Indexical on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 13:09:46 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/indexical/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Law of Excluded Middle: Christian Beliefs</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 13:09:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was expecting you to show me where &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/"&gt;the reasoning I formulated goes wrong&lt;/a&gt;, but you do not do so. The analogy you draw, I am afraid, does not quite do the job you want it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One can easily hold the following two beliefs (your example) without any fear of contradiction:
(a) There is only one way to Bombay (this is it) and (b) There are many ways to Bombay (this is one of them).
The &amp;lsquo;how&amp;rsquo; of it must be obvious: the &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo; is an indexical. Consequently, any person can hold both these beliefs together (at the same time or about the same route) without being contradictory (depending upon what he points out using the word &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo;).
In fact, even statements like (c) &amp;ldquo;Route 19 is the only way to Bombay&amp;rdquo; and (d) &amp;ldquo;Route 24 is one of the ways to Bombay&amp;rdquo; can be held to be true by one and the same person at the same time without fear of contradiction. ( Both  statements would be true if Route 24 allows one to join Route 19 at some point or the other.) In other words, Minimus, your examples do not work the way you want them to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regarding my reasoning, this is what you say:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindus may have ideas/opinions about the beliefs of the Christians but &amp;ldquo;beliefs about&amp;rdquo; cannot be compared to &amp;ldquo;beliefs&amp;rdquo; and I think that is the error.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Achievements of Indology: Esoteric Indian traditions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/achievements-of-indology-esoteric-indian-traditions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2011 23:10:30 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/achievements-of-indology-esoteric-indian-traditions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A science of cultures is not Atmagyaana or Brahmagyaana. Let me also add that I find a quest for happiness a normal human striving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Indian traditions, experience itself is a state of being: anubhava. In my story, so is happiness (or atmasaakshaatkaara). Need one be enlightened in order to speak about enlightenment? Should that be the case, one cannot strive for enlightenment at all and I think that enlightenment (or happiness) is a legitimate goal for human beings. If happiness is not an esoteric state of being but a legitimate goal for all human beings, there are indefinitely many roads to that state of being. The strength of the Indian traditions lies not merely in recognizing this but also in working out many such routes.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is the Bhagavad Gita a revelation?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:22:40 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is the Bhagavad Gita revelation? E.g. 15:15, rendered by one translator as &amp;ldquo;And I am seated in the hearts of all; from Me are memory, knowledge, as well as their loss; I am verily that which has to be known by all the Vedas; I am indeed the author of the Vedanta as well as the knower of the Vedas&amp;rdquo;.If nothing else, the authorship of Vedanta is what is revealed here. But the claim is there both to be the subject and author of revelation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>