<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Petitio Principii on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/petitio-principii/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Petitio Principii on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/petitio-principii/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why the question about the origin of religion is ill-formulated?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-origin-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 23:18:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/the-origin-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Are there accounts about the origin of religion? Yes, there are at least two kinds. One kind tries to localise the origin of religion in human beings and the other in God.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. If religion is what it also says about itself, namely, it is the word of God, what are we trying to answer when we try to answer the issue of the origin of religion? Are we trying to give a scientific answer to the question, why God gave religion to humanity or are we trying to answer the question why humankind believes in the existence of God? If the former, then this question has been answered differently by different religions, i.e., this is the theology of these different religions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Could religion be a neural disorder?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/could-religion-be-a-neural-disorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 22:51:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/could-religion-be-a-neural-disorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Religion lays claim to truth, both about itself and the Cosmos. It is true the way no other account (that we know of) is. However, religion also generates (or brings into being) a configuration of learning. That is, it enables a coordination of different learning processes into a configuration. A culture is such a configuration of learning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Could religion be a neural disorder? I do not see how we could say any such thing unless we already presuppose (at a minimum) what we have to prove, viz., religion is untrue. One of the difficulties involved in disproving the truth of religion has to do with the fact that religion is true in a way none of the human cognitive products are. (Remember that its truth is founded on nothing else except itself.) Of course, we are free to say that all believers have some kind of pathology. (Many accounts of religion have tended to say this as well.) But this is an assumption that will not allow us to understand religion: we will see it either as a human product or as some kind of virus that affects human brain. In both cases, it is an assumption that begs the question.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
