<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Explanatorily Intelligible on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/explanatorily-intelligible/</link><description>Recent content in Explanatorily Intelligible on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 23:17:54 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/explanatorily-intelligible/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Self-reflexivity of Religion</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 23:17:54 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to answer the question of whether or not The Lord of the Rings (LOTR) is a religious story by testing against &amp;lsquo;religion is an explanatorily intelligible account of the Cosmos&amp;rsquo;. Does the Lord of the Rings give an account in which the causal and intentional explanations for the happenings in Middle Earth fall together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the problems in testing a scientific theory and of developing one, I might add, is to ask the right question. The other problem, of course, is to find the right answer. Let us first take a step back and look at the claim.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Creation: Spontaneous or Intentional</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 22:10:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If we want to grasp the nature of the discussions in the Indian traditions, there is much we need to do beforehand: (a) identify the entity they were talking about; (b) identify the specific questions they were answering; (c) identify the generic questions that defined both the outlines of the acceptable answers and the formulation of the specific questions; etc. (The &amp;lsquo;cetera&amp;rsquo; indicates that I do not know how to enumerate all the things we need to grasp.) In the case of the propositions you have formulated, I assume that &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; is Vishnu (or even Krishna) and not, say, Shiva or Brahma because you are talking about the Madhvas. However, to keep the discussion faithful to your formulations, I will use the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; to refer to Vishnu.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Intentional and Causal explanations</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-and-causal-explanations/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:22:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-and-causal-explanations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The first question: could we have EIA of units smaller than the Cosmos?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An explanatorily intelligible account of any object, whatever that object is, is one where causal (say) and intentional explanations fall together. The causal account provides, let us say, an explanation that makes it clear what the causal antecedents of some object (or event, or phenomenon) are. (For the sake of this discussion, let us assume that theories in Natural Sciences provide us with explanations and that they are causal in nature.) The only kind of explanation we know that provides `meaning&amp;rsquo; (or reasons) for objects (or events, or phenomenon) are intentional ones: they postulate an agent; actions, objects and phenomena are seen to embody the intentions (beliefs, hopes, desires, designs, projects, etc.) of the agent. Such an explanation is an intentional explanation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Heathens are blind to religion?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-heathens-are-blind-to-religion/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:03:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-heathens-are-blind-to-religion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Of course, the concept of explanatorily intelligible account is not easy to grasp: if it were, the &amp;lsquo;heathens&amp;rsquo; would not be &lt;em&gt;blind&lt;/em&gt; to the existence of religion. However, that does not mean we cannot grasp it either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am glad you are beginning to see why the story about &amp;lsquo;Jesus as a Yogi&amp;rsquo; (Sankrant&amp;rsquo;s famous interpretation) is wrong; and why discussions on Sulekha drive me sometimes to despair and the believers (remember Gargoyle Minimus?) into utter rage. Why I keep saying that we &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; we understand Christianity (Pradip Gangopadhyay even claims that no Christian has understood the teachings of Christ, except himself), whereas we simply do not know what we are talking about.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Stories and intelligibility</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/stories-and-intelligibility/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 23:56:25 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/stories-and-intelligibility/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;(I) In a Greek story, Persephone spends part of the year in the underworld and part of the year on earth, and winter is caused by her mother Demeter&amp;rsquo;s sorrow at parting, and spring by her mother&amp;rsquo;s joy at reuniting. When taken at face value, this story makes the change of seasons be because of someone&amp;rsquo;s emotions, and hence intelligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two points with respect to this. (a) I do not think that the story itself would say that winter and spring were &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by the emotions of the mother. Instead, it would say: &amp;ldquo;her sorrow became, her joy became…&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;thus her sorrow is, her joy is…&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;that is how seasons came into being&amp;rdquo; or some such formulation. That is because, in my view, this story &lt;em&gt;does not&lt;/em&gt; portray causal or other relations between events. That is why it remains beautiful to this day. (b) Here, you are using &amp;lsquo;intelligibility&amp;rsquo; as &amp;lsquo;understandability&amp;rsquo;. Having or experiencing emotions is not seen as an &lt;em&gt;intentional&lt;/em&gt; state, i.e., not as a propositional attitude. &amp;lsquo;He is sad because his mother died&amp;rsquo; is glossed as &amp;lsquo;he believes that he is sad because his mother died&amp;rsquo;, or as &amp;lsquo;he is sad because he believes that his mother died&amp;rsquo;. (One indicator for testing the role played by the &amp;rsquo;that&amp;rsquo; clause is: the truth value of the entire sentence does not get affected by the truth value of the sentence occurring after the &amp;rsquo;that&amp;rsquo; clause. That is, the &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/"&gt;&amp;rsquo;that&amp;rsquo; clause is not truth-functional&lt;/a&gt; unlike say &amp;lsquo;or&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;and&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;if…then&amp;rsquo; clauses.) It is important to emphasize that the notion of &amp;lsquo;intelligibility&amp;rsquo; requires that it is an expression of an intentional state and emotions are not seen as intentional states.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Intelligibility: Religion, Belief, Meaning</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intelligibility-religion-belief-meaning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 23:44:14 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intelligibility-religion-belief-meaning/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by clarifying what the notion of intelligibility says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to keep in mind is that Religion &lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. transforms, renders, or any such synonym) the Cosmos (used interchangeably with &amp;rsquo;the world&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;the Universe&amp;rsquo;, etc) into an entity that is intelligible. In the process, and by virtue of it, the explanatory account makes &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; intelligible as well. That is, Religion is an explanatory intelligible account of both itself and the Cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Extended reproduction of religion and revitalization of Indian traditions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:21:29 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/horizontal-and-vertical-extended-reproduction-of-religion-and-revitalization-of-indian-traditions/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did Christianity become a &amp;lsquo;universal&amp;rsquo; religion? How did Christians replace the &amp;lsquo;chosen&amp;rsquo; people? What was the logic behind the transformation of the Jewish god into God of the humankind?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the literature on the subject that I have read, the first two questions get a historical (semi-psychological) answer. Traces of this answer can also be found between the lines in &amp;lsquo;The Heathen…&amp;rsquo;. There is a great deal of theological discussion on the third issue but I have not followed them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The dynamic of religion: secularization and proselytization</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 03:05:49 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-dynamic-of-religion-secularization-and-proselytization/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with the idea that religion is some kind of a system (or structure or whatever you feel like using) that maintains itself. That is to say, it is able to reproduce itself, and sustain itself. I call this the `simple reproduction&amp;rsquo; of religion. This dynamic enables not only the reproduction of the community of believers but also the experiential intelligibility that the Cosmos has for them. (Worship, for instance, is one such means for the reproduction of religion.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Bible an explanatorily intelligle account of Cosmos and of itself?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-bible-an-explanatorily-intelligle-account-of-cosmos-and-of-itself/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 23:23:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-bible-an-explanatorily-intelligle-account-of-cosmos-and-of-itself/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When a religion claims that it is the word of God and that the word is unconditionally true; and that, further, the word is about the Cosmos: everything that was, is and shall be. So, when I say that religion is such an entity, namely, it claims that it is the word of God and that it claims to be unconditionally true and that it is about the Cosmos, I am accepting the self description of religion. (However, the hypothesis that religion is an explanatorily intelligible (EI) account formulates it without committing itself to any ontological claims. That is, it takes no stances about what specific religions say or do not say about the existence of entities. The hypothesis does not show how, and in what sense, the Bible, say, is an EI account. It merely says that The Bible has such a status to believers. If you reread the relevant paragraphs of &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo; where I first formulate the hypothesis, you will notice that I formulate it conditionally: &amp;ldquo;If such a being exists, if such an account is forthcoming &amp;hellip; etc then we have an EI account.&amp;rdquo;) If we do not accept the self-description of religion, The Bible becomes a mere book and we cannot study it at all to say anything about Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secularized Christian belief: worldview is a cultural universal</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 20:50:58 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Lets become clear about the nature of my claims about worldviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The word carries multiple meanings. It has partly to do with the multiple meanings of the component words: world&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;. In daily language-use, &amp;lsquo;world&amp;rsquo; is used to pick out (a) a spatial and temporal slice of the cosmos (b) and/or the entire Cosmos itself. The first, the slices, are many: from the &amp;lsquo;social world&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;rsquo;emotional world&amp;rsquo;; from earth (&amp;lsquo;our world&amp;rsquo;) to parts of the same (&amp;lsquo;our part of the world&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;in different parts of the world&amp;rsquo;) and so on. The same consideration applies to &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;: it could refer to perspectives (&amp;lsquo;my view of the issue&amp;rsquo;) and to the totality (&amp;lsquo;we now have a clear view of the situation&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As though this is not enough, the word &amp;lsquo;world view&amp;rsquo; also carries additional multiple meanings: it picks out a totality of beliefs that some individual has; it refers at times exclusively to false beliefs (the Marxist use of the notion of ideology); it is either necessary or strictly superfluous (depending on how one interprets the scope of &amp;lsquo;ideology&amp;rsquo;); it picks out the common denominator among a group of people and the latter itself can refer to a nation, a class, a culture, the species, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Religious tolerance and Ecumenism</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-tolerance-and-ecumenism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 04:31:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/religious-tolerance-and-ecumenism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One has faith in God and, therefore, trusts that His message is also The Truth. That is to say, one should not predicate the attitude of having `faith in&amp;rsquo; to the EI account directly. There is a very important additional reason for being clear about our terminologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the distinction between having no idea that the Cosmos is an EI entity and having an account that makes the Cosmos into such an entity. This distinction marks the difference between the heathen and the believer. In religious terminology, the difference can also be expressed as that which exists between the &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;non-converted&amp;rdquo;. This is one meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;conversion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chapter-wise Questions and Answers to understand “The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, the West and the Dynamic of Religion”</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/chapter-wise-questions-and-answers-to-understand-the-heathen-in-his-blindness-asia-the-west-and-the-dynamic-of-religion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 21:25:09 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/chapter-wise-questions-and-answers-to-understand-the-heathen-in-his-blindness-asia-the-west-and-the-dynamic-of-religion/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Each time I tell someone, whether in a one-to-one discussion or in a conference, &amp;ldquo;there is no religion in India&amp;rdquo;, I get the following answer: &amp;ldquo;Of course, that depends on how you define &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;. I answer as follows: &amp;ldquo;In that case, here is my definition: &amp;lsquo;Religion=what does not exist in India&amp;rsquo;. Will that do? If it is really a question of the definition of a word, why does one need to write such a big book?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>