<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Evolution on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/evolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Evolution on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 00:05:09 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Neurobiological Theory of Religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 00:05:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask whether &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; a neurobiological theory on religion could &amp;ldquo;account&amp;rdquo; for the experience of the believers. The answer depends on what kind of an account you are asking for and what you have in mind when you say &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;. If you mean by &amp;lsquo;account&amp;rsquo;, whether it could predict or even explain, I do not think so. We know that, at the least, we are made up of atoms. Your question, in terms of the kind of challenge it poses (even though the degree of complexity changes), is identical to the question: could a theory in physics, in principle, ever account for our experiences? What does &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; mean here actually? There was a period when one thought, among other things, that it was possible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; to describe mathematics in a purely logical language. That is, many thought that mathematics has a &amp;ldquo;logical structure&amp;rdquo; and that, therefore, one could reconstruct mathematics aided by a suitably powerful logic. (It is called the &amp;lsquo;Hilbert program&amp;rsquo;, named after the originator of this research program.) Then a mathematician called Kurt Gödel proved that, in principle, we cannot even prove the truth of elementary arithmetic on logical grounds: even though we can generate true statements in elementary arithmetic (and know that they are true; they are called &amp;ldquo;Gödel numbers&amp;rdquo;), we cannot prove their truth. Nor can we prove their falsity. They belong to the class of &amp;ldquo;undecidable&amp;rdquo; statements. In other words, what appears obvious to many of us today, namely, arithmetic is &amp;rsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; in nature cannot ever be &amp;ldquo;proved&amp;rdquo;. This is an impossibility theorem that Gödel proved in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s. So, what we think is possible in principle turns out to be impossible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dawkin’s  Delusion or The God Delusion?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:10:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While re-reading certain passages from Richard Dawkins&amp;rsquo; The God Delusion (2006), I was so shocked by his combination of ignorance and arrogance. Forgive me for some Dawkins- bashing:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In a memorable passage, Dawkins discusses the problem of Trinitarianism in Christianity and extends it to other forms of &amp;ldquo;polytheism,&amp;rdquo; such as the cult of the Virgin Mary and the saints in Roman-Catholicism. &amp;ldquo;What impresses me about Catholic mythology,&amp;rdquo; he shares with the reader, &amp;ldquo;is partly its tasteless kitsch but mostly the airy nonchalance with which these people make up the details as they go along. It is just shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo; (Dawkins 2006: 35). As a reader, try to bracket away all presuppositions about religion and reread the sentences. If you succeed in doing so, the impact of Dawkins&amp;rsquo; claim dissolves. So what, if certain details of Roman-Catholicism are human inventions? What is the problem in aspects of religion being &amp;ldquo;shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo;? From a non-Christian, neutral point of view, it is unclear why Dawkins bothers to mention this. However, anyone with a basic understanding of the history of Christianity will note where his claim comes from: Dawkins himself reproduces a piece of theology in this sentence (apparently without knowing it). From its earliest beginnings, Christianity claimed that it was the original and pure revelation of God, first given to Adam. This original revelation had been corrupted by sinful idolaters, seduced by the Devil into the worship of the false god and his minions. This corruption, according to Christian theology, took the form of human additions to the pure divine revelation: rites and myths, fabricated by priests and prelates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the Protestant Reformation, Luther, Calvin and their followers began to accuse the Roman-Catholic Church of the same sin of idolatry. They cried that the pope and his priests had invented a plethora of dogmas and rituals and imposed these on the believer as though they were part of God&amp;rsquo;s revelation and necessary to salvation. In this sense, the worst accusation one could make against Roman- Catholicism was that it consisted of &amp;ldquo;shameless human inventions.&amp;rdquo; The Enlightenment philosophes extended such charges of idolatry to all of Christianity and to all &amp;ldquo;religions&amp;rdquo; of humanity. All of these, including the notion of God itself, were human fabrications, the atheists among them claimed. Ironically, Enlightenment atheism thus presupposed and built on the claims of Christian theology. Without the background belief that there is something intrinsically wrong in religion being a human invention—very much a Christian belief—the impact of such charges simply disappears into thin air.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theology and evolutionary explanations of religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:00:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People like Scott Atran and Sloan Wilson abuse evolutionary biology to produce ad hoc explanations of an explanandum whose truth they presuppose: the universality of religion. Their explanations are no better than those discussed by Balu in chapter 5 of &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness&#34;&gt;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;. Paraphrasing Balu, we may say that they consist of &amp;rsquo;two quarters of theology, a quarter of evolutionary biology and a quarter of illiterate ethnology&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary explanations of religion: an exercise in petitio principii</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 04:49:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is very disappointing to see how these evolutionary theorists of religion lack knowledge of religions other than garden variety Judeo-Christianity (where they seem to have at least some factual knowledge, as in Scott Atran&amp;rsquo;s case, they reproduce standard textbook stories about Hinduism that have been left behind a few decades back).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If they did a serious study, it would perhaps strike them that no one has ever given either theoretical or empirical proof for the claim that religion is a human universal. From the 13th century onwards, European travelers, missionaries, merchants and scholars simply assumed that there would be religion in all societies. With this assumption in the background, they looked for the &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;gods&amp;rsquo; of these societies. In the process, these western minds invented religions everywhere. Later scholars began to create all kinds of definitions of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; in order to accommodate their (cultural) intuition that religion is universal. As though a definition of a word can help us decide on the universality of a phenomenon. After all, we don&amp;rsquo;t use a definition of the word &amp;ldquo;gravitation&amp;rdquo; in order to find out whether gravitation exists on all planets, do we?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
