<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Outlook on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/outlook/</link><description>Recent content in Outlook on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 23:19:39 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/outlook/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Indian Jews</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-indian-jews/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 23:19:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-indian-jews/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;social science debate in India has been hijacked by the struggle between secularism and&lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; for decades now. usually the &lt;em&gt;Sangh Parivar&lt;/em&gt; is blamed for this turn of events. However, it could well be argued that the &lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; ideologues simply adopted the stance of the secularists.  Perhaps the best illustration is the case of anti-Brahminism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be against &amp;ldquo;Brahminism&amp;rdquo; is part and parcel of the political correctness of progressive scholars in twenty-first-century India, much like being against Muslims is part of the message of their &lt;em&gt;Hindutva&lt;/em&gt; colleagues. This indicates that something is very wrong with the Indian academic debate. Promotion of animosity towards a religious tradition or its followers is not acceptable today, but it becomes truly perverse when the intelligentsia endorses it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How free are we?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-free-are-we/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 23:15:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-free-are-we/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This has been a tumultuous decade for the academic study of India. In his recent &lt;em&gt;Offence: The Hindu Case&lt;/em&gt; (2009), Salil Tripathi provides a timely overview of the growing censorship and harassment that scholars working on India have faced. Not a pretty sight to behold: people have felt the need to ban books and terrorize authors, hassle teachers and disrupt classes, toss eggs at some and blacken others’ faces. Academics now run the risk of smear campaigns, court cases and physical intimidation; all because certain groups feel offended by what they write about the Indian past or the Hindu traditions. The facts are difficult to miss. Hence, the threat that Hindu nationalism poses to academic freedom has caused commotion around the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>What can India offer?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 23:26:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-can-india-offer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, India has become a global player of significant political and economical impact. Europe and India are facing each other as equal partners in pursuit of greater economic and political co-operation. This confronts both India and Europe with a challenge. The intelligentsia, the business world, politicians, educators and others, will have to answer the following question: What can India offer to the world of today and tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will not tackle this problem directly but instead take up one of its sub-questions: to whom is this problem important and why? I believe it is important to both Indians and Europeans but for different reasons. In this article, I will spell out and reflect upon some of these reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Current state of Scholarship about India: outlook articles</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/current-state-of-scholarship-about-india-outlook-articles/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2014 09:20:12 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/current-state-of-scholarship-about-india-outlook-articles/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140529022325/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289559"&gt;Jakob de Roover&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Untangling the knot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140331032610/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289711"&gt;Sufiya Pathan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;No Alternative&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140406000302/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?289733"&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Disturbing Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100406044846/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?264014"&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;How Free are We?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110204003153/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?237702"&gt;Jakob&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Indian Jews&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110605054740/http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?235020"&gt;Balagangadhara&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;What can India offer?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>