<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sarah on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/sarah/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sarah on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 18:58:06 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/sarah/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ancient Roman Culture and Early Christianity: A Pagan Perspective from India</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/ancient-roman-culture-and-early-christianity-a-pagan-perspective-from-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 18:58:06 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/ancient-roman-culture-and-early-christianity-a-pagan-perspective-from-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/5497450/A_Pagan_Perspective_on_Early_Christianity_and_Ancient_Rome&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Original.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  [ Appeared in  &lt;a href=&#34;https://biblio.ugent.be/publication/4259026&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Christendom en filosofie : opstellen over wijsbegeerte, wereldbeeld en wetenschappen van het antieke christendom over Nietzsche tot fundamentalisme vandaag&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; p.51-82]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this article, we would like to reflect upon the contemporary relevance of the encounter between ancient Roman culture and Early Christianity. There is a reason for choosing this theme. Today, a few heathen cultures (for instance, those of India and China) have become important once again to the history of mankind. Irrespective of what else is said about the cultures of India or China, in the course of this millennium, these two are going to have a significant impact in the world. In the renewed meeting between India and China on the one hand and the western culture on the other, two issues are going to become central once again: (a) how they look at Christianity and Christian cultures and (b) how the western culture has learnt to look at them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercultural exchange of categories</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 19:42:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is wrong with the intercultural exchange of categories? Throughout one gets the impression that there is something “fundamentally wrong” with categories shifting in meaning over time or with the introduction of categories from one culture into another culture. But what is important about these shifts in meaning? What exactly is the problem in introducing the category of religion into India or among Native Americans? The category “yuppie” did not exist in the Middle Ages, while “orange” came through Arabic from Sanskrit, and “girl” used to refer to a young person of either sex. When we analyse the genetics of early modern populations, we are also introducing categories that they did not possess. Or take the word “silly,” which in Old English used to mean blessed. So what? An historical analysis of discourse and categories is significant not to identify shifts in meaning per se. Shifts in meaning become significant only against the background of a theory on the historical development of the western culture and its understanding of other cultures. Such a theory is needed to clarify as to why a shift in the meaning of “religion” or “the secular” is of crucial importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Question of Conversion in India</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:14:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-question-of-conversion-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian debate on religious conversion has been an ongoing one for a few centuries now. However, the mutual understanding between the advocates and the adversaries of conversion has not advanced much. This paper suggests that this is due to the fact that Hindus and Christians refer to two different objects when they discuss &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. The traits which the Christians ascribe to religion account for the premium they put on the right to convert, while the traits of the Hindu view of religion explain the opposition to conversion. As the two parties attribute mutually exclusive properties to religion, they encounter difficulties while seeking to make sense of each other&amp;rsquo;s claims about religion and conversion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
