<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Transcript on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/transcript/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Transcript on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 09:21:28 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/transcript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How to understand corruption?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 09:21:28 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-understand-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us take the word ‘duty’ for the moment. Conflict in duties does not give you a moral dilemma. For a moral dilemma to occur two necessary conditions must exist: the prescribed set of duties must be logically consistent by virtue of which one is obliged to perform them all.  A dilemma pertains to a situation where one has an obligation to do A and an obligation to do B; but can in fact do only one. It is the perfect consistency of the system of duty that gives rise to the dilemma: a choice between A and B, between a banana and an orange is not a dilemma. It becomes a dilemma when you want both and can have only one. So, a moral dilemma cannot possibly describe a conflict of duties if one uses the word ‘duty’ here.  A conflict of &lt;em&gt;dharmas&lt;/em&gt; is not a dilemma at all.&#xA;What I mean by decolonizing social Sciences is very simple thing. There are many domains today: sociology, political science, psychology, and anthropology that call themselves social sciences as distinct from humanities. So, I am not talking about decolonizing science in the specific sense given by Mohini Mullick. I do not consider the theories in these domains which call themselves social sciences to be science at all. Today, I see all of them without exception as ideologies. I call my project ‘Comparative Science of Culture’ because existing theories are not social sciences.&#xA;For instance: political corruption refers to the act of an individual public servant who is part of a state or a government and who acts against the public interest of the people or the interest of the state. Because state has an interest which coincides with the interest of the society, then any action that supports an individual’s interest is morally wrong. This is the meaning of political corruption.&#xA;I am very conservative. I want a scientific hypothesis in the sense that it solves a problem, has an explanatory potential and there is some way to test it. In this sense, political theory is completely bankrupt. I proffer two hypotheses which at least minimally do what you expect a hypothesis to do.&#xA;The first is purely historical in nature. You raised a question about the moral evaluations which comes from a completely Western ethics and is not Indian at all. We in India had our own forms of social organization. We had certain indigenous ways of governing, of organizing production. But with colonization came industrialization, bringing with it management institutions from the West; structures were imposed on native Indian industries, on native structures, which today are taught in MBA courses all over India. The result is institutional distortion, so that you come across extraordinary things that baffle management theorists.&#xA;More concretely: how were questions asked about tradition? Can we use the resources of our ancient Indian literature to tackle and explain this problem? I find the Indian tradition powerful because it can help generate scientific hypotheses beyond the reach of Western social scientists. That’s why I am against the latter, not because they are Western. I am not against everything Western: Physics, Chemistry, Mathematics, Biology come from the Western tradition.&#xA;(pp 206-8 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Descriptions about the world vs. Manuals for action</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 19:59:21 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is broadly accepted that one of the most important functions of language is to describe the world outside it. Could it be the case that when it comes to the Indian systems, they all (whether it is Advaita vedanta, Yoga vasistha, visista advaita) are teaching one to act, to live in a particular way? In other words, they are not saying what there is in the world but are manuals in a manner of speaking. Of course, in order to understand a manual you need reference points in the world. So when they say for example that when the Buddha argued for &lt;em&gt;anatman&lt;/em&gt; or Sankara spoke about &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt;, one way of interpreting, which is what most Indian philosophers have done, is that they attribute doctrines to them and say this is a description of the world. But actually they were not describing the world. Buddha does not say atman exists or does not exist or whatever. Sankara is not saying &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt; exists because that would be a description of our world. So what a guru does in our tradition, which is what the upadesa is, is to teach one to not look at these as descriptions of the world; he teaches one how to transform them into a way of living. So Yoga vasistha does not tell you what the world is like. That can be said in one sentence. Why then does this man have to write so much? It is to help you go on in a certain way and then say that this is not a description of the world.&#xA;(p. 308 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Truth, belief, intentionality, eudaimonia, ought</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:15:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to respond to three of your points Claus. First you are not talking only about the Greeks and the Romans because all the problems arising with respect to the phenomena of non-Western societies and culture are/were equally the problems in the frameworks of different varieties of culture. You not only talk about the Greeks and the Romans, you gave examples about the French and the English as well.&#xA;The second point is: you talk about the fact that people face the same problem in Europe of today when they talk about the Greeks and the Romans. You are absolutely right. But that confirms my point, namely, that the Greeks and the Romans had no religion. They were Pagan cultures and this is exactly the problem with India. The Christian culture doesn’t understand Greek — the whole of Heidegger’s philosophy is an example of that. He says we cannot think Greek. And his whole attempt to speak about what thinking is, what truth is, etc. — is an attempt to rescue the Greek language from what he called the Christianization of Latin. I am aware that contemporary European languages and modern Europe do have problems with the Greeks and Romans. But just because of the fact that Ancient Greece and Rome are located in the Western hemisphere does not make them part of Western culture. In an earlier publication, I showed that neither Greece nor Rome were cradles of Western civilization. Western Civilization is Christian Civilization, although you might not agree with that. Greece and Rome do not belong to it. That is why we Indians can understand them. Let me give you a small example — One of the most fundamental notions of Aristotle is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, which gets translated with great difficulty as ‘well-being’, ‘feeling good’, ‘happiness’ and so on. It is a very difficult word to translate. This is not merely a translation problem because I have had discussions with Greek scholars. Aristotle asks: what is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;? It is very difficult to achieve of course but he says once you have it you cannot lose it. I told a Greek Specialist once ‘you know nothing about Greek language’, He responded: ‘how dare you say that’! So, I said: ‘here is a simple thing, forget the translation of &lt;em&gt;eudaimoni&lt;/em&gt;a, give me one example of a human  property which once you possess, you do not lose.’ I said: ‘I do not have to understand Greek to understand what &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; means.’ And of course to this day, no Greek scholar could help me in giving one example of one human property which if once you possess you do not lose&amp;ndash;this is a fundamental property of &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;. For the Indians here is my answer. &lt;em&gt;Eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;aananda.&lt;/em&gt; Once you have &lt;em&gt;aananda&lt;/em&gt; you do not lose it. It is equivalent in some conditions to &lt;em&gt;brahma-gyaana.&lt;/em&gt; And that is happiness indeed, beyond &lt;em&gt;sukha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;duhkha&lt;/em&gt;. So when Aristotle is talking about &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; I understand him and I read him carefully. Of course, there is no translation equivalent of eudaimonia in any of the European languages but that is because they have no access to that world, that conceptual framework like we Indians have. So indeed, I understand you have a problem with Greece and Rome: we understand them much better.&#xA;Two other points &amp;ndash; one on Galileo. I am not conflating the community of Christians with a community of non-Christians because one of the claims I have substantiated to which in the last fifteen years I have found no counter argument, is the following: My claim is that free thinkers and atheists, even the Communists of Europe, are actually disguised theists. That is to say that Christianity has secularized itself in political theory, in social theory, in rational choice theory; a number of theories. I can show you how assumptions from the Bible have taken secular forms. So by saying for instance, ‘look I don’t have a religious background’, it makes no difference. I know people, who do not have a religious background for generations, are atheists but they continue to have the same excuse for speaking as Christians do. For example, your ethics will be absolutely no different from Christian ethics because there is no such thing as non-Christian secular ethics present today. ‘You ought not to kill’. Don’t tell me that is an example of secular ethics. Even the notion of ‘ought not’, the normative notion itself, does not come from English: it comes from Christianity, from the Bible.&#xA;Aristotle, for example, does not have an ‘ought’. Indian languages do not have a ‘moral ought’ nor do the Chinese in their language in which Confucius wrote. These are not linguistic issues, Claus, these are problems of conceptual apparatuses that are culturally developed. So, it is in that sense that I speak about Galileo and say he made sense to the Europeans. They used his findings to investigate nature because they believed fundamentally that nature has a structure and pattern and a law which has to be discovered by human investigation. They would say that without such a structure the universe should be chaos. The whole of 2,000 years of European culture believes that, and that was Galileo’s idea as well. It is a background belief, of course, but it is a background belief of that culture and we are talking about difference between cultures. Translation is always a translation between people who use sentences, who use natural languages. So, I am shifting the level of the problem.&#xA;Last point, there is something to be said for your claim regarding the notion of belief&amp;ndash;that you can have a concept, but do not have a word&amp;ndash;that is absolutely true. That is our daily experience. I feel like saying something but I don’t know how to say it. So, you can have some sense of a concept but defined psychologically not linguistically or so cognitively. I do not know how to put it in a natural sentence. Right. But you are making out of it logical and philosophical points.&#xA;Let me put it very sharply. The notion of having a belief and the belief is always about something; this is a specific conception of man, of human beings&amp;ndash;there is philosophical anthropology which attributes some notion of intention to human beings. One of the extraordinary things about the Indian tradition is the absence of this notion of intentionality:  &lt;em&gt;agyana&lt;/em&gt;. They call it &lt;em&gt;maaya&lt;/em&gt; and many different things. So the nature of human being in the Indian tradition is that we are non-intentional creatures, which is completely incomprehensible within the framework of Christian culture. So, entertaining having a belief is not a linguistic, psychological, epistemological fact which is applicable to all human beings but is a specific assumption about the nature of human beings that comes from the Bible. So when saying that Indians have beliefs, you are not making use of any understanding of language – you are making use of a religious concept/understanding of man and saying that is what Indians have. Of course, you can say that; people have been saying that for 500 years. That is not the issue.&#xA;The issue is: is this how Indians understand themselves? In fact, if you look at the languages you find there is greater affinity when you talk of using work-words. They do not say ‘I got angry’ but ‘anger came upon me’ &amp;ndash; this is a very typical old classical Greek way of talking. ‘Why did you say that?’ ‘I do not know, my tongue moved that way’. I am literally translating local Indian languages into English&amp;ndash;this is the way we talk. In fact, even the subject notion, is not simply a linguistic subject or verb subject in action, the fundamental ontological notion of subject itself is missing in India as also the notion of agency.&#xA;Take the problem about truth: the notion of truth for applying to sentences, to propositions by some other philosophers is a very philosophical disease. If you look at the middle-ages, take Aquinas for example, he had two notions of truth: &lt;em&gt;adeequatio re&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;. One is which is adequate to the object; the other which is adequate to thoughts. Hegel used the same notion. Tarski also says there are multiple notions of truth. That notion of truth — &lt;em&gt;adaquatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt; as it prevailed for 1,900 years in Western culture referred to the fact that objects are adequate to how God conceives them. That is &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;adequate not to human intellects, to God’s intellect. &lt;em&gt;Adequatio re&lt;/em&gt; had to do with how one related the word to both these notions and emerged, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; from any understanding of language, truth, philosophy, or logic, it arose from commenting on theologies and commenting the Bible.  (pp 162-166 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Narratives vs Theories</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:34:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narratives-vs-theories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The question requires deeper handling so you will forgive me for the brevity of my response but you will get some idea of where I stand.&#xA;Regarding the first question as to whether we reject social science itself, I am aware that many people have made this suggestion. I am not so much hung up on the word &amp;lsquo;social science&amp;rsquo; but I do believe that we need to systematically reflect on our experiences in the world. A systematic reflection on experiences in the form of a theory is what we can conveniently call social science. We need theories about the world to understand the World. Systematic thinking means use of certain criteria to decide which theories are good or not, etc. and which to choose. The best thing would be to appeal to the history of the natural sciences over say four hundred years to see how they have done it, what kind of criteria they used. Thus, I belong to the group which advocates systematic reflection on experience, and in that sense, I belong to the group which says we need social science.&#xA;Your second question was about Indians having different ways of understanding experience: you spoke of narratives and the autobiography of Tulsi Ram. This raises the question of what form these reflections are going to take. To give a crude example: are they going to be mathematized? Will they take the form of scientific laws or of narratives? That is a very interesting question. But all narratives are not social science: in that case every novelist would have a scientific theory. If a text is an autobiography, it is not social science.&#xA;pp 103-4 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A priori assumptions</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 14:13:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/a-priori-assumptions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am going to ask for a clarification on a question which I find very troubling. Let me first read how you have formulated the problem from the text: Sanskrit scholars need modem social scientists. What disturbs me in anthropological fieldwork is that Sanskrit literature is made to play the role of native informer to social scientists, with the anthropologists asking themselves as they might with Maori culture: is there something valuable which has been lost?&#xA;Claus Oetke also makes the same point. Even if you say that the dialogue between the primitive and the anthropologist is sophisticated, native informers are not merely informants. This idea, this interaction pattern which has existed for the last forty years has a double bias&amp;ndash;that of the anthropologist and that of the native informant. They have very powerful dialogues but anthropologists fundamentally take a priori positions, assuming that Sanskritists are the only ones who hold the key: they do not really believe that non-Sanskritists could possibly have anything to contribute.&#xA;But it would be absurd to dismiss Indian culture a priori without an investigation into India&amp;rsquo;s intellectual contributions without entertaining the possibility that Indian culture and tradition might today in a very significant sense be a challenge to the Western traditions which form our intellectual background. Your question shuts it out because it comes from Sanskrit. In your story of the fieldwork model, all Indian parameters answer the sophisticated social scientists model. I am surprised because you have another strand which goes in the opposite direction. But the fundamental framework you are using suggests maximally that we might learn something like Sanskrit aesthetics, rasa theory, etc. or even something like curry. This kind of trivialization has resulted from colonialism: it has been and is, very suppressive.&#xA;pp 42-43 of &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
