<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Language on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/language/</link><description>Recent content in Language on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 05:52:32 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Usefulness of Dictionaries</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/usefulness-of-dictionaries/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 05:52:32 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/usefulness-of-dictionaries/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Opening a dictionary to find out the meaning of an English word might indeed be an elementary student&amp;rsquo;s choice, but, if used as a methodology for settling scientific and philosophical discussions, I am afraid, it is a rather poor choice. Imagine a physicist living around the turn of the last century doing something similar when Einstein formulated his special theory of relativity. &amp;ldquo;Oh! I say,&amp;rdquo; we can imagine this physicist saying, &amp;ldquo;The New Collegiate defines &amp;lsquo;mass&amp;rsquo; as an invariable property of an object, and this chap from the Patent Office calls it a variable!&amp;rdquo; I suppose one should be grateful to Einstein that he relied less on Webster to solve scientific problems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is the Bhagavad Gita a revelation?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:22:40 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-the-bhagavad-gita-revelation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is the Bhagavad Gita revelation? E.g. 15:15, rendered by one translator as &amp;ldquo;And I am seated in the hearts of all; from Me are memory, knowledge, as well as their loss; I am verily that which has to be known by all the Vedas; I am indeed the author of the Vedanta as well as the knower of the Vedas&amp;rdquo;.If nothing else, the authorship of Vedanta is what is revealed here. But the claim is there both to be the subject and author of revelation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>