<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Supererogation on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/supererogation/</link><description>Recent content in Supererogation on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 16:56:05 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/supererogation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Evolution of 'Supererogation'</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolution-of-supererogation/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 16:56:05 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolution-of-supererogation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It is advisable to get into a discussion about this question only after one knows what ‘supererogation’ means and how it has been discussed for centuries.  In the Greek ethics (especially as Aristotle formulated it), the notion plays a very crucial role without it being related to a normative sense of duty. With the Catholics, especially as Aquinas gave expression to it, a normative notion of duty cohabits the moral universe together with supererogation. To the Protestants, it makes sense to speak only of duty and not of supererogation because the latter does not simply exist. Without understanding the issues involved in these controversies, to make a bald assertion about supererogation (while appealing to a Protestant commonsense idea of duty without even realizing its Protestant origin) is to “…rush in, where Angels fear to tread”.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ideology of Crime</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ideology-of-crime/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:16:11 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ideology-of-crime/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice is that I use the word &amp;ldquo;ideology&amp;rdquo; in a technical sense, which is both counter-intuitive and, for the time being, idiosyncratic. It is the first, namely counter-intuitive, because, as I use it, my use of the word does not refer to any theory, or to sets of beliefs, or to what one believes in. Normally, as we use the word in English, &amp;lsquo;ideology&amp;rsquo; has multiple meanings: a false consciousness; accepting a theory known to be false; presenting the interests of a small strata of people as the universal interests of all; subscribing to premises that are either unjustified or not-examined; and so on. My use has no such connotation. It is the second, namely idiosyncratic, because I have not yet developed a hypothesis about ideology that can explain and justify my use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Saint, The Criminal and The Terrorist—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:10:20 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the phenomenon of terrorism has begun to occupy the media, politics, and the lives of people in different parts of the world. The more the attention, however, the less the clarity: what kind of a phenomenon is terrorism? What generates it, what sustains it, and what allows it to expand on an ever-increasing scale?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of clarity has to do with the fact that our ideas about terrorism appear as an incoherent set. First, terrorism horrifies most of us; the acts of terrorists are seen as monstrous in scope and size. But the number of deaths or the human suffering, even if we look at an event as momentous as 9/11, is dwarfed by what traffic accidents and smoking do in any given year.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ought one to be generous?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-one-to-be-generous/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:46:38 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ought-one-to-be-generous/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There is ethics in India, but it is not normative ethics. It is a non-normative ethics. To get you going, consider acts like &amp;lsquo;generosity&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;kindness&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;bravery&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;friendliness&amp;rsquo; and such like. Often called &amp;lsquo;virtues&amp;rsquo;, these actions do not come under the scope of normative ethics. You cannot say: &amp;ldquo;one ought to be generous&amp;rdquo;, because generosity implies doing &amp;lsquo;more than&amp;rsquo; what is expected in the act of giving. Such notions are also called &amp;lsquo;supererogatory&amp;rsquo; in the literature, i.e. they are &amp;lsquo;over and beyond the call of duty&amp;rsquo;. This is one way to start coming to grips with the idea of non-normative ethics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>