<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Rationality on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/rationality/</link><description>Recent content in Rationality on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 13:28:33 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/rationality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Who needs a world view?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 13:28:33 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;. In this talk, I would like to focus on the two attitudes that I have towards your project. It is not that I have ambiguous feelings; no, I have two distinct feelings. On the one hand, I am convinced that you will not reach your goal because such a goal is unreachable. Not only that. Your goal is undesirable and best abandoned. On the other hand, if you strive with integrity, clarity and passion to reach your goal, in the process, you will achieve results that are desirable, necessary and important. So, I would like to support and encourage your project. On the one hand, I believe that I can develop a few impossibility arguments that will show why you best abandon your project; on the other hand, I have given no thought to developing such a set of arguments because I want you to work further towards your goal so that you produce the results that we, as humankind, need. This might suggest that I am ambiguous toward your project, but, as I said, I am not. To explain thus attitude better, let me use an illustration from the history of philosophy (albeit in a slightly caricatured form),&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Questioning the axioms</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are three ideas in the West about Law that are taken as axioms. The first: all societies are founded on Law; if they are not, they ought to be. The second is that Law teaches and educates a people. Third is their corollary: only thus do a people become a Nation. As far as I know, none has shown their empirical truth or proved that they are logically necessary. But their truth-value is undisputed. When they ruled India, the British followed these axioms: they tried to educate us through Law, interfered in our festivals and social practices and the State tried to educate a barbaric people by enacting  ‘just’ laws. Romulus gave Law and made a group into a people; Moses gave Law and made a people into a Nation; Mohammed gave Law and transformed multiple nations into a caliphate; Manu acquires the exalted status of a Law-giver for the ‘Hindus’. These ideas are not dated, apparently. Today, they enjoy the same privilege they had during the colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Superstition and rationality</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/superstition-and-rationality/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2011 18:40:29 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/superstition-and-rationality/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the question: &amp;ldquo;why superstition?&amp;rdquo; Our problem lies in circumscribing this notion itself: is it something we should use to characterize beliefs, or attitudes, or theories or actions or all of them? Our linguistic usage allows it mostly of &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; and to the act of believing: to believe that walking under the ladder brings bad; to believe that vampires exist and walk as ordinary humans in the night; to believe in the fairy who watches over you, etc. are all instances of superstition. It also allows us to use it in connection to the truth status of theories like, for instance, the claim that it is superstitious to believe in astrology. However, accepting this usage is not enough: what makes a belief a superstitious belief or an act of believing a superstitious act? It is here that many, many problems come to the fore. One easy way out is to use science and scientific theories as the contrast set: any belief that is not countenanced by the scientific theories of today is a superstitious belief. Of course, this is too broad: on this account, every belief that displaces the current scientific beliefs (i.e., the new scientific theories) becomes superstitious. If you try and circumvent this problem by speaking about &amp;lsquo;scientific theories&amp;rsquo; in the abstract (i.e., do not circumscribe them in time), the danger is that every belief (almost) escapes the net. Just because scientific theories of today do not recognize the existence of ghosts, it does not follow, one could argue, that the sciences of tomorrow cannot recognize the role that mediums play in talking to the spirits of the long departed. You can try and say that all beliefs disproved by science should belong to the set of superstitious beliefs: however, similar problems occur. On top of it, you have the difficulty of saying why one should not have superstitious beliefs. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Do practices need rational justifications?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-practices-need-a-rational-justification/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 22:57:58 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-practices-need-a-rational-justification/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If we understand the word &amp;rsquo;tradition&amp;rsquo; to mean &amp;lsquo;a set of practices&amp;rsquo;, then the question is this: why continue a set of practices? When someone &amp;lsquo;justifies&amp;rsquo; (I will soon explain why I use scare quotes for this) this by referring to the existence of a set of practices, what exactly is the person doing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way of looking at it is to say that the person &amp;lsquo;justifies&amp;rsquo; his actions and understand justification to mean providing a logically derived conclusion from a set of premises. The validity of the reasoning would constitute the justification in this context. Quite obviously, because we are speaking of logical justification, we are inclined to formulate the premises, test the derivation and look at the truth value of the conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rationality and Rhetoric</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/rationality-and-rhetoric/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:24:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/rationality-and-rhetoric/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in the nature of a rhetorical text that the author uses linguistic &amp;rsquo;tropes&amp;rsquo; (metaphors, similes, analogies, imagery, etc) to persuade a reader about the reasonableness of a specific standpoint. It does not build arguments that systematically lead to a stand point but instead tries to convince the readers (or listeners) by using the abilities built into natural languages. Such texts do not easily lend themselves to a discussion regarding the steps taken in developing a stand point, unlike, say, a mathematical proof or a philosophical argument. Of course, I do not find such texts &amp;lsquo;irrational&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>