<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Morality on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/morality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Morality on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:10:20 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/morality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Saint, The Criminal and The Terrorist—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2011 19:10:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/the-saint-the-criminal-and-the-terrorist-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, the phenomenon of terrorism has begun to occupy the media, politics, and the lives of people in different parts of the world. The more the attention, however, the less the clarity: what kind of a phenomenon is terrorism? What generates it, what sustains it, and what allows it to expand on an ever-increasing scale?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This lack of clarity has to do with the fact that our ideas about terrorism appear as an incoherent set. First, terrorism horrifies most of us; the acts of terrorists are seen as monstrous in scope and size. But the number of deaths or the human suffering, even if we look at an event as momentous as 9/11, is dwarfed by what traffic accidents and smoking do in any given year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Anthropology and Moral Domains. An Essay on Selfless Morality and the Moral Self—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 21:48:10 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Disquieting Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;Arthur Danto, the well-known American philosopher, prefaced a book he wrote in the 70’s on oriental thought and moral philosophy titled &lt;em&gt;Mysticism and Morality&lt;/em&gt; with the following words:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The factual beliefs (that the civilizations of the East) take for granted are &amp;hellip;too alien to our (the West’s) representations of the World to be grafted on to it, and &lt;em&gt;in consequence their moral systems are unavailable to us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
