<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Real on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/real/</link><description>Recent content in Real on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 21:27:14 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/real/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Brahman: Brihadaranyaka Upanishad 1.iv.10</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brahman-brihadaranyaka-upanishad-1-iv-10/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 21:27:14 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brahman-brihadaranyaka-upanishad-1-iv-10/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Two caveats. One: the commentary is very, very short. To write down all the things I want to say about this citation requires a long paper and not a brief mail. Two: I have not checked either the citation or the reference (Brihadaranyaka upanishad - I.iv.10). I assume that both are accurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This (Self) was indeed Brahman in the beginning. It knew itself only as &amp;ldquo;I am Brahman.&amp;rdquo; Therefore it became all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Blind men and an Elephant: Historicity of Rama</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/blind-men-and-an-elephant-historicity-of-rama/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 20:12:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/blind-men-and-an-elephant-historicity-of-rama/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin with the following dialogue between a Swiss-German and a young Balinese (from Bichsel, Peter, &lt;em&gt;Der Leser, Das Erzählen: Frankfurter Poetik-Vorlesungen&lt;/em&gt;, 1982, Darmstadt und Neuwied: Hermann Luchterhand Verlag. Pp. 13-14, my translation and italics):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I discovered, or when it was explained to me, that Hinduism is a pedagogical religion, namely, that in so far as the best “good deed” of a Hindu consisted of explaining something or the other, I lost my inhibitions and began with questions&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Brahman and Atman</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brahman-and-atman/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 13:49:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/brahman-and-atman/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question: “Certainly that Brahman == self-awareness == Atman is also a matter of direct experience, not of intellectual reasoning?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first begin with reason and then drift towards experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose, as an expansion of the sentence that ‘Atman is Brahman’, it is said: “Atman and Brahman are identical to each other”. What kind of sense does it make and how do we explain that sense? Let us note that this sentence makes linguistic sense. Therefore, the question is, how do you parse this sentence to bring out that sense?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Atman, Witness, and Experience</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/atman-and-experience/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 10:56:38 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/atman-and-experience/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some Swamiji claims: “One cannot experience the Atman[, the Atman] is the witness, it is what experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is a very rough and approximate formulation. This statement is both wrong and right in different ways. (a) In the very early days, when I began to develop my meditation exercise, I ‘sensed’ the vague presence of an observer (somewhere present in the background of my experiential world). Or, you could say, I vaguely sensed that I was being ‘seen’ or that my meditative performance was being performed for an ‘outside’ observer. Perhaps, it would also be accurate to say that I sensed its vague presence outside my meditative world, but touching upon its edges. Later, when I was trying to help other people meditate, I discovered that some sensed this presence too and yet others had to ‘let go’ in order to sense this presence. I am guessing that this is the idea of Atman as a ‘witness’. Some were fearful and afraid of this presence as well. If you say that to sense the vague presence is to experience that presence, the Swamiji is wrong. If you see this vague sensing of a presence (or sensing the vague presence of something) as not experiencing, the Swamij would be right. (b) Does the Atman experience? If you keep the word ‘experience’ sufficiently broad (or nebulous), yes, that is true. Self-awareness is obviously ‘aware’ (working purely at a linguistic level); self-consciousness is obviously ‘conscious’ (I say this in my note as well to understand the access). In this sense, yes, the Swamiji is right. However, the Swamiji is wrong if we claim, which we have to, that experience (as we know it today) requires some kind of bodily constraint (i.e. the presence of an apparatus to experience). We have to say here that self-consciousness is not tantamount to ‘experience’. Then the question opens up: if self-consciousness is not ‘experience’ what else is it? I have no answer except to say that it is ‘self-consciousness’, period. It is also further true, on both accounts, that &lt;strong&gt;sentience does not experience self-consciousness but merely accesses it.&lt;/strong&gt; In that case, the next problem: what does this access generate? Some or another kind of experience or not? If we cannot provide some kind of a satisfactory answer, the word ‘access’ is an occult word and does no work. (These are not the only set of problems, but it does indicate why understanding ‘enlightenment’ is far, far more difficult than achieving that state.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Shakti vs. Natural Sciences</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shakti-vs-natural-sciences/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 16:28:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shakti-vs-natural-sciences/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You say that you experienced Shakti as an emanation of a force that is overpowering and palpable; you also say that you felt the ‘presence’ of Shakti strongly. These two sentences make one think that you felt the presence of the force. In that case, there are only two routes open to us: (a) either reject that we have knowledge of the world which forbids linguistic utterances from infusing material objects with ‘life’ forces that can have causal impact in the world; (b) or ‘downgrade’ science as knowledge of the world by allowing ‘spiritual’ (or supra-mundane) worlds to causally interact with the ‘physical’ world. Your own process of thinking about this experience is rigidly hemmed in by these alternatives. Neither, I think, is what you are seeking. If you are, you cannot and will not find what you seek, even if it is to merely figure out your experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>'Grotesque' nature of Murtis</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/grotesque-nature-of-murtis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 15:56:52 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/grotesque-nature-of-murtis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the fact that the Indian ‘gods’ are portrayed in at least two ways. First, there is their portrayal with four arms (say) and there is their portrayal in completely human forms. Krishna has four arms (with Shankha, Chakra, Gada and Padma or one hand with a blessing palm or downward indicating a mudra of some kind) and he also has a fully human form. The balakrishna’s I have seen give him only two arms. So do many images of Krishna: he has only two arms. However, apart from other symbols (flute, peacock feather, etc), his colour is almost invariant. Ganesha is even more interesting: there are balaganesha’s crawling with two arms and with four arms. There are images of a four-armed Ganesha sitting on the lap of a two-armed Shiva (with and without his third eye but holding a trishula). In any case, he has the elephant head. Most Durga’s have multiple arms, a few frightening heads but there are also those with human form and pretty faces. Same applies to Parvati, Laxmi and Saraswati. Except, of course, they invariably have pretty faces. They too have characteristic traits: seated on Padma, carrying a Veena, or next to Shiva or Ganesha or sitting on top of a mountain surrounded by snowy peaks. There are also others where she is on a peetha or is very well dressed and adorned with ornaments. In short, some or another trait is mostly present that identifies which ‘goddess’ or ‘god’ s/he is. The rest, obviously, is left free. Of course, there are also images that can only be identified, if so identified by local stories, the pujari’s at the temples and so on. If these are our ‘popular gods’, the less-known (say the village ‘goddesses’) are even more problematic. Many village ‘goddesses’ look similarly vague and are almost but not quite amorphous.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Examples of Real vs. Existence</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/examples-of-real-vs-existence/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 23:30:40 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/examples-of-real-vs-existence/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Two points should be kept in mind before using these examples: (a) the examples illustrate that the distinctions are not unknown to an English language-user (b) the distinction does not require denying the knowledge that we have about the world. These merely indicate that the distinction between ‘real’ and ‘existence’ might be worth a serious investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A possible set of examples&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not Real but exists&lt;/strong&gt; : the Earth, Planets, Stars, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Para vs. Apara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/para-vs-apara/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 23:22:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/para-vs-apara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: I have some problems understanding &lt;em&gt;apara, para, existence, and presence&lt;/em&gt;. Apara exists, but is not present; para is present but does not exist. Are you saying that what is present does not exist, what exists is not present? If so, how can you reconcile with our common sense notion that what exists is present?  Even though presence doesn’t imply existence, we can’t say that existence imply non-presence. So, this is an issue of definitional equivalence: para = presence; apara = existence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Accessing 'Para' (Real)</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/accessing-para-real/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 23:04:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/accessing-para-real/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It would be a good thing to narrow-in on the ‘spookiness’ of the accessing &amp;lsquo;Real&amp;rsquo;. However, because there is a very great danger that ‘access’ can be conceptualised as an access to a ‘supra-mundane’ or a ‘spiritual’ world, or to a world that is not accessible to ‘sciences’  but can be ‘spiritually’ accessed, etc. a few extra words are required. Therefore, an attempt that might reduce one possible kind of spookiness that you might be referring to.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Tattvadarshi, Gyaani, and Bullshitter</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 22:07:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let us agree on the proposed division into two categories: “1) That which exists or could exist (2) That which could not and does not exist but is present (therefore ‘Real’)”. Let us also accept that (1) collects: “(a) everything that we know like Earth, stars, mud, (b) everything that we can think of or imagine - models, formulas, triangles, present and future scientific theories, tooth fairies, ‘murtis’ of Ganesha, methods or procedures of performing ‘abhisheka’ etc. (these exist and could exist in our minds, even the ‘Real’ we imagine still belongs here as long as it is an imagined object)”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Sat explainable?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-real-explainable/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 21:25:55 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-real-explainable/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;No, I cannot explain the real; nor has anybody else in the world. Even more radically: the Real can never be ‘explained’, nor will there be an explanatory theory, ever (that is what is meant by ‘providing an explanation’ or speak of explaining) about the real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, if the ‘Real’ comprises of “all these doctrines” then the Real is the world of ideas as distinct from the material and the mental world. Popper believed this to be the case, and called it the ‘third world’. You are, therefore, right on the spot when you call me ignorant. Yes, indeed, I did not know that Indians were Popperians &lt;em&gt;avant la letter&lt;/em&gt;: avant la letter, because Popper did it with a clarity and verve that Indians never attained. This is the second reason I do not want to wake up. ‘Awakening’ of the type you propagate is terribly depressing because the resultant ‘gyaanodaya’ is this: Buddha, Shankara, Ramanuja, Madva (to mention only a few names) merely “prepared” the advent of Sir Karl Popper, in exactly the same way all cultures in the world before Christ were merely ‘Praeparatione Evangelica’. I wish you, who appears to be a disciple of this new ‘praeparatione’ (the famous ‘Second Coming’?), the best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Translating vibhaktis</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translating-vibhaktis/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 22:06:11 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translating-vibhaktis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The problem is more complicated and the implications far more massive than either of us can even dream of. In fact, I think we are not even aware of the nature, size and the dimensions of the problem(s) today. We do not even know whether we are dealing with something called the ‘translation’ problem or whole sets of other issues and problems that also redefine what it is to ‘translate’ texts between different cultures.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Real vs. Existence</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/real-vs-existence/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:46:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/real-vs-existence/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;With some justifiable distortion, one can claim that the Indian Adhyatmic traditions revolve partially around some &amp;lsquo;philosophical&amp;rsquo; questions: what is real and what is existence? Is there a distinction between the two and, if yes, how to draw that line? This is a distortion because the debate never took this form; it is justifiable nonetheless to present it this way because it gives us a handle to tackle them today. However, we need to note that this is our way of posing the question, not theirs. Therefore, whether or not &amp;ldquo;believing&amp;rdquo; in Rama or Krishna entails the existence of such entities requires clarity about notions like &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;belief&amp;rsquo; in the Indian traditions. I do not have this clarity and, only recently, I was told that the Indian intellectual traditions (in Sanskrit) do not have a word for &amp;lsquo;belief&amp;rsquo;. (It is as yet unclear to me what this implies: does it have the same force as the statement that Indians did not have a word for &amp;lsquo;gravitation&amp;rsquo; either or whether the notion of knowledge that we have is different from what we think knowledge is today.) Consequently, I cannot say much about this discussion today.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Historicity of Rama, Krishna, Anjaneya</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historicity-of-rama-krishna-anjaneya-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:38:27 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/historicity-of-rama-krishna-anjaneya-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the questions that has come up in this discussion is the following: are we logically forced to assume the &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo; of, say, Rama or Krishna, when we &amp;lsquo;believe&amp;rsquo; in them? This question has partly been responsible for the discussion about the &amp;lsquo;historicity&amp;rsquo; of Ramayana. Here is my answer as I see the situation today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some sense, we all work with some notions (however vague they might be) of &amp;lsquo;belief&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;existence&amp;rsquo;. These have at least two origins: (a) the western philosophical and scientific discourses about them, the way these have percolated into our common-sense; (b) their reinforcement by our day-to-day experiences in the world. That is to say, we have some conceptions of what human beings are (however vague or even incoherent these may be), what their properties are and so on. In other words, this notion of human beings tells us that (a) we are creatures who can form beliefs about some things (this &amp;lsquo;aboutness&amp;rsquo; is called intentionality in the relevant literatures); (b) that these beliefs could be about the world, about language, about ourselves, about what exists in the world and so on; (c) that some of these beliefs are about existent objects, whereas other beliefs are about non-existent objects; (d) and that to &amp;lsquo;believe in&amp;rsquo;, logically speaking, either entails or presupposes (it is irrelevant for now whether it is a presupposition or an entailment) that the entity we &amp;lsquo;believe in&amp;rsquo; is believed to exist. And so on. If we assume this picture of human beings to be true, then it follows that &amp;ldquo;believing in Rama or Krishna&amp;rdquo; has the same force as &amp;ldquo;believing in Christ or God&amp;rdquo;. Thus, one has to ascribe the logical truth about their existence to those who &amp;ldquo;believe in&amp;rdquo; these figures. In simple terms, if you &amp;ldquo;believe in&amp;rdquo; Rama or Krishna, then you are logically compelled to believe in their existence as well, just in case you endorse this picture about human beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Logical Acumen of Romila Thapar</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2012 09:28:45 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/logical-acumen-of-romila-thapar/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the debates in the Indian traditions is about the kind of creatures that exist in the world and about the reality of what exists. The Jains, for instance, disagreed that the &amp;ldquo;deva&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; of other traditions (with the properties they were supposed to possess) existed in this world or were real. (Their so-called &amp;lsquo;atheism&amp;rsquo; is a result of this debate.) Consequently, when they call Valmiki Ramayana false, they are making claims about the logical falsehood. They did not, on the basis of some or another empirical enquiry, establish that Ravana was a vegetarian or that Rakshasas were human beings (in fact, in many parts of India, people believe that Ravana was both a Brahmin and a rakshasa at the same time) or that Rama was different from what Valmiki said he was. The same applies to Anjaneya: the claim of some or another author that he was a human being and was married does not either &amp;lsquo;prove&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;disprove&amp;rsquo; the claim of Valmiki.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>