<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Christianity on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/christianity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Christianity on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 18:46:27 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/christianity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Spirituality = Adhyatma?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/spirituality-adhyatma/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 18:46:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/spirituality-adhyatma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One could justifiably see spirituality (the Jewish, Christian and Islamic) as ‘Adhyatma’ if one focusses on the psychological transformations that a human being undergoes in the process of moving from the mundane life to a ‘spiritual’ one. You would be closer to the notion of ‘Adhyatma’ if you can also additionally guide such a process. Such guidance requires, of course, that there is some deep understanding of such transformative processes and their mechanisms.&#xA;Yet, I would be hesitant to suggest that ‘spirituality’ translates ‘adhyatma’ or the other way round. From among the many reasons, I pick three:&#xA;(a) because the weight of the word ‘spirituality’ is drawn from Christianity, i.e., the kind of transformative force on a human being that we have in mind is the work of the ‘holy spirit’, it would be inappropriate to translate ‘adhyatma’ as ‘spirituality’;&#xA;(b) it is difficult to characterize the changes in human beings that we are talking about by using this word in Islam and Judaism as well. There is no ‘holy spirit’ in these two religions that does the work of the Trinitarian holy spirit;&#xA;(c) since a ‘spiritual’ person is the result of the workings of the holy spirit, in the context of Adhyatma which insists that transformations are the results of human phenomena working on human beings, the use of this word would be inappropriate. Both the Christian and the Adhyatmic use militates against such a translation.&#xA;In short, no, we should not translate ‘spirituality’ as ‘adhyatma’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Law of Excluded Middle: Christian Beliefs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 13:09:46 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/law-of-excluded-middle-christian-beliefs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was expecting you to show me where &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/&#34;&gt;the reasoning I formulated goes wrong&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, but you do not do so. The analogy you draw, I am afraid, does not quite do the job you want it to.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One can easily hold the following two beliefs (your example) without any fear of contradiction:&#xA;(a) There is only one way to Bombay (this is it) and (b) There are many ways to Bombay (this is one of them).&#xA;The &amp;lsquo;how&amp;rsquo; of it must be obvious: the &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo; is an indexical. Consequently, any person can hold both these beliefs together (at the same time or about the same route) without being contradictory (depending upon what he points out using the word &amp;rsquo;this&amp;rsquo;).&#xA;In fact, even statements like (c) &amp;ldquo;Route 19 is the only way to Bombay&amp;rdquo; and (d) &amp;ldquo;Route 24 is one of the ways to Bombay&amp;rdquo; can be held to be true by one and the same person at the same time without fear of contradiction. ( Both  statements would be true if Route 24 allows one to join Route 19 at some point or the other.) In other words, Minimus, your examples do not work the way you want them to.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Regarding my reasoning, this is what you say:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hindus may have ideas/opinions about the beliefs of the Christians but &amp;ldquo;beliefs about&amp;rdquo; cannot be compared to &amp;ldquo;beliefs&amp;rdquo; and I think that is the error.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proselytizing drive of the Eastern Christianity in India</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:31:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/proselytizing-drive-of-the-eastern-christianity-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually, there are two questions that need to be distinguished from each other. There is, firstly, the question about the nature of &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity. If it is muted in its proselytizing drive in all cultures the &lt;em&gt;same way&lt;/em&gt; and if it is &amp;rsquo;tolerant&amp;rsquo; in &lt;em&gt;exactly the same way&lt;/em&gt; in all cultures, it makes sense to ask the question whether (a) different factors in all these cultures have brought about the same effect (different &amp;lsquo;causes&amp;rsquo; can generate one and the same effect in differing circumstances) or (b) it is due to the nature of the &amp;lsquo;Eastern&amp;rsquo; Christianity itself. Nobody is able to make such a claim today. We do not possess the theoretical apparatus which would allow us to make sense of the remarks I have made in italics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Jesus a mystic?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-jesus-a-mystic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 00:29:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-jesus-a-mystic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You claim that Jesus of Nazareth is a mystic. From the conversations so far, I presume that this is both your gut-feeling and conviction. The one deriving from your own mystical experience and the other because you find that mysticism, qua experience, does not distinguish between people on the basis of their color, creed, culture and country. I am perfectly willing to bow to authentic experience, but convictions? They need arguments and evidence, even if it is a subject as thorny as mystical experience. However, I will not ask you for your evidence but will try to present &lt;em&gt;counter-evidence&lt;/em&gt; to your conviction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theology of Tolerance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/theology-of-tolerance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 21:39:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/theology-of-tolerance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to Judaism, Christianity and Islam, &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; is devil&amp;rsquo;s worship. Instead of quoting from their scriptures, let me give the barest of the bare outlines of their fundamental story about &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. No&lt;em&gt;believer&lt;/em&gt;from any of these religions (their religious authorities included) could ever disagree with this outline. There are two &amp;lsquo;Gods&amp;rsquo;: the true God and the false God (notice the capitalization). The first created the world and everything in it; the second, who is his creature too, is the &amp;lsquo;fallen&amp;rsquo; one. (Why he fell, what his &amp;lsquo;sin&amp;rsquo; was, etc. are glossed differently by these three religions.) The devil has &lt;em&gt;many names&lt;/em&gt; (Baal, Beelzebub, Satan, Lucifer, Mephistopheles, &amp;hellip;) and his followers are &amp;ldquo;legion&amp;rdquo;. This devil is the lord of the earth, the prince of darkness, the father of lies, the king of deceit, etc. the devil is the &amp;lsquo;false god&amp;rsquo;, i.e., he constantly seduces mankind into worshipping him as though he was God himself. To worship the devil is to go to hell for eternity; the road to salvation (please, do not confuse this with mukthi or moksha) lies in worshipping the true God. However, how to know who is the true God so that one may worship him? What does it mean to &amp;lsquo;worship&amp;rsquo; him? (After all, so their story goes, the false God also parades as &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; and deceives the humankind.) Hence, God &lt;em&gt;reveals&lt;/em&gt; himself (again, please do not confuse this with avataaras.), and tells that he is the true God and how humankind &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to worship him. (&amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, as they see it, is the worship of God.) This &lt;em&gt;revelation&lt;/em&gt; is what their scriptures are about. According to these revelations, God has commanded not to &lt;em&gt;build his likeness&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. create idols); to worship the idols is to worship the devil. This true God is one; the false &amp;lsquo;gods&amp;rsquo; are many (the devil&amp;rsquo;s &amp;rsquo;legion&amp;rsquo;); he has one name (Yahweh written without the consonants in Hebrew; the Holy Trinity in Christianity; the merciful Allah in Islam); the devil has &lt;em&gt;many names&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;Do not confuse names with the hundred and odd properties of God that Koran talks about.&lt;/em&gt; Now, these and more are God&amp;rsquo;s revelations in these three religions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religious Intolerance and Believers</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/believers-vs-their-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 21:15:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/believers-vs-their-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two distinct problems: one involving religions (like Christianity, Judaism and Islam) and the other involving the believers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Regarding these three religions: (a) insofar as these religions (Judaism, Christianity and Islam) are concerned, Hinduism is demonic. It is that because, according to all the three religions, &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; worship the devil (&amp;lsquo;shaitan&amp;rsquo;) and his minions. That is to say, our Rama, Vishnu, Ganesha, Saraswathi, etc. are all lieutenants of the devil himself. The idols, according to their theology, are representations of the devil, and Pat Robertson is simply echoing this standard Christian (Judaic, and Islamic) doctrines. There is nothing &amp;rsquo;extremist&amp;rsquo; about this statement: it is, as I say, one of the basic claims of these three religions. Because we worship the devil, they are convinced, we will all go to hell (do not confuse this with our naraka) for eternity. Because they want to save souls, these religions want to convert others into &amp;lsquo;believers&amp;rsquo;. (By the way, the &amp;lsquo;jealous&amp;rsquo; God is God of the Jews - God of Israel - in one of the more known aspects from the Old Testament Bible. In the New Testament, God is supposed to be &amp;rsquo;loving&amp;rsquo;. If you want to irk a Jew just tell him that his God is jealous and punishing, whereas God of Christianity is loving.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Devil worship in &#39;Hinduism&#39;</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/devil-worship-in-hinduism/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 00:01:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/devil-worship-in-hinduism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here goes: that &amp;lsquo;Hindu&amp;rsquo; religion is devil&amp;rsquo;s worship is central, crucial and vital to the religions that Judaism, Christianity and Islam are. &amp;lsquo;Why is that?&amp;rsquo;, you may ask. It is impossible to cover this question in the space of a post, and with the details the question demands. So, here is what can be done: (a) I will provide a very crude outline with respect to Christianity; (b) reread what &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/&#34;&gt;I wrote about God and devil .&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belief vs Faith</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 23:50:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/belief-vs-faith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) It appears to me that in these discussions, a very vital issue (if we want to talk about Judaism, Christianity and Islam, and their &amp;lsquo;problems&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;, etc) is not being recognized. and that is this: religious &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; are not accorded their place, and are talked about as though they are merely a subset of the class of &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) &amp;lsquo;Being a believer&amp;rsquo; (I will confine myself to Christianity for the sake of brevity) does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean assenting to the proposition that &amp;lsquo;God exists&amp;rsquo;. For, if this is what it would mean, then the Devil himself is the first believer: after all, he does accept it as true that God exists. (The Devil is not an atheist, mind you.) He knows that God exists: after all, he rebelled against him! As the new testament Bible puts it: &amp;ldquo;thou believest that there is one God; thou doest well: the devils also believe, and tremble.&amp;rdquo; (James 2: 26)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercultural exchange of categories</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 19:42:30 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intercultural-exchange-of-categories/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is wrong with the intercultural exchange of categories? Throughout one gets the impression that there is something “fundamentally wrong” with categories shifting in meaning over time or with the introduction of categories from one culture into another culture. But what is important about these shifts in meaning? What exactly is the problem in introducing the category of religion into India or among Native Americans? The category “yuppie” did not exist in the Middle Ages, while “orange” came through Arabic from Sanskrit, and “girl” used to refer to a young person of either sex. When we analyse the genetics of early modern populations, we are also introducing categories that they did not possess. Or take the word “silly,” which in Old English used to mean blessed. So what? An historical analysis of discourse and categories is significant not to identify shifts in meaning per se. Shifts in meaning become significant only against the background of a theory on the historical development of the western culture and its understanding of other cultures. Such a theory is needed to clarify as to why a shift in the meaning of “religion” or “the secular” is of crucial importance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religion ‘sui generis’?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/religion-sui-generis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2011 22:24:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/religion-sui-generis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a religion claims that it is the word of God and that the word is unconditionally true; and that, further, the word is about the Cosmos: everything that was, is and shall be. So, when I say that religion is such an entity, namely, it claims that it is the word of God and that it claims to be unconditionally true and that it is about the Cosmos, I am accepting the self description of religion. (However, the hypothesis that religion is an EI account formulates it without committing itself to any ontological claims. That is, it takes no stances about what specific religions say or do not say about the existence of entities. The hypothesis does not show how, and in what sense, the Bible, say, is an EI account. It merely says that The Bible has such a status to believers. If you reread the relevant paragraphs of &amp;lsquo;The Heathen&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo; where I first formulate the hypothesis, you will notice that I formulate it conditionally: &amp;ldquo;If such a being exists, if such an account is forthcoming &amp;hellip; etc then we have an EI account.&amp;rdquo;) If we do not accept the self-description of religion, The Bible becomes a mere book and we cannot study it at all to say anything about Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theme: Hacker’s inclusivism and exclusivm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-hackers-inclusivism-and-exclusivm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 02:43:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-hackers-inclusivism-and-exclusivm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we consider  Paul Hacker&amp;rsquo;s story on &amp;lsquo;inclusivism as a typically Indian thought form&amp;rsquo;, all we can conclude is that he has used a &lt;em&gt;typically Christian  thought form&lt;/em&gt; to understand an aspect of the Indian cultural traditions, which he is unable to understand because it is completely different from what he knows. Hacker&amp;rsquo;s inclusivism is merely an attempt to strip the following Christian account from its recognizably Christian characteristics: &amp;ldquo;When God created man he inscribed him with a sense of divinity, and when it is &lt;em&gt;not corrupted&lt;/em&gt; this sense is the true religion. Throughout human history the devil and his minions corrupted this sense of divinity into false religion or worship of the devil among all human peoples. Until the good Lord brought mankind back to the true religion by revealing himself in Jesus Christ. Thus, Christianity is the one true religion. It is the message of self-disclosure in which God reveals his Will for the universe to the humankind. Of course, all other traditions contain traces of divine revelation, but these are nothing but the preparation of the Gospel. Once the true religion was revealed again, all non-Christian traditions could be nothing but pale and erring variants of Christianity.&amp;rdquo; Now Hacker has merely taken this Christian conceptual scheme to make sense of the attitude the Indian traditions take towards other traditions. Although it happens unconsciously most of the time, this is &lt;em&gt;the basic method of Indology&lt;/em&gt;: one looks at the Indian traditions, and the only way to make sense of them is to make them fit into a conceptual framework of secularized Christian theology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enlightenment vs. Mysticism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-vs-mysticism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 02:57:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-vs-mysticism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(1) What is called &amp;lsquo;mysticism&amp;rsquo; in the western culture is not the same &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of experience that the different Indian traditions talk about. (2) I do think, as a corollary, that to describe the Indian &amp;rsquo;enlightenment&amp;rsquo; (let me use this word temporarily, the scare quotes indicate my reservations) as &amp;lsquo;mysticism&amp;rsquo; is not to understand either. (3) There are different levels in and different ways to achieve &amp;rsquo;enlightenment&amp;rsquo;. (4) It is extremely important and significant that finitely different means to achieve this state have been worked out by each of these ways. I want to go further in exploring the significance of these points and in exploring this state of &amp;rsquo;enlightenment&amp;rsquo; that the Indian traditions talk about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christian theology and linguistic intuitions: prostitute</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christian-theology-and-linguistic-intuitions-prostitute/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 06:30:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christian-theology-and-linguistic-intuitions-prostitute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In so far as the suggestion is that the English word &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; does not capture the connotations of the earlier uses of &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo;, as I said, I agree with all of you. In this sense, if you further suggest that &amp;lsquo;Apsara&amp;rsquo; should not be considered as a synonym for &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo;, I would also agree. I do not suggest that &amp;lsquo;apsara&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; are synonyms: for two words to be synonymous in this context, we need that both words refer to one and the same set of objects. This cannot be the case here because &amp;lsquo;apsara&amp;rsquo; picks out only non-human entities, whereas &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; can also refer to human beings. I would also be grateful if anyone has a better suggestion for translating &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo;. As I said in an earlier post,&amp;lsquo;courtesan&amp;rsquo; is an alternative. However, a &amp;lsquo;courtesan&amp;rsquo; is also a prostitute, whatever else she is. On this, linguistic part, there are no disagreements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Bible an explanatorily intelligle account of Cosmos and of itself?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-bible-an-explanatorily-intelligle-account-of-cosmos-and-of-itself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 23:23:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-bible-an-explanatorily-intelligle-account-of-cosmos-and-of-itself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a religion claims that it is the word of God and that the word is unconditionally true; and that, further, the word is about the Cosmos: everything that was, is and shall be. So, when I say that religion is such an entity, namely, it claims that it is the word of God and that it claims to be unconditionally true and that it is about the Cosmos, I am accepting the self description of religion. (However, the hypothesis that religion is an explanatorily intelligible (EI) account formulates it without committing itself to any ontological claims. That is, it takes no stances about what specific religions say or do not say about the existence of entities. The hypothesis does not show how, and in what sense, the Bible, say, is an EI account. It merely says that The Bible has such a status to believers. If you reread the relevant paragraphs of &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo; where I first formulate the hypothesis, you will notice that I formulate it conditionally: &amp;ldquo;If such a being exists, if such an account is forthcoming &amp;hellip; etc then we have an EI account.&amp;rdquo;) If we do not accept the self-description of religion, The Bible becomes a mere book and we cannot study it at all to say anything about Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christological Dilemma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 23:20:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says that Christological dilemma is some kind of theological logic and suggests that ordinary Christians are not affected by this artificial problematic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two issues here worth looking at separately.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is the problematic artificial? Well, it depends. I am not claiming that every Christian (past, present and future) is &lt;em&gt;aware&lt;/em&gt; of this problematic, of course. This is a general formulation that attempts to capture the variety in Christianity as answers to some specific problem. It has the same status as some or another scientific law. Even though what we have in this Cosmos, say, are &lt;em&gt;concrete, moving objects of specific size, volume, density and so on&lt;/em&gt;, we have laws that describe such specific movements as instances of a &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; law. In exactly the same way, I (partially) describe the varieties within Christianity as various answers to the Christological dilemma. Does that make my description artificial? Well, this is an issue about &lt;em&gt;your own&lt;/em&gt; metaphysics: what &amp;rsquo;natural&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; is and what &amp;lsquo;artificial&amp;rsquo; is. All I can say is that my description does partially capture the &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt; within Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atheism: a secularized theism—Jakob de Roover</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 01:25:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/atheism-a-secularized-theism-jakob-de-roover/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1: Atheism is a phenomenon that came into being in the western culture at around the time of the so-called Enlightenment. The West claims that it liberated itself from the dogmas of the Christian religion in this Enlightenment, and those who call themselves atheists mean by this that they belong to the enlightened people who &amp;ldquo;have escaped from the dogmatic illusions of religion.&amp;rdquo; Now, as it has always done, Christian Europe simply identified its own history with human history in general, and it claimed that all cultures had so far been under the ignorant spell of religion, but that they could now be liberated by the Enlightened West. This claim needs two separate premises: (a) That all cultures have religion (b) That atheism was a new and rational system of beliefs that could liberate people from all cultures from this illusion of religion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What makes Christianity a religion? The structure of Christianity as a religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-structure-of-christianity-as-a-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:55:49 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/the-structure-of-christianity-as-a-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The logical steps that &lt;em&gt;inevitably&lt;/em&gt; make the claim that God revealed His Will in Jesus Christ into an unconditional and exclusive truth claim are fairly simple:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) Christianity says that the universe was created by God, and that this universe is the perfect embodiment of His will or plan;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(b) Furthermore, it claims that this God has revealed His Will to humankind, and that this revelation is the Christian doctrine as it is &amp;rsquo;embodied&amp;rsquo; in Jesus Christ;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Presumption of Knowledge—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/presumption-of-knowledge-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:32:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/presumption-of-knowledge-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first striking thing is their &lt;em&gt;presumption of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; at several levels. Yet, they display abysmal ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(a) Christianity has not just had a two thousand years&amp;rsquo; history. It has also had two thousand years of doctrinal development. In the latter, every notion that has been employed here has been &lt;em&gt;continuously&lt;/em&gt; discussed, refined, contested and so on. Their meanings, as they apply to Christianity&amp;rsquo;s self-description, has seeped into and determined what they mean in the English language. Not only words like &amp;lsquo;Christ&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Church&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Worship&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;idol&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;revelation&amp;rsquo; and so on but also issues like &amp;lsquo;Who is a Christian&amp;rsquo;? (&lt;em&gt;Quid sit Christianum esse?&lt;/em&gt;) The discussions hardly exhibit any knowledge of either the richness or complexity of these matters; yet, they express the firm conviction that what is there to be known is also known. In matters of knowledge, this combination is deadly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about “Who is a Christian”—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:27:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine that I were to say the following: Christ and &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; are manifestations of the same divinity; Christ came about 2000 years ago in the Middle East, whereas &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; is how he has appeared in India some 4000 years ago. Now no one can forbid me from saying this and &lt;em&gt;calling myself a Christian&lt;/em&gt;. Question: what should a theory about Christianity do? Show &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; anyone who decides to call himself a &amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo; is, in fact, also a Christian? In that case, all such a &amp;rsquo;theory&amp;rsquo; can do is say something like the following: anyone who calls himself some name (&amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Democrat&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Marxist&amp;rsquo;, etc) is also whatever he calls himself. Such an attitude simply ends up making any knowledge of society and human beings impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Indian Christians not bound by Christian Theology? –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-indian-christians-not-bound-by-christian-theology-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:34:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-indian-christians-not-bound-by-christian-theology-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You say: Thus when one says that many Indian Christians are pluralistic &amp;hellip; it cannot be refuted simply by saying, well Christian doctrine fundamentally cannot be pluralistic &amp;ndash; because all doctrine ultimately always gets interpreted at the level of the individual.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While it is indeed true that, in the last analysis, everything happens at the level of the individual, it is wrong to say that, &lt;em&gt;therefore&lt;/em&gt;, claims about the Indian Christians cannot be refuted by referring to Christian theology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christological dilemma and “who is a Christian”</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-and-who-is-a-christian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:26:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-and-who-is-a-christian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Christians of all hue agree that the &lt;em&gt;figure of Christ&lt;/em&gt; is central to the religion that Christianity is. This figure is &amp;ldquo;the promised one&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;messiah&amp;rdquo;, the &amp;ldquo;anointed one&amp;rdquo;, and so on. Kindly note that there is a difference between the Christ as a figure and &lt;em&gt;Jesus of Nazareth&lt;/em&gt;. The Jews also believe in the Christ figure, but they figure that he has not yet come, and they are awaiting his arrival. The Christians reckon that the Christ has come and that Jesus of Nazareth was the &amp;ldquo;prophesied one&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is tolerant Christianity a contradiction in terms?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-tolerant-christianity-a-contradiction-in-terms-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 23:19:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-tolerant-christianity-a-contradiction-in-terms-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even if one insists (wrongly in my view) that I am suggesting that Alex Alexander is not a Christian, there are two ways of looking at the &lt;em&gt;object&lt;/em&gt; of my assertion: (a) it is about the &lt;em&gt;unique&lt;/em&gt; individual that Alex Alexander is; (b) it is about him in so far as he is an &lt;em&gt;instance&lt;/em&gt; of the tolerant Christianity that some Indian Churches are supposed to be. I am &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; discussing (a): I do not know this unique individual, his history, his feelings and such like. Let us look at what discussing (b) entails.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intentional operator and inconsistent reasoning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 20:10:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intentional-operator-and-inconsistent-reasoning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A Christian netizen says:&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;here is within exclusive religions the claim that theirs is the only way to God (that claim can be true or false). There is in inclusive religions the claim that there are several ways to God and that it is quite possible that one of the exclusive ones (or many of them) are also ways to God. Both these statements cannot be true at the same time iff the logical law of excluding the middle holds. I don&amp;rsquo;t think that I have come across a way around this except through it &amp;ndash; i.e. one of the claims must be false or worst case both are false (there is no God or there is no path yet).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
