<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Colonial Consciousness on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/colonial-consciousness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Colonial Consciousness on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 14:41:17 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/colonial-consciousness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Servitude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 14:41:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[ Published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://swarajyamag.com/politics/prime-ministers-panch-pran-and-decoloniality-indian-servility-may-have-roots-in-secularised-islam&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; Aug 26, 2022]&#xA;Let me recollect the question we agreed upon: &lt;em&gt;how does the combined phrase (colonial mindset and servitude) make sense within the framework of my research programme?&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;My hypothesis on religion includes characterizing the dynamics of its expansion. As I see it, such a dynamic includes (a) conversion and (b) secularization. The first side of the dynamic, ‘conversion’, is well-known to most of us: here, some or another religion &lt;em&gt;inducts&lt;/em&gt; ‘non-believers’ into its fold or into its community of believers and practitioners. (I also called it ‘proselytization’, a term that notices how Judaism and Christianity use ‘proselyte’.) The second side of the dynamic, ‘secularization’, is known to us only very partially.&#xA;Made popular since the Enlightenment period in Europe, this partial description identifies an &lt;em&gt;antithetical movement&lt;/em&gt; where an individual religion begins to lose its earlier influence on its spheres of influence: the civil organizations and the civil authorities. This classical story is about the withdrawal of religion from various domains in society: politics, law, judiciary, and so on. In this ‘age of reason’, it is suggested that human reason begins to govern these institutions and provide their foundations instead of religious opinions and dogmas. One of its consequences is the loss of the power and control of the Church on the State. Called ‘secularism’, this process indicates the waning power of religion on people and their imaginations especially by freeing the civil, the social, and the psychological spheres of human beings and society. The freedom from those shackles that enslaved them over the millennia made human beings and their societies grow and expand. ‘Indian Secularism’ (both as a vacuous doctrine and in the threadbare ‘foundation’ it received in the Indian constitution) expresses this faith and this conviction in an extremely pathetic form ever since (or even decades before) the Indian independence 75 years ago.&#xA;My story, while giving credence to the hostility it expresses, locates the ‘secularization process’ as another side in the expansion of religion. Secularization is antithetical to the expansion of &lt;em&gt;some or another&lt;/em&gt; religion, but it expands religion itself as a phenomenon in a culture or society. As we know, each religion (I have the Semitic religions in mind here) is always &lt;em&gt;a specific religion:&lt;/em&gt; it emerged at some time, in a specific region, among a specific people, in a specific language, embodying specific doctrines, and specific practices. Thus, every religion (even where it aspires to be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; religion for the entire humankind) is always a specific religion. These very specificities that lend identity to some or another religion act as constraints on &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt;, which is, as I characterize it, the explanatory intelligible account of the Cosmos and itself. This account is &lt;em&gt;the truth&lt;/em&gt; about all that was, is and shall be. This truth is not only in the world but religion, as such an account, exhibits that truth. Thus, religion, &lt;em&gt;as religion&lt;/em&gt;, expands itself while this or that specific religion expands through conversion. Both, taken together, are moments in the expansion of religion.&#xA;Even though secularization of religion is a general process, how this process occurs is determined by the conditions of emergence of a specific religion and how that religion converts. That is, how religion secularizes itself is subject to the nature and constraints that the specific religions face. Thus, the secularization of Judaism, Christianity and Islam occur &lt;em&gt;differently&lt;/em&gt; even where each of them undergoes secularization as a moment in its expansion. In each of these religions, secularization is inimical and hostile to a particular religion because of the specificities that give us an individual religion.&#xA;In ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ I said that Indians were children of two colonialisms: one colonizer was Islam and the other was the British. This means that &lt;em&gt;religions too colonize&lt;/em&gt;. I did not expand on the idea in that book (you must wait for the upcoming works to grasp the idea more fully), but I will briefly outline only one element of this colonizing event. It is true that Islam tried to convert Indians and it is also true that it did so violently. While Islam launched many waves of destructive attacks on Indian traditions, their temples, and practices, etc., we were not colonized by this aspect or phase of Islamic expansion. (It is in the nature of religions, Christianity and Islam, to convert through extremely violent means when conversion is directed towards larger populations and established cultures. Judaism, after around 5th century C.E., almost stopped conversion. There are various reasons for this cessation, none of which is relevant for my story here.) &lt;em&gt;We were colonized by secularized Islam&lt;/em&gt;. That is, conversion into Islam did not colonize us; the secularized Islam did.&#xA;I have already noted that secularization is inimical and hostile to religion. What does it mean in our case? It means that the secularized Islam that colonized us was hostile to &lt;em&gt;Islam as a religion&lt;/em&gt;. Among other things, it means that it is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to Islamic doctrines as well. How? In very simple religious terms: &lt;em&gt;secularized Islam is blasphemy&lt;/em&gt; (within the framework of Islam as a religion). What does this mean?&#xA;According to Islam, Allah is the Lord and the Ruler of the Universe. As the word ‘Islam’ indicates, it demands an attitude of absolute submission and total surrender to Allah and His will. It requires a complete obedience to Him; human beings must follow His rules and Laws unconditionally. In its phase of conversion into a religion, Islam tried to inculcate this reverential attitude and habit towards Allah among the converted. In its secularizing moment, Secularized Islam reversed this thought and attitude entirely and gave it &lt;em&gt;a blasphemous form&lt;/em&gt;: among Indians, it inculcated and induced such a habit and attitude, &lt;em&gt;not towards Allah&lt;/em&gt;, but towards human rulers. &lt;em&gt;Secularized Islam put human Muslim rulers of India above the Prophet Mohammed and placed the same rulers as Allah’s equals&lt;/em&gt;. This is how secularized Islam expressed its antithetical attitude to Islam as a religion and expressed its hostility towards Islam.&#xA;I have claimed that colonialism transforms the experience of people and prevents the colonial subjects from accessing it in any form other than how the colonizer defines it. This inability to access our experience is what I call ‘colonial consciousness’. This is what secularized Islam also did: it introduced slavishness and servitude into Indian psychology. Centuries of this colonization made a &lt;em&gt;slavish submission to civil authorities&lt;/em&gt; the hallmark and an important trait of Indian cultural psychology. In very simple terms: &lt;em&gt;Indians became slavish, submissive, and servile to civil (i.e., human) authorities&lt;/em&gt;.&#xA;The British noticed this psychological trait of Indians and said that Indians were ‘effeminate’ and had ‘no backbone’. Though this is what all the Bengalis were in their eyes, after all, Bengal was one of first important ports of call to the British; very soon, all Indians joined the group of a servile people. That is why they went in search of ‘military’ castes in their attempts to recruit Indians to the British army. They found such ‘castes’ among the Sikhs and the Marathas (both of whom fought the Muslim rulers over long periods) and the Gurkhas (who were least subject to secularized Islamic rule). They found it among some ‘sub-castes’ as well: the Coorgis in Karnataka belonged to the ‘martial type’. The rest of India was too effeminate to be of much use except to slavishly obey the British authorities and lick their boots. How Indian child-rearing practices and the socialization processes in India succumbed to cultivating servility in Indian children because of Islamic colonization has not been understood yet. But that is not relevant to this story now.&#xA;When British ‘gave’ India her independence, the Indian servility did not disappear. It continues to be produced and reproduced even today. If we look at how Indians relate to &lt;em&gt;civil authorities&lt;/em&gt;, we see this servitude everywhere. The bureaucracy, the police, the ministers receive obsequiousness without demanding it. They punish those who dare ‘defy’ them. This is not merely how ordinary Indians relate to political and administrative authorities: this is institutionalized within these organizations too. How a peon responds to the boss; how a junior secretary bows down to the Deputy secretary; how the Chief secretary deals with Principal secretaries; how the chief minister treats the principal and the chief secretaries, how the circle inspector treats the local constable and is treated in turn by the assistant commissioner of police… This servitude, often called sycophancy, goes all the way to the very top.&#xA;This is how Indians are seen abroad: whether by the Chinese or in the West. Obsequious, eager to please and servile. This cultural psychology expresses our colonial consciousness as induced by Islamic colonization. Very recently, a few weeks ago, I read somewhere that Rahul Gandhi fulminated against the Indian foreign service officials thus: Indian diplomats are seen to have become &lt;em&gt;arrogant&lt;/em&gt; by others elsewhere in the world (due to Modi’s government). This perception makes sense: Indian diplomats are not any more as servile as they were in the last sixty years. They continue to have this psychology, but they do not express it as ‘the normal’ anymore.&#xA;There is much, much more to say than what I have. The story is bigger, broader, and richer than what I have penned so far. But I will round-off here. The phrase that combines ‘colonial mindset’ and ‘servitude’ makes sense within my research programme this way. It tells me how one colonialism has generated one aspect of our psychology. This attitude and orientation are in us and with us even now and will have their own poisonous and deleterious impacts on the development of the amritkaal that the PM spoke about. As I told you in an earlier mail, I have no clue what the PM intended or meant. This post is merely an attempt to see whether the combination makes sense within my research programme. It does. However, the implications are &lt;em&gt;gigantic&lt;/em&gt;: both for pursuing the pledge (the pran) and to fulfill it in the amritkaal that the PM seeks. They have their own pernicious effects on the current programmes of the government and all its future policies.&#xA;I must apologize for the brevity. You must wait for the upcoming works to understand this story properly. But I do hope this post will have done enough to keep the promise that I made in my earlier post.&#xA;Clarifications:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stupidity of Indian meanings of English words</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/stupidity-of-indian-meanings-of-english-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 10:31:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/stupidity-of-indian-meanings-of-english-words/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Note: For a broader application and context, please read this paper: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/2014-comparative-theology.pdf&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;translation, interpretation and culture&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;rsquo;temple&amp;rsquo; is not used in English to refer to a place where false gods are worshipped. It is used to speak of &amp;ldquo;the temple of Solomon&amp;rdquo; (the king Solomon of the Jews) too and there is no suggestion in the western culture that the Jews worshipped false gods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Your friend is providing you with an identifying description: &amp;ldquo;this building which&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and identifies it in terms of several functions tied to that building.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Enlightenment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 15:31:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post will use an imagery as its organising thread, which tracks the search for enlightenment in terms of notions known to us from our secondary and higher education.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;If we consider the search for happiness in these terms, then the ideas expressed &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/&#34;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/strong&gt; could be reformulated thus: as human beings, almost all of us would like to be literates or would like to have a primary education. This is the move ‘away’ for unhappiness that all of us aim at, namely, to be ‘less unhappy’. After a period of time, many of us would like to move further. This is the move ‘towards’ (peace of mind, contentment, satisfied, etc.) happiness now formulated in positive terms: the phase of secondary education. The completion of this process is to reach a state of peace (shanti), or contentment (samadhana), or satisfaction (trupti) etc. The Sri Sri’s and the Sadguru’s of this world help us here through their Sudarshan Kriya’s, their yogic practices, their meditative courses and so on. The vipassana meditation, the Satsangh’s, the bhajans, the dhyaanas etc. are also situated here. Some people in this phase also call themselves Saadhakas, doing their ‘saadhana’ on a very regular basis.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you want to go further and, therefore, seek higher education (call it Ananda, or happiness). There are two broad routes here: technical or vocational education is one route; university education is another. If you want to be plumber, a carpenter, a sculptor, a painter, a machinist…then you are better-off choosing technical education. However, you could also go for a university education. There is no ‘higher’ or ‘lower’ here; both are different forms of higher education. (Of course, there are endless discussions about ‘superiority’: one group disparagingly calls the other ‘vocational training’, while the other caricatures the first as ‘purely theoretical’ that is unsuited for fulfilling the ‘need’ for useful education or the ‘needs’ of society.) A society cannot survive without plumbers, electricians, machinists, artists, etc. Nor can it live without the ‘ivory tower’ that universities are and should be. Individual students make their choice based on multiple reasons (from aptitude to financial rewards) and many gifted teachers prefer to teach in vocational or professional schools than in a university. However, whatever the choice, both demand that the student specifies clearly what s/he wants to learn: do you want to be a sculptor or a machinist; in which subject do you want  your bachelor and Master’s degree? ‘Ananda’, the generic word, does not suffice here because it merely picks out ‘higher education’: do you want to do physics or chemistry or biology or English literature at the university? ‘Gyaana marga’ (the university) on the one hand and ‘other routes’ (vocational and professional training) on the other hand are the main avenues in higher education.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of this imagery, ‘enlightenment’ refers to the total process of ‘higher education’ and ‘seeking ananda’ fixes the goal of higher education. Each avenue has its way of classifying its internal levels or divisions (Bachelors, Masters, Doctoral, Post-doctoral in the university, for example) and teaches students accordingly. They share many commonalities: the subject matter, the instruments, the theoretical frameworks, etc. etc. They are also different from each other in ways of teaching, investigating, making and reporting discoveries, and so on. The names of some teachers in higher education are known to us: Buddha, Shankara, Ramanuja, Madhva, Vallabha, Ramakrishna Paramahamsa, Ramana, Nisargadatta Maharaj, etc. Let us not deal with the question whether they taught at the University or were active in professional or technical education because something else of greater importance has to be noticed: you have to choose the ‘subject’ of higher education first. ‘Seeking Happiness’ or ‘wanting enlightenment’ are not adequate at all. You need to specifiy what you are seeking and, preferably, why.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of Intellectual Svaraj</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:34:03 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In so far as one sees &lt;a href=&#34;http://creative.sulekha.com/the-axis-of-neocolonialism_103313_blog&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; as a beginning of a certain type of enquiry, it is excellent. However, it is not adequate as a formulation of either the problem that confronts the Indian intellectuals (and not merely them) or the solutions. The problems are far more complex and the task is far more daunting than they appear at first sight.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What may not be forgotten, if one wants to be relevant and rational at all, is that we live in a world which has not merely included colonialisms but also our responses to them. Our generation is molded (mostly) by a colonial past that has basically been accessed only through its critique: whether nationalist, Marxist or Orientalist. Consequently, our questions, problems and misgivings are not those of a generation or two ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why study the Western culture?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 06:04:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-study-the-western-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two substantial questions have been raised in response to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-intellectual-svaraj/&#34;&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;: (a) why do we need to study and understand the Western culture in order to access our own traditions? (b) Is it my claim that Buddha and Shankara (for example) are irrelevant to us? One other sort of &amp;lsquo;objection&amp;rsquo; too has surfaced, albeit disguised as a characterization of what I have said: (c) is not my position itself illustrative of &amp;lsquo;Eurocentrism&amp;rsquo;? These issues are intertwined.  Hopefully, addressing them together will lend some clarity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: M.N. Srinivas and Sanskritization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-m-n-srinivas-and-sanskritization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2013 04:25:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-m-n-srinivas-and-sanskritization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;M. N. Srinivas (MNS) claims that &amp;ldquo;a caste was able, in a generation or two, to rise to a higher position in the hierarchy by adopting vegetarianism and teetotalism and by changing its rituals and deities.&amp;rdquo; The first basic problem here is how one can establish the position of a jati in the supposed hierarchy and measure it in such detail that one can see over two generations that the jati has attained a higher position. Which standard does one use to establish the position of jati x? What members of jati x say about its position relative to other jatis? What members of other jatis say about the position of x relative to their own jatis? As our fieldwork in Karnataka has already shown, it is impossible to infer any hierarchy from such empirical data, because all one gets is a series of inconsistent statements with regard to the relative positions of jatis. This basic problem becomes even more intractable when we take into account the history of assigning positions to jatis in the so-called &amp;ldquo;caste hierarchy&amp;rdquo;. When the British had their caste census in the late nineteenth and early twentieth century, many jatis classified as shudras or untouchables sent in petitions arguing that they held higher positions; they were kshatriyas, they said. Today, the same jatis insist that they are really shudras or untouchables and should be classified as OBCs or SCs. When jatis can radically revise their &amp;lsquo;position in the hierarchy&amp;rsquo; according to the status or benefits they win by doing so, what could one ever conclude about their position and how it changes over generations?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Should one calculate the average socio-economic level of jati x and compare it to the average level of other jatis? Apart from difficulties in calculating this socio-economic level, one faces an even more difficult problem: how does one circumscribe jati x? Are two groups with the same name both sub-divisions of jati x? What if they claim they are different jatis? What geographical or social unit should one begin with to establish the (socio-economic) position of jati x in the hierarchy? Let us say one takes the village as the relevant unit. How does the socio-economic level that jati x enjoys in some village tell us anything about its position in the hierarchy? If the socio-economic welfare of jati x increases markedly over two generations in this village, does this mean it has attained a higher position? What if the same jati in the surrounding villages has declined? In terms of empirical data, then, it becomes impossible to say (a) what the position is of a jati in the supposed hierarchy and (b) when it has attained a higher position. In other words, MNS can never have inferred his conclusions about Sanskritization and castes rising to higher positions from his &amp;lsquo;fieldwork data&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to access Indian traditions?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-access-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 07:08:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-access-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As I have often said, the most intriguing aspect of the Indian culture is the kind of knowledge it produced and encouraged people to produce: experiential knowledge which emerges by systematically reflecting on our (human) experiences in the world. As human beings, our experiences are many: no one set, no one kind of experience exhausts what we go through. From the purely personal experiences of the world (our ambitions, hopes, dreams, frustrations, etc) to the entirely social ones (the experiences of sorrow and injustice that other human beings in the world experience). So, knowledge that reflects on or thinks about and systematizes such experiences presupposes multiple learning sites, many diverse perspectives and varied kinds of intellectual skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation: Spontaneous or Intentional</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 22:10:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If we want to grasp the nature of the discussions in the Indian traditions, there is much we need to do beforehand: (a) identify the entity they were talking about; (b) identify the specific questions they were answering; (c) identify the generic questions that defined both the outlines of the acceptable answers and the formulation of the specific questions; etc. (The &amp;lsquo;cetera&amp;rsquo; indicates that I do not know how to enumerate all the things we need to grasp.) In the case of the propositions you have formulated, I assume that &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; is Vishnu (or even Krishna) and not, say, Shiva or Brahma because you are talking about the Madhvas. However, to keep the discussion faithful to your formulations, I will use the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; to refer to Vishnu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BJP does not have Intellectuals!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/bjp-does-not-have-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2011 04:40:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/bjp-does-not-have-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I see it, the issue is not whether Arun Shourie is an intellectual (or whether Prakash Karat and EMS Namboodaripad represent intellectuals). The point I was trying to make is the one between a social movement and intellectuals.  Any movement that captures the imagination of a people (or even of a cross-section of a people) has to have some or another kind of narrative. Normally, the crafting of such a narrative involves the labor of intellectuals. Congress had one such when it was a mass movement; however, it lost that narrative in the course of the last decades. In the process of losing its own narrative, it has also accommodated multiple voices and narrators: the so-called &amp;lsquo;radical&amp;rsquo; intellectuals in India have prospered under the congress rule. The Communist Parties have their intellectuals, both native and foreign and from yesterday and today. The BJP did find resonance in a cross-section of the people in India and yet it does not appear to possess a distinct narrative of its own. The fact that BJP gets characterized in different ways (&amp;lsquo;Hindu Fundamentalist&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Fascist&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Nationalist&amp;rsquo;, etc) by different people indicates that these characterizations have more to do with the theory that one accepts about these phenomena (&amp;lsquo;religious fundamentalism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;fascism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;nationalism&amp;rsquo;, etc) than they have to do with the &amp;lsquo;story&amp;rsquo; that BJP tells. Furthermore, the BJP is also hostile to intellectuals: in fact, it is very typical to hear them identify &amp;lsquo;intellectuals&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;secular thinkers&amp;rsquo;. It is almost as though they think that this social layer, which the intellectuals are, is an &amp;lsquo;alien growth&amp;rsquo; in the Indian culture, something that the British created. While it is undoubtedly true that the kind of academic intellectuals we have today are outgrowths of colonial and post-colonial developments, this situation does not quite explain the hostility of the BJP. Hostility towards knowledge is not &amp;rsquo;native&amp;rsquo; to the Indian culture. At the same time, BJP is not hostile to something that is really &amp;lsquo;alien&amp;rsquo; to Indian culture: Nationalism. Instead, the &amp;lsquo;ideologues&amp;rsquo; of the BJP try to spin a deeply &amp;rsquo;nationalist&amp;rsquo; story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sanskrit Pundits, Indian texts, Colonial Consciousness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/sanskrit-pundits-indian-texts-colonial-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 20:04:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/sanskrit-pundits-indian-texts-colonial-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we go-about with our fellow human beings, we need to possess some or another idea about the nature of ourselves and our fellow human beings. (Call it, for the sake of convenience, an &amp;lsquo;intuitive theory&amp;rsquo; about human beings.) It is an implicit understanding because each one of us does not have to be a professional philosopher or psychologist to get along with ourselves and fellow human beings. So, in principle, we must possess a vocabulary to talk about human beings; if we do not, we can neither talk about human beings nor could we make sense of their actions in the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do we understand Colonialism?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/do-we-understand-colonialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 18:32:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/do-we-understand-colonialism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Colonialism has been one of the most significant phenomena in the history of humankind in the last three hundred years or so. Its importance can hardly be overstated. Yet, as many have said before, it has not been adequately theorized. There is of course a great deal of material on the histories, the effects, and the political resistances to colonialism. Reading them, however, &lt;strong&gt;merely increases the puzzlement about colonialism&lt;/strong&gt;: though it seems to be at &lt;strong&gt;the root of all the ills&lt;/strong&gt; of the modern world, what is not clear is how or why that is the case. Perhaps, that has to do with an implicit consensus shared by many: everyone appears to know what it is and most agree about its immoral nature. &lt;em&gt;Colonialism emerges as a self-clarifying and a self-explaining phenomenon. If it is self-luminescent and so manifest an evil, why did many people in the Metropolis argue both about the nature of the phenomenon and its moral status for centuries on end?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religious colonialism: Islamic vs. Christian</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/religious-colonialism-islamic-vs-christian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2011 00:39:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/religious-colonialism-islamic-vs-christian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As Indians, if we have to access the Indian traditions we need two things: (a) it must be possible for us to access them; (b) we must know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to access them. That is to say, growing up in the Indian traditions not merely means that we have the possibility of accessing them if we want to but we have also learnt how to access them when we want to.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Only for the sake of convenience, let me put it this way: in so far as we are brought up in the Indian culture, &lt;em&gt;in ideal conditions&lt;/em&gt;, we learn two things: (a) we learn to access our experience (one kind of ability); (b) we also learn to access the Indian traditions that are the results of accesses that the earlier generations have had to their experience (a second kind of ability). If we get only the ability (a) transmitted to us, it is like reinventing the wheel but a through a cumbersome process: trial and error, stumbling and standing upright, going through dead ends and false avenues and so on. Some might succeed in this venture, yet others might fail. There are no signposts, no heuristics, and no established results to work with etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Buddha and Colonial Consciousness</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/understanding-buddha-and-colonial-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 19:42:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/understanding-buddha-and-colonial-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How do we understand the idea that an enlightened person has no wants?&amp;rdquo; Before we understand what the idea says, it would be good to find out what it does not say. Understanding this would also allow us to appreciate the depth and extent of colonial consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you look at the way the Buddha was portrayed in the middle-class text books you studied (that is also how he was more or less portrayed during my period), it appears as though he &lt;em&gt;gave up&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;renounce&lt;/em&gt; all his desires. In other words, he became an &amp;lsquo;ascetic&amp;rsquo; man. Yet strangely enough, if we read about the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s road to enlightenment, we find something else: he did take to and practice asceticism, but, he says, it did not help him to get enlightened! That is, even though some people do practice asceticism and can get enlightened (after all, every path can lead to enlightenment), this was not the Buddha&amp;rsquo;s way. The Buddha, then, did not become enlightened by &amp;lsquo;giving up&amp;rsquo; his desires. Almost in a similar vein, Purandara Dasa also says in his &amp;ldquo;Eenu Maadidareenu Bhava Hingadu&amp;rdquo; that &amp;ldquo;punishing his body&amp;rdquo; did not help him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indian way of Westernization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/indian-way-of-westernization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:44:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/indian-way-of-westernization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How the Indians learn whatever they learn will be in accordance with their ways of going-about in the world. That is to say, the configuration of learning determines how they learn whatever it is they learn.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What do they learn from the West? That theoretical knowledge is the foundation of all human going-about. That is, that their activities have to be theoretically founded.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;Indian way of going-about&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, the practical or the performative dominates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the hypothesis about colonial consciousness ad hoc?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-hypothesis-about-colonial-consciousness-ad-hoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 06:10:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-the-hypothesis-about-colonial-consciousness-ad-hoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have come to accept that the most interesting facts that a theory explains are those of the theory itself. Furthermore, a &amp;rsquo;theory&amp;rsquo;, which collects all kinds of facts first and tries to &amp;rsquo;explain&amp;rsquo; them subsequently, is worse than having no theory. Such a theory is completely ad hoc and is cognitively uninteresting. It is pernicious too because it generates the belief that one understands such facts, when, in fact, all one has is an ad hoc explanation. In this sense, I have not collected evidence for the statement that &amp;lsquo;Indians accept European reports as descriptions of their world&amp;rsquo;; nor am I explaining these assembled facts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Sanskrit Concepts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 05:13:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-sanskrit-concepts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many are concerned that English translations of some words from native languages distort their meaning. If we restrict ourselves to terms like &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Dharma&amp;rsquo; and such like, the worry is not just that their translations distort the meaning of these words (as we use them in our native languages) but that they suggest something (by way of reference and meaning) that does not even exist in these languages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With respect to some of these words, we can build a reasonable case in defense of this stance. That is because there is at least some theory about religion that we accept (however provisional or conditional such an acceptance might be) using which we can show that &amp;lsquo;Deva&amp;rsquo; cannot be translated as &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo;. So far so good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Brahmins ‘priests’?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 04:01:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/are-brahmins-priests/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not have a theory of meaning. I do not know which of the many fragmentary theories of meaning I should choose from and why. Even though I acknowledge the importance of the topic, I do not feel called upon to do research on it. So far, I have been able to steer clear of the topic in &lt;em&gt;an interesting way&lt;/em&gt;: I am able to show that what appears as translation problem or a meaning problem (how should Sanskrit words be translated or the definition of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;, etc) is, at least in some instances, actually not that kind of a problem at all. Such an attitude has generated a psychological bonus for me: I do not go around criticizing Jeffrey Kripal for not knowing Bengali well enough, or for Wendy Doniger for not realizing that Dharma is not religion or that Brahmins are not priests, when my knowledge of either Bengali or Sanskrit does not match up to what they know.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is Colonial Consciousness?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 03:53:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Colonial consciousness incorporates the following element: in making statements about the colonized, the colonizer thinks that he is describing the colonizer. The latter, for his part, takes such statements as true descriptions of himself. What is involved is not the authority of the explainer (the colonizer) but the truth-value of the statements. How do we know this to be the case? Because we continue to think such statements are true even after &amp;lsquo;direct&amp;rsquo; colonization has ended.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Victorian Morality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 06:13:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-victorian-morality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You suggest that calling Apsaras as &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo; is an extreme statement. Of course, you would be right if you mean that the English word does not carry all the connotations of &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; or even that our current usage of the word &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; is not as rich as the earlier uses of the same word were. You are right too when you point out that the word &amp;lsquo;Kama&amp;rsquo;, as a pursushartha, embraces a bigger set than sexual pleasure or romantic love. Perhaps, one might prefer the word &amp;lsquo;courtesan&amp;rsquo; to &amp;lsquo;prostitute&amp;rsquo; but that distorts the Indian &amp;lsquo;Veshya&amp;rsquo; too: a courtesan was either a mistress of the wealthy or a prostitute who entertained only the rich. However, I am not sure whether my claim is really that extreme (with the proviso that we keep in mind the current-day changes in the meanings of the words in both English and Indian languages). Let me explain why.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we read, say, Kamasutra, we discover that prostitutes had to be cultured and learned human beings; they were supposed to be proficient in multiple arts including music, poetry, dance, handicrafts and so on. &amp;lsquo;Treating the prostitutes humanely&amp;rsquo; includes teaching these skills to them: after all, many of the arts they practiced to entertain men requires teaching and learning. This suggests that a teacher could take prostitutes as his/her students and that the society did not disapprove. Instead, it countenanced such teaching. However, this is not all there is to the story. Consider the fact that a prostitute is also called &amp;rsquo;nitya sumangali&amp;rsquo;: one who can never become a widow. As you know, the word &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; is not usedlightly in India and it carries a very positive connotation as is also indexed by the use of &amp;lsquo;su&amp;rsquo;. (Of course, one uses this term also sarcastically in colloquial language but such use does not take away the positive connotation.) Even though the prostitute never marries, our traditions did not withhold the appellation &amp;lsquo;sumangali&amp;rsquo; from her. Consider too, in this context, the &amp;lsquo;good qualities&amp;rsquo; of a wife: &amp;lsquo;Karyeshu dasi, Karaneshu mantri&amp;hellip;.&amp;rsquo; As this verse (I have forgotten both its source and how it ends) continues, it appears that a wife should also be &amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo; (a prostitute in bed). Quite independent of the conjectures we can make about its anti-feministic character or whatever, think about what this verse is suggesting: the wife should behave like a prostitute in the bedroom. What does that mean? Whether or not it also means that she should entertain her husband through music, recitation of poetry, dance and such like, one thing is clear: she must be well-versed in sexual matters. Step back for a moment and ask yourself how any girl could be well-versed (better than her husband, in fact) in sexual matters. There are only two possibilities: either the girl had a lot of experience in sex before marriage (there goes the idea of virginity of one&amp;rsquo;s wife) or she was trained and educated in the art of sex in her family. Irrespective of which of the possibilities is true, this verse indicates at least two things: being a prostitute did not make one immoral anymore than visiting a prostitute made one immoral. The prostitute had qualities which a &amp;lsquo;good wife&amp;rsquo; should emulate. Note that these qualities are not those that prostitutes also have; the wife is supposed to have those qualities that make a woman into a prostitute (&amp;lsquo;shayaneshu veshya&amp;rsquo;).  Furthermore, in so far as women were taught the &amp;lsquo;art of loving&amp;rsquo; (kama-sutra) in their families, surely, it tells us that the reaction of the middle class in India today is anything but Indian: it is an inherited prudishness drawn from the Victorian morality. It is in this sense that I suggested that the Indians are not prudes in matters of sexuality. In this sense too, in this Indian sense, Apsaras, I claim, are &amp;ldquo;prostitutes in the court of Indra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victorian morality of NRI and middle class Hindus: Prostitution, Adultery</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 05:53:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The Indian traditions did not have the same attitude as Christianity towards prostitution or adultery. And the Indians of yesteryears were not defenders of the Victorian (and Christian) morality. Of course, I approvingly said that the &amp;ldquo;Indians are not prudes&amp;rdquo; but this approval has to do with the thrust of Indian thought, as I have understood it: the impossibility of prohibiting or making obligatory some or another action universally. (This is my formulation, of course.) I do believe that the Indians recognized the impossibility of abolishing prostitution (which is why it is called &amp;ldquo;the oldest profession&amp;rdquo;). Instead, therefore, of banning and condemning prostitution (and subsequently turn a blind eye towards its existence), Indian thinkers suggested that we treat the prostitutes humanely. I have never been to a prostitute nor will I ever go to one; but that does not mean that I want to ignore their existence and treat them as non-humans. Nor am I willing to call all those who visit prostitutes as criminals and perverts. I know of too many lonely men and women who have found human warmth and personal comfort in the arms and companionship of prostitutes to consider them as perverts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is the most ideal social security system (safety net)?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-the-most-ideal-social-security-system-safety-net/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 04:57:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-the-most-ideal-social-security-system-safety-net/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me invite you to do a thought-experiment along with me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Imagine that all human beings seek happiness. Imagine too that they can all achieve this state of being. Because, as I said in one of my posts, there are no qualifications (or requirements) to reach this end-state; any and all ways are conducive to reach this end-state: thinking, meditation, music, dance, and, yes, even going to temples and reciting &amp;lsquo;sahasranaamams.&amp;rsquo; At any and every stage and moment, people can achieve happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is tradition akin to following moral obligations?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 04:45:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-tradition-akin-to-following-moral-obligations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditions are inherited practices, which mean two things: they are both transmitted and learnt. The learning occurs through imitation, following instructions, through stories and so on. Consequently, traditions &amp;lsquo;change&amp;rsquo; (i.e. undergo modifications) even as they are being transmitted and learnt. This makes traditions flexible and adaptive.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Human practices conserve, that is, we do not go around inventing new practices every day. In this sense, traditions are essentially conserving in their nature. This is one of the reasons why we see &amp;lsquo;being traditional&amp;rsquo; as `being conservative&amp;rsquo; as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is experience? IV</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-experience-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 01:31:16 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-is-experience-ii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If we take our English language use as a reference point, it appears as though we can speak sensibly about experiencing our feelings (&amp;lsquo;I experience sadness&amp;rsquo;), experiencing thoughts (&amp;lsquo;I can even now experience my jumbled thoughts when &amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo;), experiencing colour (&amp;lsquo;I experience a redness&amp;rsquo;), experiencing actions (&amp;lsquo;I still experience my shaking limbs when I&amp;hellip;&amp;rsquo;) and so on. That is, we can experience the &amp;lsquo;inputs&amp;rsquo; of all our five senses. From this, it follows that experience &lt;em&gt;cannot be&lt;/em&gt; identical to any of them. Experience might contain, as its elements, inputs from these five senses in the form of thoughts, feelings, sensations, etc. but it cannot be coextensive with any one of them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explanations that trivialize experiences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/explanations-that-trivialize-experiences-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 05:33:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/explanations-that-trivialize-experiences-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, especially in the Indian case, it is important to understand that stories are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; explanations. They are neither true nor false because they do not describe &amp;lsquo;factual&amp;rsquo; events; they do not claim that they do either. Unlike the Bible, the Puranas do not have to be true or known to be true for them to play the role they do in the Indian culture. The Indian myths neither allegorize virtues nor are they &amp;lsquo;disguised&amp;rsquo; histories. In other words, the presuppositions of your question (common ones in the western scholarship since the Enlightenment) are &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt; and based on ignorance about the genre of the myth and the roles they play. (I can only assert these claims having argued them &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;elsewhere.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness as a process and as an event</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-as-a-process-and-as-an-event/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 09:27:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-as-a-process-and-as-an-event/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is an event because the colonial consciousness that I am talking about comprises of multiplicity of actions executed by indefinitely many Indians over a long period. It is a process because colonial consciousness reproduces itself, colonial consciousness is transmitted from generation to generation and it is learnt. Consequently, we need to understand the mechanisms of this process and the structure of that event.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the minimum, this process has to be cognitive in nature. It must be cognitive because a cognitive framework (and theories within that framework) denies access to our experience and makes us reproduce some sets of descriptions as though they are descriptions of our experience. It has to be cognitive at the minimum because in reproducing some sets of descriptions and in embellishing them with details, we act as though we understand such descriptions. In other words, the growth and spread of colonial consciousness requires some kind of a cognitive explanation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introspection vs. reflection on experience—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/introspection-vs-reflection-upon-experience-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 09:05:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/introspection-vs-reflection-upon-experience-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to reflect on what it means &lt;em&gt;to access and think&lt;/em&gt; about experience. Perhaps, not so much on what these words mean but what is entailed by (or what happens when we indulge in) this kind of activity. I think the best way to begin this analysis is by asking the following two questions about an activity familiar to most of us: what do we do when we think about ourselves? Do we do it the &amp;lsquo;right&amp;rsquo; way? Let me begin with the first question and postpone looking at the second for a later stage, including how we should understand it. Because most of us know how we think about ourselves most of the times, I will take a trivial example and skip over certain explanations and analyses. The holes in my reasoning can either be filled by our memories or by discussing them at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative assumptions and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-assumptions-that-make-actions-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 01:17:20 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-assumptions-that-make-actions-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that there is no distance between how we use corruption in our daily language and the way it is used in political and sociological theories of corruption. You see, the problem we (Indians) face is the asymmetry &lt;em&gt;in the way the word is used&lt;/em&gt; while talking about us and the way it is used when talking about India. I want to signal this by putting up the red flag: I want to suggest the reader not to assume the truth of these descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: Burden of Proof</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-burden-of-proof-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 00:22:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-burden-of-proof-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The first thing that is really striking involves what I will call the &lt;em&gt;burden of proof&lt;/em&gt;. That is, I am being asked to prove that my assertions about corruption are true. In one sense, it appears an entirely reasonable demand to make: after all, one should not entertain gratuitous claims. But what seems to have escaped the attention of many is this: what precisely do I have to prove? Who has the burden of proof?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Let us strip the issue to its barest form. I am supposed to prove that we Indians are not corrupt, immoral and/or moral imbeciles. Without proof, is it difficult to accept these claims? But who has proved that we are any or all of these things? Not the western theorists, surely. Not any Indian either. All that exist are bare-bone assertions that some moral principles are violated in a systematic fashion in India. So, what exactly do I have to prove?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness: The Logic of “India is Corrupt”</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 22:17:32 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-the-logic-of-india-is-corrupt-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(A)&lt;/strong&gt; Consider the following sequence of sentences:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are perfectly and fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are perfectly fully moral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All Indians are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All westerners are immoral.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For sentences (1) and (2), all it takes is one instance of immorality to be proven wrong. Our proverbial municipal clerk would be immoral, and it would disprove the sentence (1). The same example could also confirm sentence (3); an instance of a moral act would also be a counter-example.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Colonial Experience and the Indian Renaissance: A prolegomenon to a Project—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the striking things about the British colonial rule is its success in developing certain ways of talking about the Indian culture and society. The British criticised the Indian &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;, the Indian &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo;, the Indian education system, practices like &amp;lsquo;sati&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;untouchability&amp;rsquo;, and so on and so forth. They redrew the outlines of Indian intellectual history as indigenous responses to some of the ills they saw in the Indian society and culture: for example, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, as it emerged out of their reconstruction, was a revolt against &amp;lsquo;Brahmanism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo;. Many Indian intellectuals emphasized British criticism by making &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; in the latter their own: the Arya Samaj, the Brahmo Samaj, many Hindu &amp;lsquo;reform&amp;rsquo; movements, and so on exemplify this trend. I say &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; and place it in scare quotes because the &lt;em&gt;unbroken line of continuity&lt;/em&gt; between the colonial period and the one following the Indian independence raises two &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of questions. The first is this: would there have been such a line of continuity if there was no &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; to the British portrayal of our history, traditions, and culture? This question uses the &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; of continuity to suggest that the British descriptions &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; That is, our current experience of our culture and society appears to lend truth-value to the colonial descriptions of India. The second question transforms our &amp;lsquo;current experience&amp;rsquo; itself into a problem: does such a line of continuity indicate that our experiences themselves are still colonial in nature? This question throws doubts upon the &amp;lsquo;facticity&amp;rsquo; of the British descriptions of India, and suggests that they &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;lsquo;untrue&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; In the process, it also challenges us to look more closely and investigate our own experiences today. That is, the second question withholds assent to the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of the colonial descriptions of India and of some of the claims we make about our experiences of our culture and society today. To some extent, and only to some extent, the so-called &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; writings can be seen as attempts to make sense of the second question. Even though I do not fancy the label of being a &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; myself, I perceive a shared sense of a quest with them. &lt;em&gt;There is something deeply, deeply wrong with the line of continuity that exists between the colonial period and today&amp;rsquo;s India,&lt;/em&gt; and the challenge is to say what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Experience: Normative Ethics I</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-experience-normative-ethics-101-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:32:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/colonial-experience-normative-ethics-101-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is western normative ethics? It is a structure or style of thinking about ethics. What is its structure? It makes use of norms. What are norms? &amp;lsquo;Rules&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;principles&amp;rsquo; which have a characteristic structure that use certain concepts like the moral &amp;lsquo;ought&amp;rsquo; and moral &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo;. That is, some actions &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to be performed (i.e. they are obligatory); some actions &lt;em&gt;ought not&lt;/em&gt; to be performed (i.e. they are forbidden) and some actions are neither of the two (i.e. they are permitted). What is important to note is that these norms (i.e. for example, some action is obligatory) hold irrespective of time, place, condition or the person. In other words, norms are supposed to hold universally. From what I have said above, it logically follows that violation (or transgressing) some moral norm or the other is immoral (or unethical) and following some moral norm is moral (or ethical).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
