<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Colonialism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/colonialism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Colonialism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 08:39:14 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/colonialism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Indian education system is a social parasite</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/indian-education-system-is-a-social-parasite/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 08:39:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/indian-education-system-is-a-social-parasite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask: “(a) Do you mean Islamic colonial rule affected our attitude towards knowledge (how we learn)? And (b) How do we fix the colonial era bureaucracy?” Because of their relevance, my answer is posted on the forum.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To begin answering these huge questions, we must look at the world in terms of “&lt;em&gt;tendencies&lt;/em&gt;” (both social and cultural) &lt;em&gt;at a high level of abstraction&lt;/em&gt;. An example of what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colonial Consciousness and Servitude</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 14:41:17 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-servitude/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[ Published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://swarajyamag.com/politics/prime-ministers-panch-pran-and-decoloniality-indian-servility-may-have-roots-in-secularised-islam&#34;&gt;swarjyamag&lt;/a&gt; Aug 26, 2022]&#xA;Let me recollect the question we agreed upon: &lt;em&gt;how does the combined phrase (colonial mindset and servitude) make sense within the framework of my research programme?&lt;/em&gt;&#xA;My hypothesis on religion includes characterizing the dynamics of its expansion. As I see it, such a dynamic includes (a) conversion and (b) secularization. The first side of the dynamic, ‘conversion’, is well-known to most of us: here, some or another religion &lt;em&gt;inducts&lt;/em&gt; ‘non-believers’ into its fold or into its community of believers and practitioners. (I also called it ‘proselytization’, a term that notices how Judaism and Christianity use ‘proselyte’.) The second side of the dynamic, ‘secularization’, is known to us only very partially.&#xA;Made popular since the Enlightenment period in Europe, this partial description identifies an &lt;em&gt;antithetical movement&lt;/em&gt; where an individual religion begins to lose its earlier influence on its spheres of influence: the civil organizations and the civil authorities. This classical story is about the withdrawal of religion from various domains in society: politics, law, judiciary, and so on. In this ‘age of reason’, it is suggested that human reason begins to govern these institutions and provide their foundations instead of religious opinions and dogmas. One of its consequences is the loss of the power and control of the Church on the State. Called ‘secularism’, this process indicates the waning power of religion on people and their imaginations especially by freeing the civil, the social, and the psychological spheres of human beings and society. The freedom from those shackles that enslaved them over the millennia made human beings and their societies grow and expand. ‘Indian Secularism’ (both as a vacuous doctrine and in the threadbare ‘foundation’ it received in the Indian constitution) expresses this faith and this conviction in an extremely pathetic form ever since (or even decades before) the Indian independence 75 years ago.&#xA;My story, while giving credence to the hostility it expresses, locates the ‘secularization process’ as another side in the expansion of religion. Secularization is antithetical to the expansion of &lt;em&gt;some or another&lt;/em&gt; religion, but it expands religion itself as a phenomenon in a culture or society. As we know, each religion (I have the Semitic religions in mind here) is always &lt;em&gt;a specific religion:&lt;/em&gt; it emerged at some time, in a specific region, among a specific people, in a specific language, embodying specific doctrines, and specific practices. Thus, every religion (even where it aspires to be &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; religion for the entire humankind) is always a specific religion. These very specificities that lend identity to some or another religion act as constraints on &lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt;, which is, as I characterize it, the explanatory intelligible account of the Cosmos and itself. This account is &lt;em&gt;the truth&lt;/em&gt; about all that was, is and shall be. This truth is not only in the world but religion, as such an account, exhibits that truth. Thus, religion, &lt;em&gt;as religion&lt;/em&gt;, expands itself while this or that specific religion expands through conversion. Both, taken together, are moments in the expansion of religion.&#xA;Even though secularization of religion is a general process, how this process occurs is determined by the conditions of emergence of a specific religion and how that religion converts. That is, how religion secularizes itself is subject to the nature and constraints that the specific religions face. Thus, the secularization of Judaism, Christianity and Islam occur &lt;em&gt;differently&lt;/em&gt; even where each of them undergoes secularization as a moment in its expansion. In each of these religions, secularization is inimical and hostile to a particular religion because of the specificities that give us an individual religion.&#xA;In ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ I said that Indians were children of two colonialisms: one colonizer was Islam and the other was the British. This means that &lt;em&gt;religions too colonize&lt;/em&gt;. I did not expand on the idea in that book (you must wait for the upcoming works to grasp the idea more fully), but I will briefly outline only one element of this colonizing event. It is true that Islam tried to convert Indians and it is also true that it did so violently. While Islam launched many waves of destructive attacks on Indian traditions, their temples, and practices, etc., we were not colonized by this aspect or phase of Islamic expansion. (It is in the nature of religions, Christianity and Islam, to convert through extremely violent means when conversion is directed towards larger populations and established cultures. Judaism, after around 5th century C.E., almost stopped conversion. There are various reasons for this cessation, none of which is relevant for my story here.) &lt;em&gt;We were colonized by secularized Islam&lt;/em&gt;. That is, conversion into Islam did not colonize us; the secularized Islam did.&#xA;I have already noted that secularization is inimical and hostile to religion. What does it mean in our case? It means that the secularized Islam that colonized us was hostile to &lt;em&gt;Islam as a religion&lt;/em&gt;. Among other things, it means that it is &lt;em&gt;hostile&lt;/em&gt; to Islamic doctrines as well. How? In very simple religious terms: &lt;em&gt;secularized Islam is blasphemy&lt;/em&gt; (within the framework of Islam as a religion). What does this mean?&#xA;According to Islam, Allah is the Lord and the Ruler of the Universe. As the word ‘Islam’ indicates, it demands an attitude of absolute submission and total surrender to Allah and His will. It requires a complete obedience to Him; human beings must follow His rules and Laws unconditionally. In its phase of conversion into a religion, Islam tried to inculcate this reverential attitude and habit towards Allah among the converted. In its secularizing moment, Secularized Islam reversed this thought and attitude entirely and gave it &lt;em&gt;a blasphemous form&lt;/em&gt;: among Indians, it inculcated and induced such a habit and attitude, &lt;em&gt;not towards Allah&lt;/em&gt;, but towards human rulers. &lt;em&gt;Secularized Islam put human Muslim rulers of India above the Prophet Mohammed and placed the same rulers as Allah’s equals&lt;/em&gt;. This is how secularized Islam expressed its antithetical attitude to Islam as a religion and expressed its hostility towards Islam.&#xA;I have claimed that colonialism transforms the experience of people and prevents the colonial subjects from accessing it in any form other than how the colonizer defines it. This inability to access our experience is what I call ‘colonial consciousness’. This is what secularized Islam also did: it introduced slavishness and servitude into Indian psychology. Centuries of this colonization made a &lt;em&gt;slavish submission to civil authorities&lt;/em&gt; the hallmark and an important trait of Indian cultural psychology. In very simple terms: &lt;em&gt;Indians became slavish, submissive, and servile to civil (i.e., human) authorities&lt;/em&gt;.&#xA;The British noticed this psychological trait of Indians and said that Indians were ‘effeminate’ and had ‘no backbone’. Though this is what all the Bengalis were in their eyes, after all, Bengal was one of first important ports of call to the British; very soon, all Indians joined the group of a servile people. That is why they went in search of ‘military’ castes in their attempts to recruit Indians to the British army. They found such ‘castes’ among the Sikhs and the Marathas (both of whom fought the Muslim rulers over long periods) and the Gurkhas (who were least subject to secularized Islamic rule). They found it among some ‘sub-castes’ as well: the Coorgis in Karnataka belonged to the ‘martial type’. The rest of India was too effeminate to be of much use except to slavishly obey the British authorities and lick their boots. How Indian child-rearing practices and the socialization processes in India succumbed to cultivating servility in Indian children because of Islamic colonization has not been understood yet. But that is not relevant to this story now.&#xA;When British ‘gave’ India her independence, the Indian servility did not disappear. It continues to be produced and reproduced even today. If we look at how Indians relate to &lt;em&gt;civil authorities&lt;/em&gt;, we see this servitude everywhere. The bureaucracy, the police, the ministers receive obsequiousness without demanding it. They punish those who dare ‘defy’ them. This is not merely how ordinary Indians relate to political and administrative authorities: this is institutionalized within these organizations too. How a peon responds to the boss; how a junior secretary bows down to the Deputy secretary; how the Chief secretary deals with Principal secretaries; how the chief minister treats the principal and the chief secretaries, how the circle inspector treats the local constable and is treated in turn by the assistant commissioner of police… This servitude, often called sycophancy, goes all the way to the very top.&#xA;This is how Indians are seen abroad: whether by the Chinese or in the West. Obsequious, eager to please and servile. This cultural psychology expresses our colonial consciousness as induced by Islamic colonization. Very recently, a few weeks ago, I read somewhere that Rahul Gandhi fulminated against the Indian foreign service officials thus: Indian diplomats are seen to have become &lt;em&gt;arrogant&lt;/em&gt; by others elsewhere in the world (due to Modi’s government). This perception makes sense: Indian diplomats are not any more as servile as they were in the last sixty years. They continue to have this psychology, but they do not express it as ‘the normal’ anymore.&#xA;There is much, much more to say than what I have. The story is bigger, broader, and richer than what I have penned so far. But I will round-off here. The phrase that combines ‘colonial mindset’ and ‘servitude’ makes sense within my research programme this way. It tells me how one colonialism has generated one aspect of our psychology. This attitude and orientation are in us and with us even now and will have their own poisonous and deleterious impacts on the development of the amritkaal that the PM spoke about. As I told you in an earlier mail, I have no clue what the PM intended or meant. This post is merely an attempt to see whether the combination makes sense within my research programme. It does. However, the implications are &lt;em&gt;gigantic&lt;/em&gt;: both for pursuing the pledge (the pran) and to fulfill it in the amritkaal that the PM seeks. They have their own pernicious effects on the current programmes of the government and all its future policies.&#xA;I must apologize for the brevity. You must wait for the upcoming works to understand this story properly. But I do hope this post will have done enough to keep the promise that I made in my earlier post.&#xA;Clarifications:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hindering the emergence of alternative explanations: Colonialism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/hindering-the-emergence-of-alternative-explanations-colonialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 02:40:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/hindering-the-emergence-of-alternative-explanations-colonialism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I suggested that the psychoanalytical explanations (like the transformation of Linga into a penis as a fertility symbol etc.) not only trivialize and distort but also deny access to our own experience. In this post, I want to highlight &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of the consequences of transforming our experiences in this fashion. In at least two different ways, &lt;em&gt;these explanations hinder the emergence of alternative or different explanations of our experiences&lt;/em&gt;. This is relevant to both of us. That is why, when confronted with such explanations, we do not know &lt;em&gt;what to say&lt;/em&gt;. These explanations rob us not only of our experience; while doing so, they shut us up as well. As far as you are concerned, while rendering you deaf to the silence from our end, it further &lt;em&gt;blinds&lt;/em&gt; you. If this is the case, one might as well ask oneself what you describe. Are you describing what you &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; in the mystical Ramakrishna? You could not: after all, what can you see, when you are blind? Nor it could be that you describe what you hear: you have become deaf to us. What, then, are you describing when you describe &lt;em&gt;your experience&lt;/em&gt;? This issue is what this post will be about.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularism, Colonialism and Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:01:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/secularism-colonialism-and-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the last few decades, &amp;ldquo;secularism&amp;rdquo; has become the subject of caustic debate in the Indian media. The dispute about the value of this idea to contemporary India is no longer confined to the academic circles. Politicians, journalists and others have strong views on the topic. Secularism regularly surfaces in newspaper articles, speeches and public meetings. The critics of the idea, however, are not often taken seriously at the theoretical level. The proponents of secularism dismiss all objections against their pet idea as misguided. Critics are either considered to be naive obscurantists, who dream of a return to a romantic image of Indian traditional society; or they are condemned as Hindu fundamentalists, who resist modern secular values and strive for a Hindu religious state.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do we understand Colonialism?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/do-we-understand-colonialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 18:32:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/do-we-understand-colonialism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Colonialism has been one of the most significant phenomena in the history of humankind in the last three hundred years or so. Its importance can hardly be overstated. Yet, as many have said before, it has not been adequately theorized. There is of course a great deal of material on the histories, the effects, and the political resistances to colonialism. Reading them, however, &lt;strong&gt;merely increases the puzzlement about colonialism&lt;/strong&gt;: though it seems to be at &lt;strong&gt;the root of all the ills&lt;/strong&gt; of the modern world, what is not clear is how or why that is the case. Perhaps, that has to do with an implicit consensus shared by many: everyone appears to know what it is and most agree about its immoral nature. &lt;em&gt;Colonialism emerges as a self-clarifying and a self-explaining phenomenon. If it is self-luminescent and so manifest an evil, why did many people in the Metropolis argue both about the nature of the phenomenon and its moral status for centuries on end?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denying Experience: Do Hindus ‘worship’? Do they do Pooja to phallus (linga)?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 20:46:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/denying-experience-do-hindoos-worship-do-they-do-pooja-to-a-phalluslinga-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone, let&amp;rsquo;s say her name is Wendy Doniger, comes along and sniggers &amp;lsquo;when you worship the lingam, you worship a phallus&amp;rsquo;. I do not identify Wendy&amp;rsquo;s statement as an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation. I say that it trivializes what I am doing by providing a distorted description of what I do. Here is what I say: &amp;ldquo;I am doing Puja to Shiva.&amp;rdquo; No discussion about &amp;lsquo;Lingam&amp;rsquo; or its many meanings. This is a &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; way of conducting a discussion. She cannot, therefore, argue that I am giving an &amp;lsquo;ad hoc&amp;rsquo; explanation because I am not giving an &amp;rsquo;explanation&amp;rsquo; of what I am doing but merely describing it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
