<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NRI on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/nri/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NRI on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:28:31 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/nri/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Courting controversy in the West</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:28:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/courting-controversy-in-the-west/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sustained efforts by certain Hindu groups in the west to redefine and &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; long existing Hindu traditions are perhaps reflective of their desire to put in place a cogent and structured religious system that is able to hold its own against other scripture-based religions. Concomitantly, American identity politics and European political correctness is also &amp;ldquo;forcing&amp;rdquo; minority communities to assert their separate &amp;ldquo;churches&amp;rdquo;, as a way of emphasising their own distinct religious or ethnic identity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facing the challenge of American Pluralism on the future of NRI community</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facing-the-challenge-of-american-pluralism-on-the-future-of-nri-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 08:29:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facing-the-challenge-of-american-pluralism-on-the-future-of-nri-community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In years to come, the Indian community in the U.S. will face a major challenge from American pluralism. This is the first time a powerful community of pagans has to be accommodated within the American society. The NRI community is well-educated, well-to-do and proud of its cultural traditions. At the same time, the representation of the Indian traditions in the U.S. educational system shows a pathetic level of understanding. I will argue that recent events like the California textbook controversy point to a profound problem: &lt;em&gt;the American model of pluralism is unable to accommodate these pagan traditions&lt;/em&gt;. This is the case, because its structure has emerged from a co-existence of Protestant denominations. Maximally, the resulting model could encompass other variants of the religions of the book: Catholicism, Judaism and Islam. Incorporating the pagan traditions of India, however, will require a fundamental rethinking of American pluralism.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Follow Our Forefathers: The Nature of Tradition –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 07:25:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While reading this contribution and all the others (&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;) I hope to write, we need to keep the context in mind. The context is this: many intellectuals, both in India and among the NRIs elsewhere, appear bent on transforming our multiple traditions into a single &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. The problem does not lie in the transformation of variety and diversity into a unity. Rather, it lies in trying to fit our traditions into the straightjacket of &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;. While calling ourselves &amp;lsquo;Hindus&amp;rsquo; might be a convenient way of talking, the danger lies in going further and trying to develop &amp;lsquo;doctrines&amp;rsquo;, &amp;rsquo;theologies&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;catechisms&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Ten Commandments&amp;rsquo; so that those around us in the West could recognize us as followers of a religion called &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;. (These reflections are also applicable to &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Jainism&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Saivism&amp;rsquo; and all such entities.) In the course of my future contributions, I will look at some of the compulsions that force us to manufacture &amp;lsquo;Hinduism as a religion&amp;rsquo;. In this piece, I want to focus on the nature of traditions. What is a tradition? What differentiates religions from traditions? The second question will remain implicit until the end. By that time, we should have a better understanding of what it means to speak of a tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Understand the Western Culture?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 04:53:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-understand-the-western-culture-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin this contribution, the third piece about our culture and traditions(&lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/to-follow-our-forefathers-the-nature-of-tradition-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/translations-or-travesty-of-traditions-s-n-balagangadhara/&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;), by sharing something you are familiar with. Very often, I have heard the NRI parents in the USA making the following remark:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I came to the US so many decades ago, I knew very little about Hinduism. My ignorance was driven home when I had children and they began to ask what Hinduism was. Because I had to educate them, I ended up learning more about Hinduism in the US (thanks to this or that organization or Swami) than during all the years I spent in India.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kids of NRI and their Balvihar education</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/kids-of-nri-and-their-balvihar-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 05:40:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/kids-of-nri-and-their-balvihar-education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of what Hindu kids are told we have, they will discover later that that all the beliefs they have heard and been taught about, everything about the Ten Commandments and the manifestations of the &amp;lsquo;brahman&amp;rsquo;, and so on are based on stories. They will discover too that these gods of their, these &amp;lsquo;manifestations&amp;rsquo; of Brahman, display immoral and disgusting behaviors: like incest, adultery, lying, cheating, murder, and so on and so forth. They will discover furthermore that there is no theology worth speaking of in the Indian traditions, and they will become one deeply ashamed Indian if they come across the Christian evangelicals or writers like the future Kripals or Courtrights. Their training (in Balvihar) will have set them up as an easy target for conversion into a Christianity or Islam (if (s)he remains &amp;lsquo;religious&amp;rsquo;).If not, they might grow up to loathe the tradition they are part of. They will not have been provided with the weapons they need in order to survive a theological discussion about the nature of &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuity of NRIs and their symbolic interpretations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:34:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vacuity-of-nris-and-their-symbolic-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vyasa&amp;rsquo;s argument (to the extent we can speak of an argument in this context) is quite subtle: When Urvasi comes to Arjuna at the behest of his father, and when she is possessed by desire, and when the Apsaras choose freely and unconfined, then (a) one cannot reject her; (b) and with the argument that she is a superior to him. If you split this conjunction and cast in normative terms, it says something like this: (a) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when one&amp;rsquo;s father indicates that a son should sleep with a woman; (b) Rejection of a woman is not permitted when the woman is sexually attracted to oneself; (c) Rejection of a woman, whoever she might be, is not permitted when she chooses freely and without confines. Because such a rejection is triply prohibited (or forbidden), Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s argument that he &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the parent of his race (which has only one prohibition) possesses less value. So, Urvasi is justified in her curse of Arjuna. In other words, if we read this fragment of Mahabharata in normative terms, Arjuna was wrong in not having an incestuous relationship with one of his great-great-grandparents.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1&amp;rsquo;. While one could argue that one &amp;lsquo;ought not&amp;rsquo; to sleep with the &amp;lsquo;superiors&amp;rsquo;, Urvasi suggests that because she has chosen freely, this argument is void. On top of saying why Arjuna is wrong to reject sleeping with her, she also comes up with two other reasons why he could sleep with her: (a) Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s ancestors have done so and without committing any &amp;lsquo;sin&amp;rsquo;; therefore, it is &amp;lsquo;permissible&amp;rsquo; that he does the same; (b)  it is a morally good thing to emulate one&amp;rsquo;s ancestors and therefore Arjuna &amp;lsquo;ought to&amp;rsquo; sleep with her.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indian culture’s attitude toward sex vs. Christian Morality</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-cultures-attitude-toward-sex-vs-christian-morality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 07:14:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/indian-cultures-attitude-toward-sex-vs-christian-morality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let us begin with the assumption that our stories about Indra and the Gandharvas are just that: stories, authored by human beings, without truth-content. (That is to say, they are neither true nor false.) When human beings write stories, their imagination is (partially) constrained by their societies, cultures and the times they live in. None quite knows how exactly the latter constrain human imagination even though the extant theories about myths try to explicate this relation: some see in them a mirroring of society, some see in them a disguised historiography or sociology, some see in them a personification of virtues, and so on. Because this issue is not settled yet, I shall presuppose the truth of none of the theories about myths that dot the landscape. However, I take the &amp;lsquo;constraint&amp;rsquo; I spoke about to incorporate the following minimal claim: the myths suggest that some attitudes fall within the limits (or transgress them, as the case may be) of the cultures whose myths they are. Under this assumption, let me isolate some of the attitudes that come to the fore if we look at our stories about apsaras.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Victorian morality of NRI and middle class Hindus: Prostitution, Adultery</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 05:53:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/victorian-morality-of-nri-and-middle-class-hindus-prostitution-adultery/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1.1. The Indian traditions did not have the same attitude as Christianity towards prostitution or adultery. And the Indians of yesteryears were not defenders of the Victorian (and Christian) morality. Of course, I approvingly said that the &amp;ldquo;Indians are not prudes&amp;rdquo; but this approval has to do with the thrust of Indian thought, as I have understood it: the impossibility of prohibiting or making obligatory some or another action universally. (This is my formulation, of course.) I do believe that the Indians recognized the impossibility of abolishing prostitution (which is why it is called &amp;ldquo;the oldest profession&amp;rdquo;). Instead, therefore, of banning and condemning prostitution (and subsequently turn a blind eye towards its existence), Indian thinkers suggested that we treat the prostitutes humanely. I have never been to a prostitute nor will I ever go to one; but that does not mean that I want to ignore their existence and treat them as non-humans. Nor am I willing to call all those who visit prostitutes as criminals and perverts. I know of too many lonely men and women who have found human warmth and personal comfort in the arms and companionship of prostitutes to consider them as perverts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
