<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Paul Courtright on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/paul-courtright/</link><description>Recent content in Paul Courtright on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/paul-courtright/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why Social sciences are not providing knowledge, including the likes of Wendy Doniger and her children?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 22:08:03 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/why-social-sciences-are-not-providing-knowledge-including-the-likes-of-wendy-doniger-and-her-children/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general pattern that has come to the fore is that Wendy and her children (including Jeffrey Kripal) &lt;em&gt;systematically&lt;/em&gt; portray the Indian traditions in an unfavorable light, even when compared to how religions like Christianity, Islam and Judaism are portrayed. This claim is made in several articles, independent of whether these religions and the Indian traditions are true or false, whether they are irrational or rational, and so on. The discussion is not about the truth-claims of these religions and traditions but about their depictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Negative portrayals of non-Western Cultures like Indian: Secularization of Christianity – S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 04:59:02 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/negative-portrayals-of-non-western-cultures-like-indian-secularization-of-christianity-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I want to raise three issues: (a) how to analyze what Rajiv portrays about Wendy and her children in the field of religious studies; (b) depending on that, what an adequate response consists of. Before we do either (this is one of the things I have discovered through my own research during the last two decades), we need to be clear about (c) how we &lt;em&gt;should not&lt;/em&gt; analyze this situation. Given that all three (in their general form) have been my obsessions, I have been reflecting on them deeply, seriously and systematically for some time now. I would like to share some of the results of this reflection. In the first part, I will take a (rather slow) run up to tackling the third issue first. And even here, I look at RISA &lt;em&gt;lila&lt;/em&gt; as an exemplification of a more general issue or as an expression of a much broader tendency.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>