<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Gita on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/gita/</link><description>Recent content in Gita on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 13:41:52 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/tags/gita/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Enlightenment by Grace or Efforts or Birth?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-by-grace-or-efforts/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 13:41:52 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/enlightenment-by-grace-or-efforts/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9.32 Bhagavadgita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;māṃ hi pārtha vyapāśritya
ye &amp;lsquo;pi syuḥ pāpayonayaḥ
striyo vaiśyāstathā śūdrās
te&amp;rsquo; pi yānti parāṃ gatim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation is a bit more complex. The word &amp;lsquo;yoni&amp;rsquo; here does much more work than one assumes. All the four are born from &amp;lsquo;Yoni&amp;rsquo; but yet are distinguished in terms of punya and paapa. The last two are earnt by the organism in question: &amp;lsquo;svayaarjita&amp;rsquo;, suggesting that being a brahmana and a rajarshi are earnt titles. As against it, we have a gender and a shudra. &lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Psychological Traits and Enlightenment: Ignorance and Knowledge</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ignorance-knowledge-psychological-traits-and-enlightenment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 21:30:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ignorance-knowledge-psychological-traits-and-enlightenment/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;About the relationship between scientific knowledge and enlightenment: If every human being can become enlightened (at any time, place or culture), it logically follows that some or another hypothesis about the world cannot be a requirement to become enlightened. People were enlightened (in the past) without possessing knowledge that humankind has today; one can become enlightened without being a physicist or a geneticist; one can believe in the existence of ghosts and spirits and still be enlightened… and so on. In the same way one can seek and find enlightenment while believing that human body is composed of five sheaths, one can also become enlightened by dismissing the idea of five sheaths as a false and primitive belief. There is, however, a caveat that ties knowledge to enlightenment. Perhaps, a contemporary example would help here.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to go about developing an alternative to the so-called social sciences? -- S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-go-about-developing-an-alternative-to-the-so-called-social-sciences-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 07:07:51 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-go-about-developing-an-alternative-to-the-so-called-social-sciences-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I would like you to consider the following four &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of answers, each pitched at a different level of generality and at a different level of description. One could provide more, but these four should be enough to give a &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt; of the kind of wine you might care to drink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose that one were to ask you: how to go about doing &amp;lsquo;science&amp;rsquo; (in general) or, say, doing &amp;lsquo;physics&amp;rsquo;? What kind of an answer could you possibly give? If you do not want to be unkind, you will probably give answers that will not be satisfying to the questioner. Like what? May be you will say: one needs to read, think about a problem, provide a solution and critically evaluate the hypothetical answer and so on. If the questioner presses his point and asks: yes, but &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; does one go about doing any of these, what will your answer be? The only reasonable answer you can give him is to point him in the direction of a &lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt;: go, read that book on physics, you will perhaps say, and then you have an idea of what I am talking about.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>