<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jeffrey Kripal on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/jeffrey-kripal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jeffrey Kripal on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 04:56:05 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/jeffrey-kripal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Does Kripal have an agenda?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 04:56:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do understand the anger that people feel when they read Jeffrey Kripal&amp;rsquo;s and other people&amp;rsquo;s assessment of Indian traditions. If someone were to come up with a similar distortion of my own cultural heritage, I would probably feel the same. However, I do feel troubled when people end up calling Kripal a &amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;ldquo;spiritual bandit&amp;rdquo; or begin to speculate about hidden &amp;lsquo;agendas&amp;rsquo;. My problem is not that these accusations are ad hominem. My problem is that they threaten to obscure a genuine intellectual problem of a more serious nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about people and their cultures?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:53:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us begin in a very intuitive way and ask ourselves this question: where do we encounter &amp;lsquo;cultural differences&amp;rsquo;? In human contacts, of course. What kind of human contacts? &lt;em&gt;In inter-individual contacts&lt;/em&gt;. That is, we see (or sense, or intuit or whatever) cultural differences in our contacts with &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; human beings. You do not meet &amp;rsquo;the western culture&amp;rsquo; but individual Americans, Germans, French, etc. Neither do these individuals meet &amp;rsquo;the Indian culture&amp;rsquo;: they meet individual Indians (or, even better, a &amp;lsquo;Madrasi Brahmin&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;lsquo;Gujerati Baniya&amp;rsquo; - even these are general categories but I use them just to get the point across.) And yet, we appear to see cultural differences in these contacts. How to make &amp;lsquo;sense&amp;rsquo; of &lt;em&gt;this experience&lt;/em&gt;? Let us first see what is partially involved to truly appreciate the complexity of our &amp;lsquo;perception&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. Each individual human being is a complex combination of at least four aspects. There is his biological (or genetic) inheritance; there is his &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; inheritance (whether he is from the Middle Ages or from a capitalist society); there is his psychological makeup (let us say his &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;); and there is his cultural upbringing (whether he is a Madhva Brahmin or a Lingayat, say). When we meet individuals, in many different ways we notice these &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt;: the biological, the psychological and, after some time perhaps, &amp;rsquo;the social&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the cultural&amp;rsquo;. Let us bracket the biological away so that the situation becomes deliciously complex. Let us agree to use the following &amp;lsquo;words&amp;rsquo; (they are just words for now) in order to go ahead and raise the problem. Let us call the &amp;lsquo;social aspects&amp;rsquo; of a person the &amp;lsquo;sociality&amp;rsquo; of the person; the psychological aspects the &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo; of the person; and the &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; aspects the &amp;lsquo;culturality&amp;rsquo; of the person. Thus we meet individual human beings and see the differences between ourselves and the other human beings. What kinds of differences do we see?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
