<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Michael Witzel on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/michael-witzel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Michael Witzel on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 May 2012 19:16:48 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/tags/michael-witzel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Intellectual prowess of Michael Witzel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intellectual-prowess-of-michael-witzel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2012 19:16:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intellectual-prowess-of-michael-witzel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I would have liked to make the following points on the IER forum but either of the two moderators are (obviously) willing to be courteous enough to post my letter on their forum, despite my explicit request. Let me react to their letters on this forum, and I shall leave it there for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Neither Michael Witzel nor Steve Farmer answers my request for clarifications but simply take off on polemical tones. I do not see what purpose is thereby served. Globally speaking, both their letters seem to indicate that they are convinced that either I am aligned with the Hindutva movement or that I am a Hindutva man myself or both. Of course, because we have not met each other so far, there is only one way for them to divine my political preferences: through my writings. Witzel claims that he has read them, whereas Farmer keeps silent about the issue. It is a matter of public record that I claim that &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; (as a &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;) does not exist in India. Consequently, from my writings on the subject, no one can accuse me of supporting a stance that wants to found India on &amp;lsquo;hinduness&amp;rsquo; or on &amp;lsquo;hindudom&amp;rsquo; or on &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; (whether conceived as a &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; or called as &amp;lsquo;sanatana dharma&amp;rsquo;). So, from where could anyone draw conclusion that these two have drawn?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following possibility: let us assume that in some of my writings, I reach the same conclusion as some or another ideologue from Hindutva. (Of course, neither Farmer nor Witzel shows that this is the case. But that is not the issue.) In other words, let us assume that, with respect to some or another issue, I arrive at the same conclusion as people from the Hinudtva movement do. The question is: what does that indicate, or prove or is an evidence for? After all, Witzel, Farmer and others reach the same conclusion as the Hindutva people do, when you ask them about the sum of two integers (say adding two to itself); or (assuming the presence of relevant There is only one answer possible in this case: there exists a unique theory (&amp;rsquo;the Hindutva theory&amp;rsquo;) from which one can derive certain conclusions. It is not possible to derive the same conclusion from any other theory that we know (or can invent). Consequently, one can argue backwards: if someone, anyone, supports a specific conclusion (&amp;rsquo;the Hindutva conclusion&amp;rsquo;) then that is because such a conclusion is derivable only from the &amp;lsquo;Hindutva theory&amp;rsquo;. Only a fool could entertain making such a claim today, if ever. Assuming that Witzel and Farmer are not fools, they appear reasonably intelligent to me, how then could they &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; Hindutva in my writings? A more charitable assumption would be: Witzel either has not read my writings (he lies when he says he has) or has not understood them at all (which makes him dim witted). Choose your poison.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What makes one an intellectual?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 06:51:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steve Farmer is not an expert on secularism only in the sense that he has followed it from the &amp;lsquo;outside&amp;rsquo; (meaning, probably, he has not written anything about the issue himself). Apparently, the reason why he has not contributed to the debate has to do with the fact that (a) no legitimate researcher can take the debate seriously; and (b) Farmer is one such. Witness how he describes it: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched this so-called debate for nearly a decade now from the outside, and nothing whatsoever has changed. Nor have I ever met a single legitimate researcher who took it seriously.&amp;rdquo; I wish some of the Indian intellectuals who have participated in the debate would read this judgment and digest what Farmer thinks of them. They will be thrilled to know that they are &amp;lsquo;illegitimate&amp;rsquo; scholars!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Patrick Hogan’s &#39;Why Hindus should be grateful to Wendy Doniger&#39;—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:04:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Patrick Hogan,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is jolly good of you, as the British say, to contribute to the &amp;rsquo;literary landscapes&amp;rsquo; column in Sulekha at this particular juncture. I am glad too that you put across some thoughtful considerations without being polemical, and that can only help generate a stimulating discussion among all the concerned parties. However, the way you frame your points make the task an exercise in walking on a tight rope.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
