<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Knowledge on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/knowledge/</link><description>Recent content in Knowledge on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 08:47:12 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/knowledge/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to read Gita?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-read-gita/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2024 08:47:12 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-read-gita/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you insist that without situating Gita in the massive text that Mahabharata is, we cannot understand or interpret Gita, then you provide such a gigantic &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt;-text to the 18 chapters that the Gita is, and because a move like this can only give interpretations of a small text by situating in such a huge &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt;-text, any and almost every interpretation can become valid or acceptable or permissible. We will have on our hands a plethora of interpretations, many in conflict with the other, so that we cannot even decide whether there is even one or some interpretation(s) that is (are) better than the other. We end up formulating an impossible problem: which interpretation to choose and why? We cannot appeal to the implicit goal present in text interpretations, viz., consistency and completeness nor to criterion like coherence (because it is unclear what coherence would consist of in this case).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you ask the following question instead: which other texts (that is, &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt;-texts) do we need to read and understand the two articles on relativity? We do need background knowledge to draw some possible implications from these articles, but what &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt;-texts do we need? Which con-texts are needed to study Feynman’s Lectures, or Darwin’s origin or similar works in the natural sciences? Some knowledge is required; some skills are necessary; we must be able to read a natural language, etc., but these are not &lt;em&gt;con&lt;/em&gt;-texts but requirements to acquire knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose further that you see the Gita as a text that imparts knowledge. (I will leave out the question what that knowledge could be.) Suppose too that there are prerequisites to acquire this knowledge, as is the case with knowledge. And that we can evaluate and judge the Gita as knowledge as well. Which insurmountable problem does such an approach create? One might not be able to read the Gita and acquire the knowledge it imparts by just knowing a natural language. However, that would apply to all knowledge, would it not? You will not understand the relativity theories just because you can read those articles in, say, the original or in a faithful translation. A popular commentary that ‘explains’ these papers will not make you a physicist either. What hinders us from looking at the Gita this way? What objections are there for such an approach?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In fact, if you look at most claims made about the Gita (Sen, Doniger, Danto, etc.), you notice that they look at the Gita either as a literary text, or as a quasi-moral or philosophical text, or as a religious text etc. I have not come across a single interpretation of even the first chapter of the Gita that goes beyond these approaches and almost all of them tell the same story: Arjuna was despondent or felt extremely sad that he must kill (his relatives) on the battlefield and the 17 chapters of the Gita are there to ‘comfort’ him. How do they do so? The acts and consequences story is one answer. Here are my naïve questions: why write 17 chapters just to say ‘karmanyevadhikaraste…’? After all, this thought is exactly one verse long and, in fact, it is written out in the Gita. What do the other verses do? How, exactly, do these 17 chapters ‘comfort’ Arjuna and ‘therapeutically’ cure his despondency? I have not read anyone either raising these questions or answering them. (I confess that I have not read many commentaries. I am glad about this.) How does the fourth chapter (on Jnanyoga) answer any of the questions that Arjuna raises in the first chapter; what are the answers to those questions; and how exactly do these answers remove Arjuna’s despondency?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Such and many other questions arise if and only if you do not see the Gita as a literary, moral, philosophical, or religious text. If you see it as a knowledge text, these and many more questions arise to which the Gita attempts to give an answer. If one takes such an approach, I see its con-&lt;em&gt;text&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;adding&lt;/em&gt; (in some of the Parvas) explications, clarifications and reasonings that are present in extremely abbreviated forms in the Gita.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description></item><item><title>Accessing knowledge through past theories</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/past-theories-and-knowledge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 21:22:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/past-theories-and-knowledge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You raise the question whether using earlier theories, which are &lt;em&gt;superseded&lt;/em&gt; by newer theories, one can (or even could ever) access knowledge? (I am not a physicist, but I do not think that physicists have junked Newtonian theories. I think that Newtonian physics retains its validity in the macroworld we live in and is not considered false. As far as I remember, I have not come across writings that claim that Newton’s theory is false but that most of its consequences (but not all) are derivable in Einsteinian theory, under some ‘limiting conditions’ (like mass remaining invariant, etc.) Anyway, I do not know enough Physics to enter a discussion about it. Arun and Kannan are more competent here than I am.) If we do not get stuck on any one example, it appears to me that there are three questions here: (a) Could defective, incomplete, partial theories help us access knowledge?; (b) Could false, or partially false and partially true, theories help us access knowledge?; (c) Was knowledge ever accessed by past theories, which, as we know today, expressed ignorance?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Solving vs dissolving problems</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/solving-vs-dissolving-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 17:05:23 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/solving-vs-dissolving-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the examples you refer to, you touch on an approach to situations and problems that are Indian (in the sense of culture) contrasted to which stands another culture’s way of dealing with situations. The simplest way to explicate this difference in a general way, using your examples as a reference point, would be this: when we speak of problems and solutions, there are two ways of looking at them. In the first, an existing problem gets &lt;em&gt;resolved&lt;/em&gt;: both the problem and its solution continue to exist (both in memory and in records) in their forms of appearance. They have their independent existence even though they are conceptually (and chronologically) linked to each other. That is, a problem does not ‘disappear’ after its resolution; the solution retains its status (as a solution to a particular problem) as does the problem. This is how the West looks at problems and their resolution (mostly). This is also how we think scientifically. To put it in the form of a slogan, which has its own limitations: a situation is transformed into a theoretical problem.
In human situations (i.e., situations involving human conflicts and difficulties), the above approach is &lt;em&gt;damaging&lt;/em&gt;. In the Indian way, which is geared and focused on human situations, the event (or the situation) is turned into a &lt;em&gt;practical problem&lt;/em&gt;. In such cases, the solutions &lt;em&gt;dissolve&lt;/em&gt; the problem. Neither the problem nor the solution has any existence thereafter because the &lt;em&gt;dissolution of the problem creates a new situation&lt;/em&gt;. The memory and the records of this act, which transformed one situation into another, will exist but in their status as &lt;em&gt;changed states&lt;/em&gt;: a memory or a record of how a state-change occurred because of a set of actions.
When the first way is used to deal with human problems, psychologically speaking, a trauma is ‘left behind’. In the second case, what you undergo in the world gets structured as an experience and this is what a human being accumulates over the course of its life. In a very general sense, again in the form of a slogan, a situation is made into a practical problem.
It appears to me that in situations of uncertainty and imperfect information, the second approach is better of the two. Even if a solution might not have been the best (speaking from hindsight), it enables a human being to continue to live as well as situations possibly allow. In the first approach, you continue to live as a crippled human being haunted by one or multiple traumas. (Because in ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ these ideas are treated in greater detail, I will not elaborate further on these here.) The general Indian approach to, say, rape, would then be contrasted with how Indian (and western) feminists speak of rape using a legal and a western language. Abortion would also be an illustration: the examples you give would then be contrasted with how the issue is ‘debated’ in the US.
Now, to the issue you raise. Is the Indian route moral and ethical? If you follow how the West has thought on morality and ethics (especially in the last 200 years or more), the answer is in the negative. This is how our intellectuals and semi-intellectuals &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt;: with the greatest possible ignorance about what the West says and about what ethics is, they reproduce their words. Moral/immoral, just/unjust, ethical/unethical, and so on. Even though most would not be able to explain what a moral obligation is or what a moral forbiddance is, they hold forth a moralizing discourse defending atrocious policies, laws, and attitudes. Those who follow the Indian way are intellectually incapable of saying or thinking coherently about their ethics: they spout what they ‘think’ Shastras say and what, according to whatever takes their fancy at the moment, dharma and adharma are. In short: all the moral talk and ethical theories in the West has only produced the most immoral civilization that humankind has the misfortune to live under. A truly humane and reasonable approach to the human predicament has generated the biggest bunch of morons that the world has ever produced in recent times, who parade their utter ignorance as knowledge.
When you formulate the above issue as a question, “pregnancy and abortion are very practical affairs - emotional yes, but not moral or ethical. Is this a right way to think about it?” the answer cannot be unambiguous. Yes, it is a moral and ethical issue &lt;em&gt;because it is a practical issue&lt;/em&gt;. Ethics and morality are practical issues par excellence: but one who talks about it (the West) has made this issue theoretical whereas the other (India) who acts in a practical way does not know how to talk about it. One is bloated with an insufferable pretention and the other is bloated with absolute ignorance. But both ply their trade on the market fighting for customers.
In simple terms: we must try to think and articulate how human issues are practical and ethical and thus live without traumas dominating our lives. A task for the millennials and the Z-generation, I suppose.
For more, read &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Who needs a world view&amp;rdquo; (&lt;/a&gt;esp 3.5 &amp;amp; 6.3)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Narrowing the search space, Ill-formed questions</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narrowing-the-search-space-ill-posed-questions/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 14:22:14 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/narrowing-the-search-space-ill-posed-questions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Assume that you get a Ph.D student who wants to do medical research. He comes to you and tells you that he wants to find out an answer to the burning question about why people get sick. Would you be able to guide this student in answering his question or give one answer to it? Your answer would be: it depends. You would also further say to him, ‘choose a particular disease, choose a particular domain and choose a particular approach within that domain, if you want to do research’. There is no ‘one answer’ to his question. As a research question, you would say it is ill-formed: you have to specify the disease, and choose whether you want to do, say, genetic research or epidemiological research or cell research or…&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Knowledge and Bullshit about Daffodil</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shock-and-awe-of-enlightenment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 15:38:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/shock-and-awe-of-enlightenment/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;To help you think through the problem you &amp;ldquo;whether Christians can get enlightened&amp;rdquo;, try using this analogy. Something, let us call it ‘daffodil’, fascinates us. Let us also assume that a great deal of concern and interest is expressed about it. Consider two scenarios now, each of which testifies to our fascination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first scenario is this. There is versification (call it ‘poetry’) and ‘embodiment’ (paintings and sculptures) of ‘daffodil’; imaginative eulogies (novels) and intimidating discourses (‘philosophy’) about ‘daffodil’ abound, etc. These classifications are based on our understanding of what art, poetry, philosophy etc. are. There are also many collations of fragmentary sentences that appear to violate metres of poetry or styles of prose. They are revered as revolutionary breakthroughs (made by the heroes of the ‘masses’ transgressing such elitist notions like ‘grammar’, ‘style’, etc.) that are ‘blinding in their beauty’. In short, there is a huge collection of material about ‘daffodil’.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Colonial Consciousness and Enlightenment</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2017 15:31:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/colonial-consciousness-and-enlightenment/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This post will use an imagery as its organising thread, which tracks the search for enlightenment in terms of notions known to us from our secondary and higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we consider the search for happiness in these terms, then the ideas expressed &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/tattvadarshi-gyaani-and-bullshitter/"&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; could be reformulated thus: as human beings, almost all of us would like to be literates or would like to have a primary education. This is the move ‘away’ for unhappiness that all of us aim at, namely, to be ‘less unhappy’. After a period of time, many of us would like to move further. This is the move ‘towards’ (peace of mind, contentment, satisfied, etc.) happiness now formulated in positive terms: the phase of secondary education. The completion of this process is to reach a state of peace (shanti), or contentment (samadhana), or satisfaction (trupti) etc. The Sri Sri’s and the Sadguru’s of this world help us here through their Sudarshan Kriya’s, their yogic practices, their meditative courses and so on. The vipassana meditation, the Satsangh’s, the bhajans, the dhyaanas etc. are also situated here. Some people in this phase also call themselves Saadhakas, doing their ‘saadhana’ on a very regular basis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose that you want to go further and, therefore, seek higher education (call it Ananda, or happiness). There are two broad routes here: technical or vocational education is one route; university education is another. If you want to be plumber, a carpenter, a sculptor, a painter, a machinist…then you are better-off choosing technical education. However, you could also go for a university education. There is no ‘higher’ or ‘lower’ here; both are different forms of higher education. (Of course, there are endless discussions about ‘superiority’: one group disparagingly calls the other ‘vocational training’, while the other caricatures the first as ‘purely theoretical’ that is unsuited for fulfilling the ‘need’ for useful education or the ‘needs’ of society.) A society cannot survive without plumbers, electricians, machinists, artists, etc. Nor can it live without the ‘ivory tower’ that universities are and should be. Individual students make their choice based on multiple reasons (from aptitude to financial rewards) and many gifted teachers prefer to teach in vocational or professional schools than in a university. However, whatever the choice, both demand that the student specifies clearly what s/he wants to learn: do you want to be a sculptor or a machinist; in which subject do you want  your bachelor and Master’s degree? ‘Ananda’, the generic word, does not suffice here because it merely picks out ‘higher education’: do you want to do physics or chemistry or biology or English literature at the university? ‘Gyaana marga’ (the university) on the one hand and ‘other routes’ (vocational and professional training) on the other hand are the main avenues in higher education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the framework of this imagery, ‘enlightenment’ refers to the total process of ‘higher education’ and ‘seeking ananda’ fixes the goal of higher education. Each avenue has its way of classifying its internal levels or divisions (Bachelors, Masters, Doctoral, Post-doctoral in the university, for example) and teaches students accordingly. They share many commonalities: the subject matter, the instruments, the theoretical frameworks, etc. etc. They are also different from each other in ways of teaching, investigating, making and reporting discoveries, and so on. The names of some teachers in higher education are known to us: Buddha, Shankara, Ramanuja, Madhva, Vallabha, Ramakrishna Paramahamsa, Ramana, Nisargadatta Maharaj, etc. Let us not deal with the question whether they taught at the University or were active in professional or technical education because something else of greater importance has to be noticed: you have to choose the ‘subject’ of higher education first. ‘Seeking Happiness’ or ‘wanting enlightenment’ are not adequate at all. You need to specifiy what you are seeking and, preferably, why.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bullshit: True Sentences and Trivialization of Knowledge</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 16:50:22 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/bullshit-true-sentences-and-knowledge-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Why understanding bullshit is important?  Three reasons: (a) there is a very frequent use of the word ‘bullshit’ (mostly in my posts); (b) bullshit has been tied directly to truth in the literature on the subject, (c) far more important is the fact that it is much more connected to &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt; than has so far been acknowledged. In this post, the focus is on the third reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, an ‘autobiographical’ point: I was charmed by how Akeel Bilgrami spoke about ‘bullshit’, when we met each other for the first time. Akeel also said that we call this ‘bakwas’ in Hindi. This resulted in revisiting &lt;a href="http://www2.csudh.edu/ccauthen/576f12/frankfurt__harry_-_on_bullshit.pdf"&gt;Harry Frankfurt’s article on the issue&lt;/a&gt;; it further led to reading the late &lt;a href="http://www.ditext.com/cohen/Cohen.pdf"&gt;G.A. Cohen’s contribution on the topic&lt;/a&gt; and going through most of the literature on the subject. (Some interesting stuff on the theme is collected in &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bullshit-Philosophy-Guaranteed-Perfect-Results/dp/0812696115"&gt;an edited volume&lt;/a&gt; on the subject that was published a few years ago.) Since then, some on and off thinking on the subject has been going on, some of whose results you shall notice in this post.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Gettier Problem, Doxa, and Episteme</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/gettier-problem-doxa-and-episteme/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 01:22:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/gettier-problem-doxa-and-episteme/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The Ancient (and modern) philosophers make the distinction between beliefs that are merely opinions of individuals and beliefs that are knowledge claims. Today, when modern philosophers speak of ‘doxastic coherence’ about the Greek thinkers, they do not merely mean that there should be a coherence in beliefs but also that Ancient philosophers have not produced knowledge but merely express opinions. Some also believe that all philosophy is mere ‘doxa’ but not ‘episteme’. The problem is this: what distinguishes a ‘doxastic’ sentence from an ‘epistemic’ sentence? One possibility was to say that ‘episteme’ was ‘justified true belief’ and not just a ‘mere belief’. This collapsed following the Gettier paradox which shows that this definition of ‘knowledge’ does not distinguish between mere opinion and knowledge. Today, one uses ‘doxastic coherence’ not as a technical term but as a judgement either about knowledge or about Greek thinkers or both or to signal that one thinks everything is an opinion. If one does not signal any of these, it is jargon.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Psychological Traits and Enlightenment: Ignorance and Knowledge</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ignorance-knowledge-psychological-traits-and-enlightenment/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 21:30:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ignorance-knowledge-psychological-traits-and-enlightenment/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;About the relationship between scientific knowledge and enlightenment: If every human being can become enlightened (at any time, place or culture), it logically follows that some or another hypothesis about the world cannot be a requirement to become enlightened. People were enlightened (in the past) without possessing knowledge that humankind has today; one can become enlightened without being a physicist or a geneticist; one can believe in the existence of ghosts and spirits and still be enlightened… and so on. In the same way one can seek and find enlightenment while believing that human body is composed of five sheaths, one can also become enlightened by dismissing the idea of five sheaths as a false and primitive belief. There is, however, a caveat that ties knowledge to enlightenment. Perhaps, a contemporary example would help here.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to speak for the Indian traditions: an agenda for the future--SN Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-speak-for-the-indian-traditions-an-agenda-for-the-future/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 05:56:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-speak-for-the-indian-traditions-an-agenda-for-the-future/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: This article appeared in the Journal of American Academy of Religion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper attempts a contrast between the process and the structure of the Christian and the Indian spirituality. Drawing attention to their dissimilarities, it attempts to reformulate the differences among the Indian traditions in a novel way. It argues that cultures and traditions are not just different; but that they differ from each other in different ways as well. The future of religious studies, it is suggested, is dependent on developing the ability to develop new ways of describing the differences between cultures and traditions. This is the agenda for the future. As a correlate to this task, the paper suggests that we replace the question &amp;ldquo;who speaks &amp;lsquo;for&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;about&amp;rsquo; a religion?&amp;rdquo; with a more pregnant and a more accurate reformulation: &amp;ldquo;how to speak for a religion in the Academy?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to access Indian traditions?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-access-indian-traditions/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 07:08:38 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-access-indian-traditions/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have often said, the most intriguing aspect of the Indian culture is the kind of knowledge it produced and encouraged people to produce: experiential knowledge which emerges by systematically reflecting on our (human) experiences in the world. As human beings, our experiences are many: no one set, no one kind of experience exhausts what we go through. From the purely personal experiences of the world (our ambitions, hopes, dreams, frustrations, etc) to the entirely social ones (the experiences of sorrow and injustice that other human beings in the world experience). So, knowledge that reflects on or thinks about and systematizes such experiences presupposes multiple learning sites, many diverse perspectives and varied kinds of intellectual skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Does Feynman know about his culture?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-feynman-know-about-his-culture/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2011 08:15:46 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/does-feynman-know-about-his-culture/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Paraphrasing Feynman: &amp;ldquo;the answers proposed like counting angels that can dance on the head of a pin are trivial.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not in the least impressed by (in fact, I am disgusted by and contemptuous about) the attitude of the likes of Feynman. Here is one reason why: I too have a criticism of (some) social sciences and (some) aspects of the western philosophy. I too consider that some of these social sciences are not sciences in any sense of the term. But that is because I believe that some of these disciplines endlessly embroider theology and I feel that my research might go someway in setting the situation straight. In other words, as far as I am concerned, the current state of social science is a problem which requires to be addressed seriously. The reason for the seriousness must be obvious: we &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; to urgently understand the nature of human beings in all its facets, if we have to survive as a species. Making fun of philosophy and social sciences is one thing; to do something about it is entirely different.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Foundationalism and Virtuous Circularity</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 04:49:31 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You do not want to call our natural sciences as &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo;. I do not even mind that. (For instance, you might want to define &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; as &amp;rsquo;true and justified belief&amp;rsquo;. You might show me that our theories in natural sciences are only believed to be true and are not proved to be true. Therefore, you might want to say that our natural sciences are not &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; according to your definition. Fair enough.) Since you want to conduct a discussion about knowledge and if our sciences are not examples of knowledge, I need to know whether there are other examples of knowledge. If such an entity exists, our discussions make sense. If we have no examples of knowledge at all, according to some or another definition of the word, how could we discuss about that? I mean to say, if not even the logics we use in out argument is an example of knowledge, how could we ever have any discussion about the scope, range, etc. of knowledge? We cannot. In other words, if we want to have discussions about knowledge, we need to have examples of knowledge and need to use these examples in our discussions about their nature. So, you have to tell me: (a) whether we have examples of knowledge; (b) what they are; (c) how we should use them in our discussions; (d) show that their use does not pervert our discussions about knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Presumption of Knowledge—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/presumption-of-knowledge-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:32:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/presumption-of-knowledge-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The first striking thing is their &lt;em&gt;presumption of knowledge&lt;/em&gt; at several levels. Yet, they display abysmal ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(a) Christianity has not just had a two thousand years&amp;rsquo; history. It has also had two thousand years of doctrinal development. In the latter, every notion that has been employed here has been &lt;em&gt;continuously&lt;/em&gt; discussed, refined, contested and so on. Their meanings, as they apply to Christianity&amp;rsquo;s self-description, has seeped into and determined what they mean in the English language. Not only words like &amp;lsquo;Christ&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Church&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Worship&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;idol&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;revelation&amp;rsquo; and so on but also issues like &amp;lsquo;Who is a Christian&amp;rsquo;? (&lt;em&gt;Quid sit Christianum esse?&lt;/em&gt;) The discussions hardly exhibit any knowledge of either the richness or complexity of these matters; yet, they express the firm conviction that what is there to be known is also known. In matters of knowledge, this combination is deadly.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to produce knowledge about “Who is a Christian”—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:27:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine that I were to say the following: Christ and &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; are manifestations of the same divinity; Christ came about 2000 years ago in the Middle East, whereas &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; is how he has appeared in India some 4000 years ago. Now no one can forbid me from saying this and &lt;em&gt;calling myself a Christian&lt;/em&gt;. Question: what should a theory about Christianity do? Show &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; anyone who decides to call himself a &amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo; is, in fact, also a Christian? In that case, all such a &amp;rsquo;theory&amp;rsquo; can do is say something like the following: anyone who calls himself some name (&amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Democrat&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Marxist&amp;rsquo;, etc) is also whatever he calls himself. Such an attitude simply ends up making any knowledge of society and human beings impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Knowledge and objectivity</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/knowledge-and-objectivity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:39:53 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/knowledge-and-objectivity/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Assuming that our theories in Physics are not false, would there be gravitational force in the Cosmos (or on our planet) whether or not there was a theory about it? This is the question about the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;objectivity&amp;rsquo; of our theories. If we say &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;, I do not see how one can say the opposite, then the truth or falsity of, say, Aristotelian theory is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; dependent on the &amp;lsquo;consumer&amp;rsquo; of that theory. Of course, once upon a time, people believed it was true but this &amp;lsquo;belief&amp;rsquo; does not &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; Aristotle&amp;rsquo;s theory true. (In Western Europe, people once believed that witches not only exist, but that they also had sexual intercourse with the Devil. There were &amp;rsquo;eye witnesses&amp;rsquo;, who provided graphic descriptions of the sexual organ and sexual prowess of the Devil. We would be hard put to call it &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo; today in Europe or in India around the same time, irrespective of what these people thought then.) That human beings believe different stories to be true, which later turn out to be false, does not make &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; relative to an audience. What it does is to make the belief-in-the-truth-of-a-theory relative to the &amp;lsquo;consumer&amp;rsquo;. This is the issue about the &amp;lsquo;objectivity&amp;rsquo; of theories. That is: could we have theories about human beings and cultures that are &amp;lsquo;objective&amp;rsquo; in this sense? I think so. That is why the discussion with Wendy and her children: they are not producing &lt;em&gt;knowledge&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is every description knowledge?</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-every-description-knowledge/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 08:10:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-every-description-knowledge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let us call the descriptions of what you see &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo;. Are your &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; a contribution to human knowledge? In one sense they are; the way any description of anything by anybody is a &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; and thus knowledge. One needs, and one has, a way of not wanting to call every piece of &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; as knowledge. Hence, we can reformulate the issue: does it contribute towards building a scientific theory of cultural differences? Do your observations in some African country tell us what &lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; their drinking habits and body decorations into a cultural difference? And how these and other differences allow us to say what the &amp;lsquo;African culture&amp;rsquo; is? In other words, not every fact, because it is a fact about people from another culture, is interesting from the point of view of building a scientific theory.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Rain dance superstitious?—Willem Derde</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-rain-dance-superstitious-willem-derde/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 04:00:44 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-rain-dance-superstitious-willem-derde/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Some consider it to be a &amp;ldquo;superstitious practice&amp;rdquo;, the implication being that it is irrational to believe that dancing &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; the rain to fall: no reasonable people on earth can buy the story that dancing actually causes rain to fall. I am not willing to buy it. However, it is a fact that in some cultures people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; perform &amp;lsquo;rain dances&amp;rsquo;. However, to explain the &amp;lsquo;rain dance&amp;rsquo; by attributing a &amp;lsquo;causative story&amp;rsquo; is to trivialize such an experience: &lt;em&gt;you are transforming the members of that group into a bunch of idiots.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to produce knowledge about people and their cultures?—S.N. Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 01:53:12 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-people-and-their-cultures-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let us begin in a very intuitive way and ask ourselves this question: where do we encounter &amp;lsquo;cultural differences&amp;rsquo;? In human contacts, of course. What kind of human contacts? &lt;em&gt;In inter-individual contacts&lt;/em&gt;. That is, we see (or sense, or intuit or whatever) cultural differences in our contacts with &lt;em&gt;individual&lt;/em&gt; human beings. You do not meet &amp;rsquo;the western culture&amp;rsquo; but individual Americans, Germans, French, etc. Neither do these individuals meet &amp;rsquo;the Indian culture&amp;rsquo;: they meet individual Indians (or, even better, a &amp;lsquo;Madrasi Brahmin&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;lsquo;Gujerati Baniya&amp;rsquo; - even these are general categories but I use them just to get the point across.) And yet, we appear to see cultural differences in these contacts. How to make &amp;lsquo;sense&amp;rsquo; of &lt;em&gt;this experience&lt;/em&gt;? Let us first see what is partially involved to truly appreciate the complexity of our &amp;lsquo;perception&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.1. Each individual human being is a complex combination of at least four aspects. There is his biological (or genetic) inheritance; there is his &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; inheritance (whether he is from the Middle Ages or from a capitalist society); there is his psychological makeup (let us say his &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo;); and there is his cultural upbringing (whether he is a Madhva Brahmin or a Lingayat, say). When we meet individuals, in many different ways we notice these &lt;em&gt;differences&lt;/em&gt;: the biological, the psychological and, after some time perhaps, &amp;rsquo;the social&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the cultural&amp;rsquo;. Let us bracket the biological away so that the situation becomes deliciously complex. Let us agree to use the following &amp;lsquo;words&amp;rsquo; (they are just words for now) in order to go ahead and raise the problem. Let us call the &amp;lsquo;social aspects&amp;rsquo; of a person the &amp;lsquo;sociality&amp;rsquo; of the person; the psychological aspects the &amp;lsquo;personality&amp;rsquo; of the person; and the &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; aspects the &amp;lsquo;culturality&amp;rsquo; of the person. Thus we meet individual human beings and see the differences between ourselves and the other human beings. What kinds of differences do we see?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>