<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ritual on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/ritual/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ritual on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 09:47:01 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/ritual/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rituals and their meaninglessness—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/rituals-and-their-meaninglessness-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 09:47:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/rituals-and-their-meaninglessness-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Consider, say, a ritual like sandhyaavandanam. Here are two extremes, when it comes to saying what it is: (a) one goes very deeply into what Mudras mean, which of the mudras occur in this daily ritual; analyses the praanayaama as it is taught; goes into what the Gaayathri mantra really means; and so on. (b) The other extreme is an ordinary Brahmin who performs all the prescribed actions without knowing what any of them mean.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1.1. When asked, they both give their answers: the one tells us of the results of his research and the other simply says: &amp;ldquo;I do not know what any of these mean. I perform them because I have been taught that way.&amp;rdquo; Question: which one of these claims is &lt;em&gt;TRUE&lt;/em&gt;? Further, unless you make a &lt;em&gt;meta-assumption&lt;/em&gt; about the whether or not rituals &lt;em&gt;ought to have&lt;/em&gt; a meaning, you cannot even privilege one story above the other.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of Staal’s Rules Without Meaning –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 06:25:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/review-of-staals-rules-without-meaning-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FRITS STAAL. &lt;em&gt;Rules Without Meaning: Ritual, Mantras and the Human Sciences. Toronto Studies in Religion&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 4. New York and Bern: Peter Lang, 1989 xxii+490.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In order to set the tone of this review article, let me begin straightway with a confession: I have been a closet admirer of Frits Staal ever since I discovered his writings in 1987. The reasons that undergird my attitude are several: firstly, most of his writings are about a culture I am familiar with, namely, India; secondly, absent from them is the dewy-eyed romanticism that is pernicious to any serious study of cultures and people; thirdly, present in them are insights that are immensely important and extremely exciting; fourthly, the theses argued for are the results of absolutely pioneering research which fly in the face of deeply entrenched commonsense wisdom; and so on… He is my fellow-traveler on more tracks than one, and my own thinking on several subjects over the last few years carry the deep imprint of Staal&amp;rsquo;s rigorous thinking and painstaking enquiries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
