<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Natural Sciences on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/natural-sciences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Natural Sciences on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2011 18:40:29 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/natural-sciences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Superstition and rationality</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/superstition-and-rationality/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2011 18:40:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/superstition-and-rationality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the question: &amp;ldquo;why superstition?&amp;rdquo; Our problem lies in circumscribing this notion itself: is it something we should use to characterize beliefs, or attitudes, or theories or actions or all of them? Our linguistic usage allows it mostly of &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; and to the act of believing: to believe that walking under the ladder brings bad; to believe that vampires exist and walk as ordinary humans in the night; to believe in the fairy who watches over you, etc. are all instances of superstition. It also allows us to use it in connection to the truth status of theories like, for instance, the claim that it is superstitious to believe in astrology. However, accepting this usage is not enough: what makes a belief a superstitious belief or an act of believing a superstitious act? It is here that many, many problems come to the fore. One easy way out is to use science and scientific theories as the contrast set: any belief that is not countenanced by the scientific theories of today is a superstitious belief. Of course, this is too broad: on this account, every belief that displaces the current scientific beliefs (i.e., the new scientific theories) becomes superstitious. If you try and circumvent this problem by speaking about &amp;lsquo;scientific theories&amp;rsquo; in the abstract (i.e., do not circumscribe them in time), the danger is that every belief (almost) escapes the net. Just because scientific theories of today do not recognize the existence of ghosts, it does not follow, one could argue, that the sciences of tomorrow cannot recognize the role that mediums play in talking to the spirits of the long departed. You can try and say that all beliefs disproved by science should belong to the set of superstitious beliefs: however, similar problems occur. On top of it, you have the difficulty of saying why one should not have superstitious beliefs. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Religion and Origin of Natural Sciences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/religion-and-origin-of-natural-sciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 22:14:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/religion-and-origin-of-natural-sciences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My proposal addresses itself to the following observation: the natural sciences, &lt;em&gt;as we know them today&lt;/em&gt;, arise in the western culture. What &amp;rsquo;natural sciences&amp;rsquo; mean in the above statement is clarified by other sentences that say, for example, &amp;rsquo;the rest of the world has accepted the western science and technology..&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;we need to learn science and technology form the west..&amp;rsquo; When we make these kinds of statements, what do we have in mind? Do we suggest that we need to learn some scientific formula from the west, or that we have to learn the proof of a theorem from the west? We do not. We are looking at sciences at a different level of abstraction. We are suggesting that there is a &lt;em&gt;way of going about the world&lt;/em&gt; that we need to learn from the west. My hypothesis about science and religion is pitched at this level of abstraction. That is to say, I answer the following question: in which way is the growth of sciences a cultural phenomenon?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
