<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Willem on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/willem/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Willem on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:21:39 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/willem/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vibrancy of Indian traditions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 22:21:39 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/vibrancy-of-indian-traditions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The discussion about re-accessing the vibrancy of the Indian culture and the question whether or not to legislate against conversion, are best treated separately. An answer to the latter does not necessarily count as an answer to the first. In fact, the tendency to counter the proselytising drive of Christianity and Islam by voting laws against conversion is itself an &lt;em&gt;indication&lt;/em&gt; of India’s cultural weakness. Hence, it cannot be a means to re-kindle the flame of India’s pluralistic tradition. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does Kripal have an agenda?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 04:56:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/kripal-does-not-have-an-agenda-nor-is-he-dishonest-willem-derde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do understand the anger that people feel when they read Jeffrey Kripal&amp;rsquo;s and other people&amp;rsquo;s assessment of Indian traditions. If someone were to come up with a similar distortion of my own cultural heritage, I would probably feel the same. However, I do feel troubled when people end up calling Kripal a &amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;, a &amp;ldquo;spiritual bandit&amp;rdquo; or begin to speculate about hidden &amp;lsquo;agendas&amp;rsquo;. My problem is not that these accusations are ad hominem. My problem is that they threaten to obscure a genuine intellectual problem of a more serious nature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Rain dance superstitious?—Willem Derde</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-rain-dance-superstitious-willem-derde/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 04:00:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/is-rain-dance-superstitious-willem-derde/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some consider it to be a &amp;ldquo;superstitious practice&amp;rdquo;, the implication being that it is irrational to believe that dancing &lt;em&gt;causes&lt;/em&gt; the rain to fall: no reasonable people on earth can buy the story that dancing actually causes rain to fall. I am not willing to buy it. However, it is a fact that in some cultures people &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; perform &amp;lsquo;rain dances&amp;rsquo;. However, to explain the &amp;lsquo;rain dance&amp;rsquo; by attributing a &amp;lsquo;causative story&amp;rsquo; is to trivialize such an experience: &lt;em&gt;you are transforming the members of that group into a bunch of idiots.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
