<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>World View on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/world-view/</link>
    <description>Recent content in World View on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 13:28:33 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/world-view/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Who needs a world view?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 13:28:33 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;. In this talk, I would like to focus on the two attitudes that I have towards your project. It is not that I have ambiguous feelings; no, I have two distinct feelings. On the one hand, I am convinced that you will not reach your goal because such a goal is unreachable. Not only that. Your goal is undesirable and best abandoned. On the other hand, if you strive with integrity, clarity and passion to reach your goal, in the process, you will achieve results that are desirable, necessary and important. So, I would like to support and encourage your project. On the one hand, I believe that I can develop a few impossibility arguments that will show why you best abandon your project; on the other hand, I have given no thought to developing such a set of arguments because I want you to work further towards your goal so that you produce the results that we, as humankind, need. This might suggest that I am ambiguous toward your project, but, as I said, I am not. To explain thus attitude better, let me use an illustration from the history of philosophy (albeit in a slightly caricatured form),&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-reflexivity of Religion</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2017 23:17:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/self-reflexivity-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It would be interesting to answer the question of whether or not The Lord of the Rings (LOTR) is a religious story by testing against &amp;lsquo;religion is an explanatorily intelligible account of the Cosmos&amp;rsquo;. Does the Lord of the Rings give an account in which the causal and intentional explanations for the happenings in Middle Earth fall together?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One of the problems in testing a scientific theory and of developing one, I might add, is to ask the right question. The other problem, of course, is to find the right answer. Let us first take a step back and look at the claim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian belief: worldview is a cultural universal</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 20:50:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-belief-worldview-is-a-cultural-universal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lets become clear about the nature of my claims about worldviews.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The word carries multiple meanings. It has partly to do with the multiple meanings of the component words: world&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;. In daily language-use, &amp;lsquo;world&amp;rsquo; is used to pick out (a) a spatial and temporal slice of the cosmos (b) and/or the entire Cosmos itself. The first, the slices, are many: from the &amp;lsquo;social world&amp;rsquo; to the &amp;rsquo;emotional world&amp;rsquo;; from earth (&amp;lsquo;our world&amp;rsquo;) to parts of the same (&amp;lsquo;our part of the world&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;in different parts of the world&amp;rsquo;) and so on. The same consideration applies to &amp;lsquo;view&amp;rsquo;: it could refer to perspectives (&amp;lsquo;my view of the issue&amp;rsquo;) and to the totality (&amp;lsquo;we now have a clear view of the situation&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As though this is not enough, the word &amp;lsquo;world view&amp;rsquo; also carries additional multiple meanings: it picks out a totality of beliefs that some individual has; it refers at times exclusively to false beliefs (the Marxist use of the notion of ideology); it is either necessary or strictly superfluous (depending on how one interprets the scope of &amp;lsquo;ideology&amp;rsquo;); it picks out the common denominator among a group of people and the latter itself can refer to a nation, a class, a culture, the species, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularization and world views</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularization-and-world-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2011 19:03:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularization-and-world-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To begin with the question raised in `The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;: Do all cultures, peoples, and individuals need a world view to navigate themselves in the world? The answer is in the negative because religion is not a cultural universal and the only examples we have of world views are religions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Are the atheists, free thinkers, and people ignorant of religious doctrines of Christianity (in the West) also religious? This question has a positive answer because of the process of secularization of religion. In this sense, keeping in mind that the process of secularization is how a religion attempts to transcend its constraints, the atheists etc. in the west do have a Christian world view. This means the following: they accept the doctrines of a de-Christianized Christianity and, for these to be continually transmitted and make sense to those who accept them, this religion requires to be present in the background (and is subject to secularization movement). That is to say, we can identify elements of a Christian world view in the west, and we can do that only because that religion is present in the culture. We need to keep in mind that these beliefs are part of a world view only because such a world view is present in that culture.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
