<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Criticism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/criticism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Criticism on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 05:23:01 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/criticism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Profound criticism 1: the logic is different</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/profound-criticism-1-the-logic-is-different/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 05:23:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/profound-criticism-1-the-logic-is-different/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many come up with criticisms like &amp;lsquo;Buddhist logics are different&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;one has to follow Indian logics&amp;rsquo;. These criticisms sound profound! They are damn shallow, unless they answer the following questions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What is their structure?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are their axioms?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are their rules of inferences?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What are some some crucial meta-logical theorems (do they all have deduction theorems?) etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intellectual prowess of Michael Witzel</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intellectual-prowess-of-michael-witzel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2012 19:16:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/intellectual-prowess-of-michael-witzel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I would have liked to make the following points on the IER forum but either of the two moderators are (obviously) willing to be courteous enough to post my letter on their forum, despite my explicit request. Let me react to their letters on this forum, and I shall leave it there for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Neither Michael Witzel nor Steve Farmer answers my request for clarifications but simply take off on polemical tones. I do not see what purpose is thereby served. Globally speaking, both their letters seem to indicate that they are convinced that either I am aligned with the Hindutva movement or that I am a Hindutva man myself or both. Of course, because we have not met each other so far, there is only one way for them to divine my political preferences: through my writings. Witzel claims that he has read them, whereas Farmer keeps silent about the issue. It is a matter of public record that I claim that &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; (as a &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo;) does not exist in India. Consequently, from my writings on the subject, no one can accuse me of supporting a stance that wants to found India on &amp;lsquo;hinduness&amp;rsquo; or on &amp;lsquo;hindudom&amp;rsquo; or on &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; (whether conceived as a &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; or called as &amp;lsquo;sanatana dharma&amp;rsquo;). So, from where could anyone draw conclusion that these two have drawn?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Consider the following possibility: let us assume that in some of my writings, I reach the same conclusion as some or another ideologue from Hindutva. (Of course, neither Farmer nor Witzel shows that this is the case. But that is not the issue.) In other words, let us assume that, with respect to some or another issue, I arrive at the same conclusion as people from the Hinudtva movement do. The question is: what does that indicate, or prove or is an evidence for? After all, Witzel, Farmer and others reach the same conclusion as the Hindutva people do, when you ask them about the sum of two integers (say adding two to itself); or (assuming the presence of relevant There is only one answer possible in this case: there exists a unique theory (&amp;rsquo;the Hindutva theory&amp;rsquo;) from which one can derive certain conclusions. It is not possible to derive the same conclusion from any other theory that we know (or can invent). Consequently, one can argue backwards: if someone, anyone, supports a specific conclusion (&amp;rsquo;the Hindutva conclusion&amp;rsquo;) then that is because such a conclusion is derivable only from the &amp;lsquo;Hindutva theory&amp;rsquo;. Only a fool could entertain making such a claim today, if ever. Assuming that Witzel and Farmer are not fools, they appear reasonably intelligent to me, how then could they &amp;lsquo;see&amp;rsquo; Hindutva in my writings? A more charitable assumption would be: Witzel either has not read my writings (he lies when he says he has) or has not understood them at all (which makes him dim witted). Choose your poison.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What makes one an intellectual?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2012 06:51:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/what-makes-one-an-intellectual/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steve Farmer is not an expert on secularism only in the sense that he has followed it from the &amp;lsquo;outside&amp;rsquo; (meaning, probably, he has not written anything about the issue himself). Apparently, the reason why he has not contributed to the debate has to do with the fact that (a) no legitimate researcher can take the debate seriously; and (b) Farmer is one such. Witness how he describes it: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve watched this so-called debate for nearly a decade now from the outside, and nothing whatsoever has changed. Nor have I ever met a single legitimate researcher who took it seriously.&amp;rdquo; I wish some of the Indian intellectuals who have participated in the debate would read this judgment and digest what Farmer thinks of them. They will be thrilled to know that they are &amp;lsquo;illegitimate&amp;rsquo; scholars!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: Are we living in barrenness?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-are-we-living-in-barrenness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 20:33:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-are-we-living-in-barrenness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not assume that, as you put it, &amp;ldquo;we are living in complete barrenness of thought but for the light which Balu has thrown.&amp;rdquo; One would be doing the members of this forum a great disservice by attributing such an assumption to them. They do not believe in this claim anymore than I do. I do not accept this claim at all. From the many reasons I have for not accepting this ridiculous claim, let me mention just two. The first is my belief that my intellectual endeavors merely reproduce the macro-pattern of India on an atomic scale: my life is the Indian history writ small. I know far too many people on so many parallel paths involved in the kind of research I am doing to make myself believe that I am the genius the world has been waiting for. There is a second reason. The development of my story would have been impossible but for the existence of stories penned by other people and the earlier generations of both Indians and westerners. Every single &lt;code&gt;error&#39; and &lt;/code&gt;mistake&amp;rsquo; made by, say, the colonial writers on India is a problem to solve: why did they make the mistakes they did? Answers to this question constitute one of the parameters that render my story scientific. The scientificity of my story presupposes the &lt;code&gt;errors&#39; and &lt;/code&gt;mistakes&amp;rsquo; of the earlier generations. In much the same way, my errors and mistakes will be the presuppositions for the subsequent attempts in building a better theory. (This is also a prosaic formulation of the Hegelian-Marxist notion of `critique&amp;rsquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Family resemblances, language games, Wittgenstein, and debates on religion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/family-resemblances-language-games-wittgenstein-and-debates-on-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 18:42:27 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/family-resemblances-language-games-wittgenstein-and-debates-on-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Balagangadhara points out an inconsistent reasoning of  the western and westernized Scholars, as well as the last 400 years of humanities scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let me summarise the dilemma. Some properties are necessary for some traditions (Judaism, Christianity, Islam) to be religions. If one accepts this, the threat is that other cultures appear not to have religions at all. For some reason or another (I discuss the reasons in chapters 3 through 7), other cultures are said to have religions too. However, the conditions under which other cultures are to have religion are precisely those that make it impossible for the Semitic religions to be religions. That is to say, if the Semitic religions are what religions are, other cultures do not have religions. If other cultures have religions, then the Semitic religions are not religions. The inconsistency lies in insisting that both statements are true.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why people resist to think critically?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-people-resist-to-think-critically/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 06:32:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-people-resist-to-think-critically/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have also come across expressions of similar thoughts and feelings both in India and in Europe and the United States. However, I think there are multiple grounds that generate such questions. Here are some I have been able to identify.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When people hear me say that the western intellectuals of the last three hundred years or more are completely wrong, invariably people skeptically wonder whether I think I am such a genius. Anticipating this (mostly) unexpressed question, I tell them that it is not a matter of psychology; I show that my theory answers the question (without making ad hoc assumptions) why the western intellectuals have been unable to see what I see. Even though they fall silent at this point, I suspect they do so not because they are convinced but because they do not know what else to say.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existential Questions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/existential-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 21:57:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/existential-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If we want to speak about the meaning of human existence, at least one condition has to be met: such an existence (from birth to death at least) must embody a plan or a reason. Such a plan or reason cannot be that of the individual in question for the simple reason that his/her birth (at the least, not to speak of the first years of his/her existence) does not instantiate any of his/her plans. Only in such cases could we say that the human existence has meaning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Indian Secularists do not think but talk?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 20:26:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/why-indian-secularists-do-not-think-but-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to go deeper into the claim of &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-%e2%80%93s-n-balagangadhara/&#34; title=&#34;Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara&#34;&gt;my earlier post&lt;/a&gt;&#xA; that Shabnum Tejanis and Neera Chandhokes of this world do not think but merely talk. In other words, is it possible to identify the problems with their accounts (that explicates more clearly why I say that they do not think) in such a way that it is susceptible to some sort of solution? If, indeed, we can show that such people do not think and we can show that their mistakes have some cognitive roots, then we can also provide additional explanations. In such a case, our answer would be richer and more complex than any other available at the market place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundationalism and Virtuous Circularity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 04:49:31 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/foundationalism-and-virtuous-circularity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You do not want to call our natural sciences as &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo;. I do not even mind that. (For instance, you might want to define &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; as &amp;rsquo;true and justified belief&amp;rsquo;. You might show me that our theories in natural sciences are only believed to be true and are not proved to be true. Therefore, you might want to say that our natural sciences are not &amp;lsquo;knowledge&amp;rsquo; according to your definition. Fair enough.) Since you want to conduct a discussion about knowledge and if our sciences are not examples of knowledge, I need to know whether there are other examples of knowledge. If such an entity exists, our discussions make sense. If we have no examples of knowledge at all, according to some or another definition of the word, how could we discuss about that? I mean to say, if not even the logics we use in out argument is an example of knowledge, how could we ever have any discussion about the scope, range, etc. of knowledge? We cannot. In other words, if we want to have discussions about knowledge, we need to have examples of knowledge and need to use these examples in our discussions about their nature. So, you have to tell me: (a) whether we have examples of knowledge; (b) what they are; (c) how we should use them in our discussions; (d) show that their use does not pervert our discussions about knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are a hindutvavaadin!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-a-hindutvavaadin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2011 00:14:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-a-hindutvavaadin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Consider the following possibility: let us assume that in some of my writings, I reach the same conclusion as some or another ideologue from Hindutva. (Of course, neither Steve Farmer nor Michael Witzel shows that this is the case. But that is not the issue.) In other words, let us assume that, with respect to some or another issue, I arrive at the same conclusion as people from the Hinudtva movement do. The question is: what does that indicate, or prove or is an evidence for? After all, Witzel, Farmer and others reach the same conclusion as the Hindutva people do, when you ask them about the sum of two integers (say adding two to itself); or (assuming the presence of relevant knowledge in both) about the chemical composition of water and any number of such allied stuff. They would also (probably) agree with respect to current geography, Capitals of different nations, and so on and so forth. Why is this agreement between them and the Hindutva not suspect? Why does some or another alleged agreement that I could have with the Hindutva make me a Hindutva man?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christological Dilemma</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 23:20:19 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/christological-dilemma-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X says that Christological dilemma is some kind of theological logic and suggests that ordinary Christians are not affected by this artificial problematic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are two issues here worth looking at separately.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Is the problematic artificial? Well, it depends. I am not claiming that every Christian (past, present and future) is &lt;em&gt;aware&lt;/em&gt; of this problematic, of course. This is a general formulation that attempts to capture the variety in Christianity as answers to some specific problem. It has the same status as some or another scientific law. Even though what we have in this Cosmos, say, are &lt;em&gt;concrete, moving objects of specific size, volume, density and so on&lt;/em&gt;, we have laws that describe such specific movements as instances of a &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; law. In exactly the same way, I (partially) describe the varieties within Christianity as various answers to the Christological dilemma. Does that make my description artificial? Well, this is an issue about &lt;em&gt;your own&lt;/em&gt; metaphysics: what &amp;rsquo;natural&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;social&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;cultural&amp;rsquo; is and what &amp;lsquo;artificial&amp;rsquo; is. All I can say is that my description does partially capture the &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt; within Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How did I come up with the theory I did?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-did-i-come-up-with-the-theory-i-did-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 23:15:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-did-i-come-up-with-the-theory-i-did-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What does it matter where they came from and how? Newton did not travel through the Cosmos and visit planets in order to formulate his theories of planetary motion. That guy did not even visit India to find out whether the &lt;em&gt;naked fakirs&lt;/em&gt; levitate or not. With the proverbial falling of the apple on his head (this story is too beautiful to let go!), Sir Isaac made claims about gravitation and flatly claimed (as an implication) that the equally proverbial &lt;em&gt;fakir&lt;/em&gt; could not levitate! Einstein was sitting in a tram, watching a car go by and feeling quite frustrated, when he came up with the theory of special relativity. Surely, while such anecdotes are quite interesting in their own right, we do not claim that the theories of Newton and Einstein are not worthy of consideration &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of how they came into existence. The theory of double helix occurred literally in a dream; would we therefore dismiss it by saying that Watson dreamt the whole thing and that it was his personal nightmare?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refutation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/refutation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 05:43:55 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/refutation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My book is not about India but about the western culture. It is a study of the western culture using one thread, namely, religion. To the extent I talk about India, I do so using some of the &amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; that Indologists (and others) have so far used. My use of their facts (to show the opposite of what they believe they have shown) illustrates the consensus in the philosophies of sciences (of the last hundred years or more) that &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/&#34;&gt;&amp;lsquo;facts&amp;rsquo; are mostly facts of a theory.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Professional Competence</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/professional-competence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:27:53 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/professional-competence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ascription of professional competence to oneself when one does not have that. Each is in a position to say what &amp;rsquo;the Caste System&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;rsquo;ethics&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;corruption&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;religion&amp;rsquo; is, what &amp;lsquo;Hinduism&amp;rsquo; is… Why does one need to build new social science, when &amp;rsquo;every Hindu specimen&amp;rsquo; is an authority on these subjects? I suppose one can also be a physicist, biologist and chemist on these grounds as well: after all, is one not subject to gravitational forces, chemical reactions in the body, and suffers pain as well?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Patrick Hogan’s &#39;Why Hindus should be grateful to Wendy Doniger&#39;—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 00:04:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-patrick-hogans-why-hindus-should-be-grateful-to-wendy-doniger-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Patrick Hogan,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is jolly good of you, as the British say, to contribute to the &amp;rsquo;literary landscapes&amp;rsquo; column in Sulekha at this particular juncture. I am glad too that you put across some thoughtful considerations without being polemical, and that can only help generate a stimulating discussion among all the concerned parties. However, the way you frame your points make the task an exercise in walking on a tight rope.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to produce knowledge about “Who is a Christian”—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:27:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-to-produce-knowledge-about-who-is-a-christian-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine that I were to say the following: Christ and &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; are manifestations of the same divinity; Christ came about 2000 years ago in the Middle East, whereas &lt;em&gt;Ganesha&lt;/em&gt; is how he has appeared in India some 4000 years ago. Now no one can forbid me from saying this and &lt;em&gt;calling myself a Christian&lt;/em&gt;. Question: what should a theory about Christianity do? Show &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; anyone who decides to call himself a &amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo; is, in fact, also a Christian? In that case, all such a &amp;rsquo;theory&amp;rsquo; can do is say something like the following: anyone who calls himself some name (&amp;lsquo;Christian&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Democrat&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Marxist&amp;rsquo;, etc) is also whatever he calls himself. Such an attitude simply ends up making any knowledge of society and human beings impossible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are spreading hate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-spreading-hate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 23:15:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-spreading-hate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Criticism: You are spreading hate by citing Deschner&amp;rsquo;s work–&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kriminalgeschichte des Christentums&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;and ANY idiot knows even the title is stupid.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have not cited a single atrocity that Christianity has committed in order to incite hate towards Christianity. In fact, I have not even discussed any specific theological doctrine of any kind of Christianity, except to speak of the Christological dilemma. This dilemma is discussed by theologians, themselves Christians, in the field of Christology. And even here, I localise in it the dynamics of Christianity. The intolerance of Christianity, I say very explicitly, is its property by virtue of being a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;religion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. That is to say, according to my research, all &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;religions are intolerant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. You might want to disagree with it; you are welcome to put your arguments across that refute the result of my research. But how does this constitute spreading hate? I am puzzled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meanings and Historical Context: the arguments from Indian scholars –S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 07:56:26 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/meanings-and-historical-context-the-arguments-from-indian-scholars-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt; Consider the thought that &amp;lsquo;meanings&amp;rsquo; (leave aside the distinction between words and sentences on the one hand and concepts and categories on the other) do not exist outside historical contexts. What exactly does this thought say? Begin with &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;. Either every situation that an individual human being finds himself is a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; (because human beings are always &amp;lsquo;in a context&amp;rsquo; and these contexts always occur &amp;lsquo;in history&amp;rsquo;) or there is a difference between &amp;rsquo; a context&amp;rsquo; and a &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo;.  She cannot possibly make the latter of the two claims because if the meaning of &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; changes only in &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo; but not in &amp;lsquo;other kinds of contexts&amp;rsquo;, it follows that &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; has a stable meaning in other contexts than  &amp;lsquo;historical contexts&amp;rsquo;, which she would want to deny. So, for the sake of consistency, we have to assume that &amp;lsquo;context&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;historical context&amp;rsquo; are synonyms. Then, the thought is that meaning varies according to contexts. Consider the word &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo;: the only way I can imagine that the meaning of this word varies according to individual contexts is the following: to one, it means a &amp;rsquo;life saver&amp;rsquo;; to the other &amp;lsquo;fattening&amp;rsquo; and to the third &amp;lsquo;sweet&amp;rsquo; and so on. (In fact, to one and the same individual &amp;lsquo;ice cream&amp;rsquo; could &amp;ldquo;mean different things&amp;rdquo; at different points in time: what ice-cream meant  when one was 3 years need indeed not be the same as what it means when one is 50 and suffers from Diabetes and obesity.) So far so good. But the problem is this: these different meanings of &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; presuppose that we are talking about the same thing. Only under this condition can we say that &amp;lsquo;ice-cream&amp;rsquo; means different things to different people (or to the same person at different times).  To talk about the same thing, ice-cream, we need a reference for that word and, in many cases (like secularism and communalism, for example) it is a &amp;rsquo;linguistic description&amp;rsquo; of that word (a &amp;lsquo;definition&amp;rsquo;, or its &amp;lsquo;meaning&amp;rsquo;) that provides us with reference. (In the case of ice-cream, one might use gestures to point out an ice-cream; you cannot do that for &amp;lsquo;secularism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;communalism&amp;rsquo;.) In other words, the ONLY possible way for secularism to have multiple meanings in multiple historical contexts is by having a meaning that is INDEPENDENT of contexts. (Or having a meaning that is common across all POSSIBLE contexts.) In other words, when Neera or Shabnum or anyone else makes the claim that meanings do not transcend contexts either (a) they are making the trivial point that every word uttered by any human being always takes place in a context (which no one had ever denied) or (b) by saying that meaning is totally context bound they are contradicting themselves. Of course, to notice that one is inconsistent, one needs to think according to the rules of grammar and rules of logic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Will Sweetman’s Criticism—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-will-sweetmans-criticism-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 07:18:38 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/on-will-sweetmans-criticism-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me just focus on one important and one not-so-important claim from Will Sweetman&amp;rsquo;s article &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hinduism&amp;rdquo; and the history of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;: Protestant presuppositions in the critique of the concept of Hinduism.&lt;/em&gt; He suggests that I argue the following.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;First premise: Christianity is prototypically what religion is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Second premise: Hinduism does not share all (or perhaps any) of the relevant properties of Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Conclusion: Hinduism is not a religion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem, here, turns around the notion of &amp;lsquo;prototypicality&amp;rsquo;. I explain at length (a) the source of the word; and (b) its meaning. For the role these clarifications play in Sweetman&amp;rsquo;s analysis, I might as well not have written those passages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: Twisted arguments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-twisted-arguments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 16:57:34 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-twisted-arguments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Criticism: I use jargon and twisted arguments on a mundane topic. And that every Swami says that Hinduism is not a religion but a way of life. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If anything, I have avoided jargon (i.e. the use of technical language) in my book. I would like to know where I use technical language without explaining it. As far as twisted arguments go, I presume you to mean invalid arguments. If you can point to an invalid argument, you would be identifying a flaw in the book. Unfortunately, you do not provide instances of it. May be, you should try being concrete.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: Nonsense</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-nonsense/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2011 16:46:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-nonsense/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regarding nonsense.&lt;/em&gt; I take it you mean that my claims are false or wrong. In that case, I would like to read your reasons. There is no point in simply saying something like that without telling which &lt;em&gt;other theory of religion&lt;/em&gt; does better than mine. Even if there are problems in my theory, I claim that this is the best theory we have in the market place. If you think differently, I would like you to tell us &lt;em&gt;the way in which&lt;/em&gt; any of the competitor theories in the market place does better. Of course, as a scientist, I do know (and accept) at a meta-level that all my claims are &lt;em&gt;hypothetical and tentative.&lt;/em&gt; I very honestly hope to see and greet, before I die, a &lt;em&gt;much better theory&lt;/em&gt; of religion than the one I am developing. Such a process will come into being, if people like you discuss the theory in a critical but rational way. It will not, if people continue nit-picking and come up with irrelevant criticisms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are essentializing cultures!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-essentializing-cultures/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 22:32:29 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-essentializing-cultures/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first question: &amp;ldquo;By saying that there exist &amp;ldquo;Western&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Indian&amp;rdquo; cultures aren&amp;rsquo;t you somehow essentializing cultures into monoliths?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I do not see how. When we talk of &amp;rsquo;the human species&amp;rsquo; (in the singular), or about &amp;rsquo;life&amp;rsquo; (again in the singular) while doing evolutionary biology, we do not presuppose or imply that either of the two is a monolithic entity, do we? In fact, &lt;em&gt;diversity&lt;/em&gt; is a presupposition for any kind of knowledge and this is my presupposition as well. I presuppose (and my theory requires) diversity in both the Indian and the western culture. Without it, one cannot test the theories.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: What’s with Behavioral Psychology?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-whats-with-behavioral-psychology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:45:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-whats-with-behavioral-psychology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not want to indulge in a discussion about Behavioral Psychology either on this forum or on any other forum. It is to waste of time I do not have. Let me very briefly state where I stand with respect to that discipline. In its early days, it was useful in providing some insights into animal behavior. I share the dominant consensus regarding its status today: it is obsolete. It does not quite have the status of &amp;lsquo;phlogiston theory&amp;rsquo; but it is pretty close to the latter. I have suffered through many writings of Skinner and his disciples, but I have neither the time nor the interest to discuss their &amp;rsquo;theories&amp;rsquo; now. This means, I am going to skip over issues involving &amp;lsquo;shaping&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;conditioning&amp;rsquo; and such like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are peddling a ‘wannabe Indianism’!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-peddling-a-wannabe-indianism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 19:35:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-peddling-a-wannabe-indianism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is there a &amp;lsquo;wannabe Indianism&amp;rsquo; in our attempts to understand our tradition? I am not sure: maybe there is, maybe there is not. Of course, the question is why is this relevant? Whatever the motives or the contexts of any individual writer why should that be an argument for either accepting or rejecting or even putting his opinions on hold? The way I see it, the nature of the phenomenon is of another level altogether: I think that the intellectuals from India will increasingly be confronted with the question of what it is to be an Indian. There are many reasons for it: the political, the social, the economic as well as cultural. In fact, I think that this is not merely an Indian phenomenon but an Asian one. Today, the centre of gravity (in economic, geo-political terms) is slowly shifting towards Asia, a non-white, non-Christian culture. That is why you and I (and many others like us) are discussing these issues passionately. To us, these issues are not &amp;lsquo;abstract&amp;rsquo;; it is very much a part of our daily life (in the appropriate sense of the term). When I was started working on these issues some two decades ago, I could count the number of interested people on the fingers of my one hand. Today, two decades later, look at what is happening: we are discussing, with a passion born out of our daily experiences, what appears from the outside as &lt;em&gt;esoteric&lt;/em&gt; issues. But it is not &amp;rsquo;esoteric&amp;rsquo; to us, is it? I think the scale, depth, and the intensity of these discussions (both in India and outside) transcend any &amp;lsquo;wannabe Indian&amp;rsquo; motive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are not an ‘authentic Indian’!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-an-authentic-indian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:51:21 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-an-authentic-indian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About who the &amp;lsquo;authentic Hind&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;the authentic Indian&amp;rsquo; is. The greatest strength of our culture lies in the fact that this is a non-question as far as our traditions are concerned. Even though I have now spent nearly as many years outside India as I have spent inside, I do not feel an &amp;lsquo;outsider&amp;rsquo;. Nor am I considered as one by the members my family, for instance, most of whom have never left India in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are usurping the right to speak for the community.</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-usurping-the-right-to-speak-for-the-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:47:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-usurping-the-right-to-speak-for-the-community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me lay this fear to rest: I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; speaking for the community. To the question, &amp;lsquo;Who speaks for the Indian traditions?&amp;rsquo; my reply is simple: &lt;em&gt;anyone, everyone, whoever feels like&lt;/em&gt;. (Of course, I do not consider the question very sensible, but that is a side-issue for the moment.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having said this much, let me also say that my discussion with Jeffrey Kripal is not about the moral right to speak in the name of the community but whether such speeches &lt;em&gt;constitute knowledge&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, I &lt;em&gt;evaluate&lt;/em&gt; what someone says about the Indian traditions for its veracity and it is here that I find Kripal falling way short.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: don’t judge others!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-dont-judge-others/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:23:12 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-dont-judge-others/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask us not to &amp;lsquo;judge&amp;rsquo;. It is not clear what the force of judgment is to which you object. When I listen to someone (today) insisting that the earth is flat or that the Sun revolves round the earth, I judge that this person (in all probability) does not have much of an idea about the physical theories. Because I am not sure, I try to find out what his arguments are. If they do not cognitively satisfy me, I judge that he is wrong. I do not see what is wrong with this kind of judgment. Equally, I do judge that Hitler is an immoral human being. I do not see what is wrong with this kind of moral judgment either. You might want to say that one ought not to judge the &amp;lsquo;worth&amp;rsquo; of a person. Frankly, I do not understand what such a sentiment wants to say. I cannot judge whether the life of some X or Y is worth living, simply because I have no way of judging it either way. Nor can I say anything about the worth of human existence. (From which perspective? The cosmic perspective?) If some person were to ask me whether it makes any difference to the Cosmos whether the human race exists or not, I would not know how to go about answering this question. Consequently, any answer will do as far as I am concerned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: one need to be Indian to study Indian culture</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-one-need-to-be-indian-to-study-indian-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:20:50 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-one-need-to-be-indian-to-study-indian-culture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a way, and in some sense, I do agree with you that one&amp;rsquo;s acquaintance with a culture is useful in writing about that culture. It is not sufficient, of course (think of the nonsense written by most anthropologists during the last 100 years on other cultures); nor are there any compelling reasons to believe that it is a sine qua non to understanding cultures. However, I am not challenging the claim that the context of the person might be relevant to producing knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are not using game theory</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-using-game-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:17:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-using-game-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is the model of games useful in understanding evolution of some aspect of society? If you use &amp;lsquo;games&amp;rsquo; in a very, very general sense (viz. there are players, strategies, end-results, and such like), then it might. There is a flourishing branch of mathematics called &amp;lsquo;Game theory&amp;rsquo; that has been used to study many things in nature and society: from the evolution of rules and norms to seeing evolution itself in Game-theoretic terms. I need to warn you that its notion of games is a technical one and involves two or more &amp;lsquo;players&amp;rsquo;, who follow certain strategies for &amp;lsquo;winning&amp;rsquo; to which a certain pay-off is coupled. While it has uncovered certain interesting dilemmas in societies, I do not find it as fruitful as its practitioners claim.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are not studying Ancient India!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-studying-ancient-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:14:22 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-not-studying-ancient-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I do not see why I have to study the history of the last 4000 years to understand modern India. To the extent past becomes relevant (my research into some particular question will tell me whether the past is relevant, if so which part of the past is relevant, and how far I need to go in understanding the issue I want to understand), only to that extent do I need to study the past. The general statement &amp;lsquo;we are what we are because of the past&amp;rsquo; is true. But this is also a general statement. How far into my &amp;lsquo;past&amp;rsquo; do you need to go in order to understand my present? That depends on which part of the present you want to understand and what this &amp;lsquo;understanding&amp;rsquo; means in the context of your research. The same applies to a study of cultures and societies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criticism: you are ‘Westernized’!</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-westernized/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 07:11:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/criticism-you-are-westernized/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the possibility that I was already &amp;lsquo;westernized&amp;rsquo; by the time I became a teenager. Even this question is wrongly posed. I am not claiming that there is some &amp;lsquo;authentic&amp;rsquo; Indian culture, which lives somewhere or lived some when in India. Such a culture, even if it exists or existed, does not concern me. I am interested in the Indian culture as it &lt;em&gt;exists&lt;/em&gt; today: including the aftermath of the Islamic and the British colonization. I am child of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; culture, and this is the one I am trying to understand. The Indian &amp;lsquo;Diaspora&amp;rsquo; in the US is &lt;em&gt;as much&lt;/em&gt; Indian as some peasant living somewhere in a far-off village in India; they both belong to the Indian culture. Neither this peasant nor the Indians in the US is &amp;lsquo;more Indian&amp;rsquo; than the other. My problem is not: who is the &amp;lsquo;authentic&amp;rsquo; Indian or what is the &amp;lsquo;authentic&amp;rsquo; Indian culture? My question is about the 21st century India, and its present culture, which has absorbed many things, adapted many things from other cultures in many different ways. It is this set of Indian traditions that interests me. Was I &amp;lsquo;westernized&amp;rsquo; by the time I was a teenager? Who knows, or even who cares? What would it mean to say that I was &amp;lsquo;authentically&amp;rsquo; Indian or that I was &amp;lsquo;quasi-westernized&amp;rsquo;? Surely, the issue is not about some kind of &amp;lsquo;purity&amp;rsquo; here. What else is it? Consequently, when I speak of my past, I speak of the past of those who were brought up like me. If we were all partly &amp;lsquo;westernized&amp;rsquo;, then the culture I am talking about is this &amp;lsquo;partly westernized&amp;rsquo; Indian culture. An age long gone by, if it ever existed, does not give me sleepless nights; what does is what is happening now. Thus, when I say I want to understand Indian culture, I am not harking back to some &amp;lsquo;golden age&amp;rsquo;, my friend, but India as I know it today. To understand this India, I need to understand how her traditions are &lt;em&gt;lived&lt;/em&gt; today, not what they perhaps meant one thousand years ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whose view is better?—S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/whose-view-is-better-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 03:32:42 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/whose-view-is-better-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Every one of us believes our own viewpoint to be the best one: such is human nature.&amp;rdquo; This is not quite how I would put it. Let me, therefore say what I think with respect to this issue.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Whenever I formulate a theory, I believe that my description is &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;. If I thought that it was &amp;lsquo;false&amp;rsquo;, I would not write what I write. This is a belief about the status of my description and its relationship to the part of reality I describe. Let us call this the &amp;lsquo;object-level&amp;rsquo; belief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critisim: are you a genius?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/am-i-a-genius-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2011 02:09:58 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/am-i-a-genius-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It appears that Sir Isaac Newton was frequently complimented for being the greatest genius the world had ever known. One of his replies is alleged to have been the following: &amp;ldquo;Even a pygmy sees further than the giants if he stands upon their shoulders. And I, Sir, stand upon the shoulders of giants.&amp;rdquo; The extraordinary humility apart, there is something very important to what Newton is saying: his theory would not have been there, if the theories of Copernicus and Galileo were not there before him. It is, of course, a historical accident that certain people preceded Newton. This allowed Newton, however, to write his Principia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
