<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Interests on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/interests/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Interests on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/categories/interests/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Swacch Bharat, Public Interest and Corruption</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 17:05:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/swacch-bharat-public-interest-and-corruption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Chairman Sir, Ladies and Gentlemen, Good Morning.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually I&amp;rsquo;m the odd man out. We have success stories. We have spiritual leaders; we have an extraordinarily organizational leader in front of us. And now I have to do an exam. You see, normally I take exams in the university. Now I have to do an exam. The exam is this I must move you from these wonderful stories, success stories, good stories, to a rather depressing story. The question is how can I do it and still catch your attention. I don&amp;rsquo;t know. After the exam, tell me please whether I&amp;rsquo;ve succeeded or failed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How about speaking the truth about reservations?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 12:20:01 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/how-about-speaking-the-truth-about-reservations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens to the future of Indian intellectual scene when most of projects driven by its intelligentsia propagate perverted truths for self-seeking purposes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Satyam Vada, Dharmam Chara”, “Satyameva Jayate”&lt;/em&gt; are but two of the well-known Sanskrit sayings that are supposed to indicate the values placed upon truth and truth-telling in Indian culture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It comes as a surprise, therefore, to read three items in the newspaper and a comment on a blog which seem to follow ‘truth’. But in such a way that &lt;em&gt;it becomes perverse&lt;/em&gt;. Because all the four issues are important, I would like to briefly talk about each.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normative Assumptions, Discriminations, and Caste Discriminations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 19:15:59 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/normative-assumptions-discriminations-and-caste-discriminations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was invited by some Sadhus from Swami Narayan Temple (BAPS) to visit the temple and have a discussion with them. Because they practice very strict Brahmacharya (eight types of avoiding women, each correlated to an organ: it is called Ashtanga Brahmacharya), the Sadhus said that women could not be present during our discussions, while they were welcome to visit the temple. As I remember the incident, my female students were a bit &amp;lsquo;upset&amp;rsquo; (hurt, insulted, indignant, or whatever) that the Sadhus were not able to meet them and felt &lt;strong&gt;discriminated against&lt;/strong&gt; by virtue of their sex. A few years later, one of my teachers from Belgium visited another wing of the Swami Narayan people and found that &amp;lsquo;women were discriminated against&amp;rsquo; because they were allowed only to come some distance from the temple when the Sadhus were present. In both cases, I was puzzled by their reaction: I explained that the action of the Sadhus should not be seen as an act of discrimination against women but as an expression of the strict Brahmacharya that the Sadhus practiced. The question here is: why did these people (my students and my teacher) experience &amp;lsquo;discrimination&amp;rsquo;, where I saw none and also knew that none was intended?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theme: interests of a social institution/Christian Church</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-interests-of-a-social-institutionchristian-church/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:08:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theme-interests-of-a-social-institutionchristian-church/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the state, state action and the issue of public interest. There are multiple problems here, which I am only slowly beginning to recognize. I will share two such problems with you without, however, being able to concretely spell out the alternatives. (a) Consider the belief that the state &amp;lsquo;ought&amp;rsquo; to act in the public interest. This belief makes sense if we assume that it is possible to speak in terms of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo; in some non-trivial fashion. Both Kenneth Arrow and Amrtya Sen have proved theorems that show that any such use incoherent: Arrow argued that we cannot speak of &amp;lsquo;public will&amp;rsquo; in any coherent way; Sen argued that we cannot aggregateprivate preferences into a consistent and coherent set of &amp;lsquo;public preferences&amp;rsquo;. Our notion of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo; includes these two notions and, as a consequence, does not allow of a coherent conceptualization. Even banning smoking in public places (whatever the notion of a &amp;lsquo;public space&amp;rsquo; be) is not very coherent, if argued in terms of &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo;. In this sense, justifying complex actions, which carry unintended consequences, in the name of public interest is not an interesting exercise. (b) Despite this, the idea of the state and its relation to public interest preoccupies people because of something else: that is the belief that every institution in society has an &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; and the state has a &amp;lsquo;public interest&amp;rsquo;. That is, there is an underlying assumption of &amp;lsquo;intelligibility&amp;rsquo; to claims about &amp;ldquo;institutional interests&amp;rsquo;: each institution has an interest the way each individual has either a &amp;lsquo;desire&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo;. The more I read history, the less intelligible it has become to me. I believe that this claim is a &amp;lsquo;secular translation&amp;rsquo; of the idea that &lt;em&gt;the Christian Church has some set of interests&lt;/em&gt; and political thinking, since the Middle Ages in Europe, has so constantly hammered on this theme that it has become a trivial fact that we take for granted. It is totally unclear to me how we identify the &amp;lsquo;interests&amp;rsquo; of a social institution, the State included, and how we find out whether we are wrong or right in attributing such an &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; to a social institution. In other words, we have no clue how we solve our disagreement in this area of legal and political philosophy: the more radical the disagreement, the less clear how we should solve the issue: suppose I deny that the State has any set of interests that it can call its own, how do we solve this disagreement? On the basis of some or another definition about what &amp;lsquo;interest&amp;rsquo; is or what &amp;lsquo;State&amp;rsquo; is?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
