<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sulekha on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/sulekha/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sulekha on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/sulekha/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Colonial Experience and the Indian Renaissance: A prolegomenon to a Project—S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 21:43:25 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-colonial-experience-and-the-indian-renaissance-a-prolegomenon-to-a-project-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the striking things about the British colonial rule is its success in developing certain ways of talking about the Indian culture and society. The British criticised the Indian &amp;lsquo;religions&amp;rsquo;, the Indian &amp;lsquo;caste system&amp;rsquo;, the Indian education system, practices like &amp;lsquo;sati&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;untouchability&amp;rsquo;, and so on and so forth. They redrew the outlines of Indian intellectual history as indigenous responses to some of the ills they saw in the Indian society and culture: for example, &amp;lsquo;Buddhism&amp;rsquo;, as it emerged out of their reconstruction, was a revolt against &amp;lsquo;Brahmanism&amp;rsquo; and &amp;rsquo;the caste system&amp;rsquo;. Many Indian intellectuals emphasized British criticism by making &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; in the latter their own: the Arya Samaj, the Brahmo Samaj, many Hindu &amp;lsquo;reform&amp;rsquo; movements, and so on exemplify this trend. I say &amp;rsquo;truths&amp;rsquo; and place it in scare quotes because the &lt;em&gt;unbroken line of continuity&lt;/em&gt; between the colonial period and the one following the Indian independence raises two &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of questions. The first is this: would there have been such a line of continuity if there was no &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; to the British portrayal of our history, traditions, and culture? This question uses the &amp;lsquo;fact&amp;rsquo; of continuity to suggest that the British descriptions &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;rsquo;true&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; That is, our current experience of our culture and society appears to lend truth-value to the colonial descriptions of India. The second question transforms our &amp;lsquo;current experience&amp;rsquo; itself into a problem: does such a line of continuity indicate that our experiences themselves are still colonial in nature? This question throws doubts upon the &amp;lsquo;facticity&amp;rsquo; of the British descriptions of India, and suggests that they &lt;em&gt;could be &amp;lsquo;untrue&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/em&gt; In the process, it also challenges us to look more closely and investigate our own experiences today. That is, the second question withholds assent to the &amp;rsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; of the colonial descriptions of India and of some of the claims we make about our experiences of our culture and society today. To some extent, and only to some extent, the so-called &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; writings can be seen as attempts to make sense of the second question. Even though I do not fancy the label of being a &amp;lsquo;post-colonial&amp;rsquo; myself, I perceive a shared sense of a quest with them. &lt;em&gt;There is something deeply, deeply wrong with the line of continuity that exists between the colonial period and today&amp;rsquo;s India,&lt;/em&gt; and the challenge is to say what it is.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>India and Her traditions: A Reply to Jeffrey Kripal – S.N. Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/india-and-her-traditions-a-reply-to-jeffrey-kripal-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2011 19:16:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/india-and-her-traditions-a-reply-to-jeffrey-kripal-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before addressing this writing to Jeffrey Kripal, I would like to very clearly stipulate some of my basic stances so that the discussion does not get derailed into these issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(A) Even though the communication will be directed to the person of Jeffrey Kripal, it is not &lt;em&gt;ad hominem&lt;/em&gt; but issue-oriented. However, I will eschew making some &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of qualifications academics are prone to make, so that any intelligent, but layperson can not only follow the discussion but also &lt;em&gt;evaluate&lt;/em&gt; what is being said.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
