<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adhoc on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/adhoc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Adhoc on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:10:13 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/adhoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Naming a phenomenon</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 00:10:13 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/naming-a-phenomenon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(a) Paolo Friere, a Brazilian educationalist, has spoken about such a phenomenon at length in his &lt;em&gt;Pedagogy of the Oppressed&lt;/em&gt;. He calls it as an ‘internalisation of the oppressor by the oppressed’. Whether we use Paolo Friere’s terminology or the much later one of ‘Stockholm Syndrome’, the problem is the same: both &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; the phenomenon without &lt;em&gt;explaining it&lt;/em&gt;. In and of itself, not such a big problem if it is not for a cognitive tendency that is &lt;strong&gt;dominant&lt;/strong&gt; in the ‘social sciences’, which brings me to the second point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Worship a Human Invention?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 01:20:48 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-worship-a-human-invention/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Let us assume that the Church Fathers (or the Apostles or whoever else) planned to introduce an eschatological doctrine and some mode of worship. (Let us further assume that their reasoning or their strategy was something analogous to your impressions: their intention was to induce a sense of urgency and guilt.) Our problem is not to explain their possible motives but to explain the &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; of these strategies. Our questions are: why do all the Semitic religions (this reference to the Semitic religions is meant only keep the discussion simple) follow these strategies? Why are these strategies successful? (You can also go further and raise questions about their relative lack of success today in the western world, but we will ignore all such complications.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In the process of answering these questions, you will inevitably be forced to appeal to the nature of human psychology. This appeal will, in its turn, make assumptions about human psychology: such is human psychology that these strategies are successful. If this assumption is made, you face a very serious problem with the fact that these strategies do not seem to work with a lot of human beings (atheists, heathens &amp;hellip;). In other words, you cannot explain the success of this strategy by appealing to &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; psychology. If you were to restrict it to the psychology of the believers &lt;em&gt;alone&lt;/em&gt;, you will end up providing &lt;strong&gt;a circular explanation&lt;/strong&gt;: such is the psychology of the believers that they are susceptible to this strategy. (Instead, you might as well say that the strategy works with &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt;people because it works with some people.)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Suppose you take the following route: religion &amp;lsquo;works&amp;rsquo; only for those people who have a specific kind of psychology, you face the almost impossible task of providing some kind of empirical data across cultures and time. Further, you will also have to explain why people who were (and are) prone to guilt cease being believers. As though this is not enough, you will also have to explain why only &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; guilt-prone individuals become believers and some others do not. In short, this is an almost impossible exercise given our state of knowledge today.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;As though these problems are not enough, any psychological assumption will have to answer two other important questions.&#xA;4.1. One is the presence of a &lt;strong&gt;manifest denial&lt;/strong&gt; of these psychological assumptions in the theologies of these religions. Worship expresses your love for God. Even if the Apostles (or whoever else) was a scoundrel (and the greatest genius that mankind has ever known) who used this claim as a palliative, why do people continue to accept and believe in it? Again, you will be forced to invent another psychological explanation: the believers are mentally deficient (in some appropriate sense of the term), whereas non-believers are intelligent enough to see through the strategies. Needless to say, this is simply an &lt;strong&gt;ad hoc&lt;/strong&gt; explanation without any kind of warrant or plausibility.&#xA;4.2. The second question is about the fact that the believers genuinely love their God. One will have to deny this. One has to insist that the believers mistakenly identify their feelings of guilt with love. Needless to say, the explanatory task here is of mind-boggling complexity.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;There is a different kind of problem concealed in your difficulty, as soon as we realise that we need to explain the success of the strategies (to induce urgency and guilt). The intention of the apostles is not sufficient to guarantee its success: something called &amp;rsquo;the world&amp;rsquo; intervenes in between. It is not sufficient that I intend doing something to reach some goal in the world. I need to take the nature of the world into account as well, if I have to succeed. In short, the worry you express is a still-born child, if the goal is to understand what religion is.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt; Worship and eschatology (for instance) are not &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; properties of an EI account. They are &lt;em&gt;contingent&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. given assumptions about our make-up, our capacities, and so on, we need to explain why all religions have such properties. In short, what I suggest is that, if we assume the existence of religion among human beings, all empirical religions will exhibit these properties. That is to say, if we come across a religion in some part of the earth that does not speak of worshipping God, does not have an eschatology, then my hypothesis is &lt;strong&gt;false&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;One final point. I am not saying that everything that happened in history is &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt;. What I do say is that given the structure of religion, some &lt;em&gt;kinds&lt;/em&gt; of events had to happen. All religions are &lt;em&gt;compelled&lt;/em&gt; to speak of worship, eschatology and so on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neurobiological Theory of Religion</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2013 00:05:09 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/neuro-biological-theory-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You ask whether &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; a neurobiological theory on religion could &amp;ldquo;account&amp;rdquo; for the experience of the believers. The answer depends on what kind of an account you are asking for and what you have in mind when you say &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;. If you mean by &amp;lsquo;account&amp;rsquo;, whether it could predict or even explain, I do not think so. We know that, at the least, we are made up of atoms. Your question, in terms of the kind of challenge it poses (even though the degree of complexity changes), is identical to the question: could a theory in physics, in principle, ever account for our experiences? What does &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; mean here actually? There was a period when one thought, among other things, that it was possible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo; to describe mathematics in a purely logical language. That is, many thought that mathematics has a &amp;ldquo;logical structure&amp;rdquo; and that, therefore, one could reconstruct mathematics aided by a suitably powerful logic. (It is called the &amp;lsquo;Hilbert program&amp;rsquo;, named after the originator of this research program.) Then a mathematician called Kurt Gödel proved that, in principle, we cannot even prove the truth of elementary arithmetic on logical grounds: even though we can generate true statements in elementary arithmetic (and know that they are true; they are called &amp;ldquo;Gödel numbers&amp;rdquo;), we cannot prove their truth. Nor can we prove their falsity. They belong to the class of &amp;ldquo;undecidable&amp;rdquo; statements. In other words, what appears obvious to many of us today, namely, arithmetic is &amp;rsquo;logical&amp;rsquo; in nature cannot ever be &amp;ldquo;proved&amp;rdquo;. This is an impossibility theorem that Gödel proved in the 1930&amp;rsquo;s. So, what we think is possible in principle turns out to be impossible &amp;lsquo;in principle&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dawkin’s  Delusion or The God Delusion?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:10:23 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/dawkins-delusion-or-the-god-delusion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While re-reading certain passages from Richard Dawkins&amp;rsquo; The God Delusion (2006), I was so shocked by his combination of ignorance and arrogance. Forgive me for some Dawkins- bashing:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;In a memorable passage, Dawkins discusses the problem of Trinitarianism in Christianity and extends it to other forms of &amp;ldquo;polytheism,&amp;rdquo; such as the cult of the Virgin Mary and the saints in Roman-Catholicism. &amp;ldquo;What impresses me about Catholic mythology,&amp;rdquo; he shares with the reader, &amp;ldquo;is partly its tasteless kitsch but mostly the airy nonchalance with which these people make up the details as they go along. It is just shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo; (Dawkins 2006: 35). As a reader, try to bracket away all presuppositions about religion and reread the sentences. If you succeed in doing so, the impact of Dawkins&amp;rsquo; claim dissolves. So what, if certain details of Roman-Catholicism are human inventions? What is the problem in aspects of religion being &amp;ldquo;shamelessly invented&amp;rdquo;? From a non-Christian, neutral point of view, it is unclear why Dawkins bothers to mention this. However, anyone with a basic understanding of the history of Christianity will note where his claim comes from: Dawkins himself reproduces a piece of theology in this sentence (apparently without knowing it). From its earliest beginnings, Christianity claimed that it was the original and pure revelation of God, first given to Adam. This original revelation had been corrupted by sinful idolaters, seduced by the Devil into the worship of the false god and his minions. This corruption, according to Christian theology, took the form of human additions to the pure divine revelation: rites and myths, fabricated by priests and prelates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the Protestant Reformation, Luther, Calvin and their followers began to accuse the Roman-Catholic Church of the same sin of idolatry. They cried that the pope and his priests had invented a plethora of dogmas and rituals and imposed these on the believer as though they were part of God&amp;rsquo;s revelation and necessary to salvation. In this sense, the worst accusation one could make against Roman- Catholicism was that it consisted of &amp;ldquo;shameless human inventions.&amp;rdquo; The Enlightenment philosophes extended such charges of idolatry to all of Christianity and to all &amp;ldquo;religions&amp;rdquo; of humanity. All of these, including the notion of God itself, were human fabrications, the atheists among them claimed. Ironically, Enlightenment atheism thus presupposed and built on the claims of Christian theology. Without the background belief that there is something intrinsically wrong in religion being a human invention—very much a Christian belief—the impact of such charges simply disappears into thin air.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secularized Christian theology and evolutionary explanations of religion</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 05:00:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/secularized-christian-theology-and-evolutionary-explanations-of-religion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;People like Scott Atran and Sloan Wilson abuse evolutionary biology to produce ad hoc explanations of an explanandum whose truth they presuppose: the universality of religion. Their explanations are no better than those discussed by Balu in chapter 5 of &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/colonialconsciousness/theheatheninhisblindness&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Heathen in his blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion.&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&amp;rsquo;. Paraphrasing Balu, we may say that they consist of &amp;rsquo;two quarters of theology, a quarter of evolutionary biology and a quarter of illiterate ethnology&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary explanations of religion: an exercise in petitio principii</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2012 04:49:44 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/evolutionary-explanations-of-religion-an-exercise-in-petitio-principii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is very disappointing to see how these evolutionary theorists of religion lack knowledge of religions other than garden variety Judeo-Christianity (where they seem to have at least some factual knowledge, as in Scott Atran&amp;rsquo;s case, they reproduce standard textbook stories about Hinduism that have been left behind a few decades back).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If they did a serious study, it would perhaps strike them that no one has ever given either theoretical or empirical proof for the claim that religion is a human universal. From the 13th century onwards, European travelers, missionaries, merchants and scholars simply assumed that there would be religion in all societies. With this assumption in the background, they looked for the &amp;lsquo;beliefs&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;gods&amp;rsquo; of these societies. In the process, these western minds invented religions everywhere. Later scholars began to create all kinds of definitions of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; in order to accommodate their (cultural) intuition that religion is universal. As though a definition of a word can help us decide on the universality of a phenomenon. After all, we don&amp;rsquo;t use a definition of the word &amp;ldquo;gravitation&amp;rdquo; in order to find out whether gravitation exists on all planets, do we?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do Indians Need: A History or the Past--S.N.Balagangadhara</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-do-indians-need-a-history-or-the-past-s-n-balagangadhara/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2012 22:55:47 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/what-do-indians-need-a-history-or-the-past-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, both in India and abroad, we see the emergence of a new intellectual trend: based on painstaking research, to write an accurate history of India. What is &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; about this approach? In one sense, as I shall explain in this article, this attempt is not novel; in another sense, which too shall be explained, there is something very new in it. I shall talk about both in the course of answering the question raised in the title, which contrasts ‘the past’ with ‘a history’. This contrast needs explication because historiography is seen as an ‘accurate recording of the past’. Yet, I am going to contrast the product of historiography, ‘a history’, with something called ‘the past’.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ad hoc explanations: why do puja to cows?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2011 03:03:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/ad-hoc-explanations-i-why-do-puja-to-cows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When we provide explanations, we should also look at their contrastive nature: why do puja to cows and not to buffalos? The problem in this case, however, is this: the explanation one gives about a tradition (you will soon see that one of the problems is to identify the explanandum itself) must also incorporate this contrast. Someone like Kanch Ilaiah has answered this question thus: the puja to cows and not to the buffalos expresses racism (that is at the origin of the caste system) because cows are white and buffaloes are always dark. In other words, you cannot simply ask for a contrastive explanation without incorporating it in a &amp;lsquo;bigger&amp;rsquo; explanation that explains the explanandum.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intentional and Causal explanations</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-and-causal-explanations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2011 00:22:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/intentional-and-causal-explanations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first question: could we have EIA of units smaller than the Cosmos?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An explanatorily intelligible account of any object, whatever that object is, is one where causal (say) and intentional explanations fall together. The causal account provides, let us say, an explanation that makes it clear what the causal antecedents of some object (or event, or phenomenon) are. (For the sake of this discussion, let us assume that theories in Natural Sciences provide us with explanations and that they are causal in nature.) The only kind of explanation we know that provides `meaning&amp;rsquo; (or reasons) for objects (or events, or phenomenon) are intentional ones: they postulate an agent; actions, objects and phenomena are seen to embody the intentions (beliefs, hopes, desires, designs, projects, etc.) of the agent. Such an explanation is an intentional explanation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
