<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Action on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/action/</link><description>Recent content in Action on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 19:59:21 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/action/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Descriptions about the world vs. Manuals for action</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 19:59:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/descriptions-vs-manuals/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It is broadly accepted that one of the most important functions of language is to describe the world outside it. Could it be the case that when it comes to the Indian systems, they all (whether it is Advaita vedanta, Yoga vasistha, visista advaita) are teaching one to act, to live in a particular way? In other words, they are not saying what there is in the world but are manuals in a manner of speaking. Of course, in order to understand a manual you need reference points in the world. So when they say for example that when the Buddha argued for &lt;em&gt;anatman&lt;/em&gt; or Sankara spoke about &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt;, one way of interpreting, which is what most Indian philosophers have done, is that they attribute doctrines to them and say this is a description of the world. But actually they were not describing the world. Buddha does not say atman exists or does not exist or whatever. Sankara is not saying &lt;em&gt;atman&lt;/em&gt; exists because that would be a description of our world. So what a guru does in our tradition, which is what the upadesa is, is to teach one to not look at these as descriptions of the world; he teaches one how to transform them into a way of living. So Yoga vasistha does not tell you what the world is like. That can be said in one sentence. Why then does this man have to write so much? It is to help you go on in a certain way and then say that this is not a description of the world.
(p. 308 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Truth, belief, intentionality, eudaimonia, ought</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 16:15:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/truth-belief-intentionality-eudaimonia-ought/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I want to respond to three of your points Claus. First you are not talking only about the Greeks and the Romans because all the problems arising with respect to the phenomena of non-Western societies and culture are/were equally the problems in the frameworks of different varieties of culture. You not only talk about the Greeks and the Romans, you gave examples about the French and the English as well.
The second point is: you talk about the fact that people face the same problem in Europe of today when they talk about the Greeks and the Romans. You are absolutely right. But that confirms my point, namely, that the Greeks and the Romans had no religion. They were Pagan cultures and this is exactly the problem with India. The Christian culture doesn’t understand Greek — the whole of Heidegger’s philosophy is an example of that. He says we cannot think Greek. And his whole attempt to speak about what thinking is, what truth is, etc. — is an attempt to rescue the Greek language from what he called the Christianization of Latin. I am aware that contemporary European languages and modern Europe do have problems with the Greeks and Romans. But just because of the fact that Ancient Greece and Rome are located in the Western hemisphere does not make them part of Western culture. In an earlier publication, I showed that neither Greece nor Rome were cradles of Western civilization. Western Civilization is Christian Civilization, although you might not agree with that. Greece and Rome do not belong to it. That is why we Indians can understand them. Let me give you a small example — One of the most fundamental notions of Aristotle is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;, which gets translated with great difficulty as ‘well-being’, ‘feeling good’, ‘happiness’ and so on. It is a very difficult word to translate. This is not merely a translation problem because I have had discussions with Greek scholars. Aristotle asks: what is &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;? It is very difficult to achieve of course but he says once you have it you cannot lose it. I told a Greek Specialist once ‘you know nothing about Greek language’, He responded: ‘how dare you say that’! So, I said: ‘here is a simple thing, forget the translation of &lt;em&gt;eudaimoni&lt;/em&gt;a, give me one example of a human  property which once you possess, you do not lose.’ I said: ‘I do not have to understand Greek to understand what &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; means.’ And of course to this day, no Greek scholar could help me in giving one example of one human property which if once you possess you do not lose&amp;ndash;this is a fundamental property of &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt;. For the Indians here is my answer. &lt;em&gt;Eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;aananda.&lt;/em&gt; Once you have &lt;em&gt;aananda&lt;/em&gt; you do not lose it. It is equivalent in some conditions to &lt;em&gt;brahma-gyaana.&lt;/em&gt; And that is happiness indeed, beyond &lt;em&gt;sukha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;duhkha&lt;/em&gt;. So when Aristotle is talking about &lt;em&gt;eudaimonia&lt;/em&gt; I understand him and I read him carefully. Of course, there is no translation equivalent of eudaimonia in any of the European languages but that is because they have no access to that world, that conceptual framework like we Indians have. So indeed, I understand you have a problem with Greece and Rome: we understand them much better.
Two other points &amp;ndash; one on Galileo. I am not conflating the community of Christians with a community of non-Christians because one of the claims I have substantiated to which in the last fifteen years I have found no counter argument, is the following: My claim is that free thinkers and atheists, even the Communists of Europe, are actually disguised theists. That is to say that Christianity has secularized itself in political theory, in social theory, in rational choice theory; a number of theories. I can show you how assumptions from the Bible have taken secular forms. So by saying for instance, ‘look I don’t have a religious background’, it makes no difference. I know people, who do not have a religious background for generations, are atheists but they continue to have the same excuse for speaking as Christians do. For example, your ethics will be absolutely no different from Christian ethics because there is no such thing as non-Christian secular ethics present today. ‘You ought not to kill’. Don’t tell me that is an example of secular ethics. Even the notion of ‘ought not’, the normative notion itself, does not come from English: it comes from Christianity, from the Bible.
Aristotle, for example, does not have an ‘ought’. Indian languages do not have a ‘moral ought’ nor do the Chinese in their language in which Confucius wrote. These are not linguistic issues, Claus, these are problems of conceptual apparatuses that are culturally developed. So, it is in that sense that I speak about Galileo and say he made sense to the Europeans. They used his findings to investigate nature because they believed fundamentally that nature has a structure and pattern and a law which has to be discovered by human investigation. They would say that without such a structure the universe should be chaos. The whole of 2,000 years of European culture believes that, and that was Galileo’s idea as well. It is a background belief, of course, but it is a background belief of that culture and we are talking about difference between cultures. Translation is always a translation between people who use sentences, who use natural languages. So, I am shifting the level of the problem.
Last point, there is something to be said for your claim regarding the notion of belief&amp;ndash;that you can have a concept, but do not have a word&amp;ndash;that is absolutely true. That is our daily experience. I feel like saying something but I don’t know how to say it. So, you can have some sense of a concept but defined psychologically not linguistically or so cognitively. I do not know how to put it in a natural sentence. Right. But you are making out of it logical and philosophical points.
Let me put it very sharply. The notion of having a belief and the belief is always about something; this is a specific conception of man, of human beings&amp;ndash;there is philosophical anthropology which attributes some notion of intention to human beings. One of the extraordinary things about the Indian tradition is the absence of this notion of intentionality:  &lt;em&gt;agyana&lt;/em&gt;. They call it &lt;em&gt;maaya&lt;/em&gt; and many different things. So the nature of human being in the Indian tradition is that we are non-intentional creatures, which is completely incomprehensible within the framework of Christian culture. So, entertaining having a belief is not a linguistic, psychological, epistemological fact which is applicable to all human beings but is a specific assumption about the nature of human beings that comes from the Bible. So when saying that Indians have beliefs, you are not making use of any understanding of language – you are making use of a religious concept/understanding of man and saying that is what Indians have. Of course, you can say that; people have been saying that for 500 years. That is not the issue.
The issue is: is this how Indians understand themselves? In fact, if you look at the languages you find there is greater affinity when you talk of using work-words. They do not say ‘I got angry’ but ‘anger came upon me’ &amp;ndash; this is a very typical old classical Greek way of talking. ‘Why did you say that?’ ‘I do not know, my tongue moved that way’. I am literally translating local Indian languages into English&amp;ndash;this is the way we talk. In fact, even the subject notion, is not simply a linguistic subject or verb subject in action, the fundamental ontological notion of subject itself is missing in India as also the notion of agency.
Take the problem about truth: the notion of truth for applying to sentences, to propositions by some other philosophers is a very philosophical disease. If you look at the middle-ages, take Aquinas for example, he had two notions of truth: &lt;em&gt;adeequatio re&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;. One is which is adequate to the object; the other which is adequate to thoughts. Hegel used the same notion. Tarski also says there are multiple notions of truth. That notion of truth — &lt;em&gt;adaquatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt; as it prevailed for 1,900 years in Western culture referred to the fact that objects are adequate to how God conceives them. That is &lt;em&gt;adequatio intellectus&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;adequate not to human intellects, to God’s intellect. &lt;em&gt;Adequatio re&lt;/em&gt; had to do with how one related the word to both these notions and emerged, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; from any understanding of language, truth, philosophy, or logic, it arose from commenting on theologies and commenting the Bible.  (pp 162-166 &amp;ldquo;Classical Indian Thought and the English Language&amp;rdquo; edited by Mullick, et al.)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Solving vs dissolving problems</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/solving-vs-dissolving-problems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 17:05:23 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/solving-vs-dissolving-problems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the examples you refer to, you touch on an approach to situations and problems that are Indian (in the sense of culture) contrasted to which stands another culture’s way of dealing with situations. The simplest way to explicate this difference in a general way, using your examples as a reference point, would be this: when we speak of problems and solutions, there are two ways of looking at them. In the first, an existing problem gets &lt;em&gt;resolved&lt;/em&gt;: both the problem and its solution continue to exist (both in memory and in records) in their forms of appearance. They have their independent existence even though they are conceptually (and chronologically) linked to each other. That is, a problem does not ‘disappear’ after its resolution; the solution retains its status (as a solution to a particular problem) as does the problem. This is how the West looks at problems and their resolution (mostly). This is also how we think scientifically. To put it in the form of a slogan, which has its own limitations: a situation is transformed into a theoretical problem.
In human situations (i.e., situations involving human conflicts and difficulties), the above approach is &lt;em&gt;damaging&lt;/em&gt;. In the Indian way, which is geared and focused on human situations, the event (or the situation) is turned into a &lt;em&gt;practical problem&lt;/em&gt;. In such cases, the solutions &lt;em&gt;dissolve&lt;/em&gt; the problem. Neither the problem nor the solution has any existence thereafter because the &lt;em&gt;dissolution of the problem creates a new situation&lt;/em&gt;. The memory and the records of this act, which transformed one situation into another, will exist but in their status as &lt;em&gt;changed states&lt;/em&gt;: a memory or a record of how a state-change occurred because of a set of actions.
When the first way is used to deal with human problems, psychologically speaking, a trauma is ‘left behind’. In the second case, what you undergo in the world gets structured as an experience and this is what a human being accumulates over the course of its life. In a very general sense, again in the form of a slogan, a situation is made into a practical problem.
It appears to me that in situations of uncertainty and imperfect information, the second approach is better of the two. Even if a solution might not have been the best (speaking from hindsight), it enables a human being to continue to live as well as situations possibly allow. In the first approach, you continue to live as a crippled human being haunted by one or multiple traumas. (Because in ‘What does it mean to be an Indian?’ these ideas are treated in greater detail, I will not elaborate further on these here.) The general Indian approach to, say, rape, would then be contrasted with how Indian (and western) feminists speak of rape using a legal and a western language. Abortion would also be an illustration: the examples you give would then be contrasted with how the issue is ‘debated’ in the US.
Now, to the issue you raise. Is the Indian route moral and ethical? If you follow how the West has thought on morality and ethics (especially in the last 200 years or more), the answer is in the negative. This is how our intellectuals and semi-intellectuals &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt;: with the greatest possible ignorance about what the West says and about what ethics is, they reproduce their words. Moral/immoral, just/unjust, ethical/unethical, and so on. Even though most would not be able to explain what a moral obligation is or what a moral forbiddance is, they hold forth a moralizing discourse defending atrocious policies, laws, and attitudes. Those who follow the Indian way are intellectually incapable of saying or thinking coherently about their ethics: they spout what they ‘think’ Shastras say and what, according to whatever takes their fancy at the moment, dharma and adharma are. In short: all the moral talk and ethical theories in the West has only produced the most immoral civilization that humankind has the misfortune to live under. A truly humane and reasonable approach to the human predicament has generated the biggest bunch of morons that the world has ever produced in recent times, who parade their utter ignorance as knowledge.
When you formulate the above issue as a question, “pregnancy and abortion are very practical affairs - emotional yes, but not moral or ethical. Is this a right way to think about it?” the answer cannot be unambiguous. Yes, it is a moral and ethical issue &lt;em&gt;because it is a practical issue&lt;/em&gt;. Ethics and morality are practical issues par excellence: but one who talks about it (the West) has made this issue theoretical whereas the other (India) who acts in a practical way does not know how to talk about it. One is bloated with an insufferable pretention and the other is bloated with absolute ignorance. But both ply their trade on the market fighting for customers.
In simple terms: we must try to think and articulate how human issues are practical and ethical and thus live without traumas dominating our lives. A task for the millennials and the Z-generation, I suppose.
For more, read &lt;a href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/who-needs-a-world-view/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Who needs a world view&amp;rdquo; (&lt;/a&gt;esp 3.5 &amp;amp; 6.3)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Questioning the axioms</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 22:22:15 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/questioning-the-axioms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are three ideas in the West about Law that are taken as axioms. The first: all societies are founded on Law; if they are not, they ought to be. The second is that Law teaches and educates a people. Third is their corollary: only thus do a people become a Nation. As far as I know, none has shown their empirical truth or proved that they are logically necessary. But their truth-value is undisputed. When they ruled India, the British followed these axioms: they tried to educate us through Law, interfered in our festivals and social practices and the State tried to educate a barbaric people by enacting  ‘just’ laws. Romulus gave Law and made a group into a people; Moses gave Law and made a people into a Nation; Mohammed gave Law and transformed multiple nations into a caliphate; Manu acquires the exalted status of a Law-giver for the ‘Hindus’. These ideas are not dated, apparently. Today, they enjoy the same privilege they had during the colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Creation: Spontaneous or Intentional</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 22:10:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/do-indian-traditions-claim-that-the-universe-is-an-expression-of-gods-intention/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If we want to grasp the nature of the discussions in the Indian traditions, there is much we need to do beforehand: (a) identify the entity they were talking about; (b) identify the specific questions they were answering; (c) identify the generic questions that defined both the outlines of the acceptable answers and the formulation of the specific questions; etc. (The &amp;lsquo;cetera&amp;rsquo; indicates that I do not know how to enumerate all the things we need to grasp.) In the case of the propositions you have formulated, I assume that &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; is Vishnu (or even Krishna) and not, say, Shiva or Brahma because you are talking about the Madhvas. However, to keep the discussion faithful to your formulations, I will use the word &amp;lsquo;God&amp;rsquo; to refer to Vishnu.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Moral Domains. An Essay on Selfless Morality and the Moral Self—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 21:48:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-moral-domains-an-essay-on-selfless-morality-and-the-moral-self-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Disquieting Suggestion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
Arthur Danto, the well-known American philosopher, prefaced a book he wrote in the 70’s on oriental thought and moral philosophy titled &lt;em&gt;Mysticism and Morality&lt;/em&gt; with the following words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The factual beliefs (that the civilizations of the East) take for granted are &amp;hellip;too alien to our (the West’s) representations of the World to be grafted on to it, and &lt;em&gt;in consequence their moral systems are unavailable to us&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Comparative Anthropology and Action Sciences. An Essay on Knowing to Act and Acting to Know—S.N.Balagangadhara</title><link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2011 20:48:37 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/comparative-anthropology-and-action-sciences-an-essay-on-knowing-to-act-and-acting-to-know-s-n-balagangadhara/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;[ &lt;a href="https://www.philosophica.ugent.be/article/82484/galley/202298/view/"&gt;Original&lt;/a&gt;, published  &lt;em&gt;Philosophica&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;40&lt;/strong&gt; (2): 77–107]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Introduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should action sciences exist, it is obvious what they would have to study; the nature of human action, the kind of knowledge that actions generate, the process of learning to perform different types of action and so forth. Comparative anthropology, as a discipline, studies and contrasts, where such contrasts are possible, the different ways in which human beings organize their lives, think about and experience both themselves and world around them. A culture is a form of life and, as such, it is a way of going about the world. One would therefore expect to find a deep and intimate relation between action sciences on the one hand, and studies of culture on the other. A perusal of literature, however, shows the fact of the matter to be different.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>