<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dailyo on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/dailyo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dailyo on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:54:54 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/dailyo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Between ignorance and deception: Satish Deshpande&#39;s idea of reservations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:54:54 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/between-ignorance-and-deception-idea-of-reservations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Clearly, advocates of the caste-based reservation system are worried by the recent upheavals in Gujarat and beyond. In his &amp;ldquo;The Patidar idea of reservations&amp;rdquo; (&lt;em&gt;The Hindu&lt;/em&gt;, September 5), Delhi University sociologist Satish Deshpande attempts to ridicule the Patidars&amp;rsquo; demand for OBC status while expressing his support for the reservation system. In this piece, I do not wish to defend or attack any particular movement, such as that of the Patidars or the Gujjars, but merely draw attention to one simple point: Deshpande attempts to defend ignorance and immorality by drawing on arguments that exhibit the same properties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Which intolerance is growing in India?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:42:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/which-intolerance-is-growing-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Increasingly loud voices are to be heard from different capital cities in India about growing intolerance in Indian society. The western press picks up echoes and magnifies them, while ridiculing Modi’s visit to Great Britain. While one can understand that Indians chant mantras, why are Europeans reproducing them? Looking from the outside, this is a very puzzling phenomenon. Because it is unclear what exactly is at stake here, I’d like to raise some questions and reflect about them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smriti Irani will destroy Indian education for good</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/smriti-irani-will-destroy-indian-education-for-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:40:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/smriti-irani-will-destroy-indian-education-for-good/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/&#34;&gt;recent piece&lt;/a&gt; on the valedictory speech of the minister of HRD at a Kolkata workshop elicited many replies from the readers. Some found that we indulged in a personal attack, our piece lacked &amp;ldquo;logic&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;argumentation&amp;rdquo; and one of her secret admirers, in her defence, even sent us a link to a report by Saptadwipa Ghosal in &lt;em&gt;The Echo of India&lt;/em&gt;. Such responses demand an adequate reply. Actually, we wanted to show how profound her new education policy is and we failed in demonstrating it. In this piece, through the use of sophisticated hermeneutics, we shall make our mistake good.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Smriti Irani as HRD minister was a terrible choice</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 17:30:57 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/why-smriti-irani-as-hrd-minister-was-a-terrible-choice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From the mouth of some babes, pearls of wisdom and truth fall like gentle rain from heaven. From the mouth of others, idiocies pour in a torrent and are considered truth only because they occupy positions of power. We leave it to the reader to decide to which group our minister of human resource development Smriti Irani belongs. Keep in mind that she determines to a large extent the course of education, including higher education policies in India. Irani&amp;rsquo;s comments on education at the conclusion of the National Seminar on the New Education Policy in Kolkata would be shocking if they were made by a mature and intelligent human being. But, as is said, from the mouth of the babes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
