<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Theory-Ladenness on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/theory-ladenness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Theory-Ladenness on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 12:18:35 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/categories/theory-ladenness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Is wearing a bindi religious?</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-wearing-a-bindi-religious/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 12:18:35 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/is-wearing-a-bindi-religious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Depending on the context of the discussion (say a dispute about some aspect of the Indian culture), the disputants can treat wearing the bindi or a saree as facts. However, in another context of the discussion, these facts might become theoretical claims. For instance, is the Indian woman wearing a bindi or an Indian male wearing kumkum on his forehead being religious or not? Consider, for instance, the recent French legislation about wearing religious &amp;lsquo;symbols&amp;rsquo; in the public. If someone decides to take an Indian to the court, then wearing bindi or kumkum becomes an issue of dispute. Then we will have disputes: one side will claim that it is religious, and the other will probably want to say that it is not religious. (If it happens, I suggest they use &amp;lsquo;The Heathen in His Blindness: Asia, the West and the dynamic of religion&amp;rsquo;!) In such a case, wearing a bindi will be described using two kinds of theories about wearing a bindi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation, Interpretation and Culture: On the disingenuity of a comparative theology</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2013 00:42:15 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/on-the-disingenuity-of-a-comparative-theology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check Balu&amp;rsquo;s paper on comparative theology, and in particular Francis Clooney&amp;rsquo;s:&#xA;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/5497443/On_the_Disingenuity_of_a_Comparative_Theology&#34;&gt;Translation, interpretration and culture: on the disingenuity of a comparative theology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vivekananda and Caste Discrimination: theory-ladenness</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:52:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/vivekananda-and-caste-theory-ladenness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;You ask whether or not it was &amp;lsquo;factual&amp;rsquo; that a &amp;lsquo;paraiah&amp;rsquo; was not allowed on the same street as a Nair or a Brahmin. The evidence we have says that a Paraiah was not allowed to be on the same street as a Nair, but it is not clear whether it also applies to the presence of a Brahmin. First, here is some of the evidence.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Portuguese traveler Duarte Barbosa was among the first to talk about it in &amp;lsquo;The Book&amp;rsquo;. Though written in 1518, it became known to the European world through the Italian translation in the book of travels edited by Gian Baptista Ramusio. In the English translation, we hear who the Nairs are: &amp;ldquo;None may become a Nayre, save only he who is of Nayre lineage. They are very free from stain in their nobility. They will not touch anyone of low caste&amp;rdquo; . You need to keep in mind that Barbosa does not speak of &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo;, as an earlier footnote by the English editor and translator, Dames, indicates: &amp;ldquo;The word used in the text in vilam (villão in modern spelling) corresponding to the English villain in its ancient sense&amp;rdquo; . In other words, Barbosa appears to have seen a distinction in lineage or a distinction between the Nobility and the Rural folk when he saw the Nairs and the &amp;rsquo;low caste&amp;rsquo; people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>‘Facts’ are facts of a theory</title>
      <link>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 20:39:40 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yogirk.github.io/hipkapi/posts/facts-are-facts-of-a-theory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Until the sixties of the previous century, there was some kind of consensus about the nature of scientific enterprise. One strand within it had to do with the nature of facts. One thought that scientists collected facts (data) and formulated hypothesis (or theories) to explain them. This distinction between theory and facts was seen as an absolute distinction: facts (or data) existed in Nature (or culture) and theories explained them. However, today, the consensus tells us that this is not the case. (This distinction has been scrutinized from many different points of view since the fifties: in terms of language, in terms of the history of the sciences, in terms of scientific revolutions, in terms of philosophy of sciences&amp;hellip;) Today, one accepts that facts are not some theory-neutral entities existing in either Nature or culture and that the distinction between them is a relative distinction. All our facts are theory-dependent; in some contexts we treat some of the claims of a background theory as facts. In another context, the same facts are discussed as theoretical claims.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For instance, in some contexts, one takes the Hindus worshipping Ganesha as a fact. (This fact, for instance, functions as evidence that Ganesha is a god and/or that Hinduism is a religion and so on.) In another context, the same fact becomes an issue of theoretical controversy: are the Hindus worshipping Ganesha or not? (I challenge that nature of this fact and suggest that some kind of theology describes our actions in these terms.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
