<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gelders on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</title>
    <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/gelders/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gelders on All Roads Lead to Jerusalem</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/categories/gelders/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mantras of Anti-Brahmanism: Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2011 09:08:41 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/mantras-of-anti-brahmanism-colonial-experience-of-indian-intellectuals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colonial Experience of Indian Intellectuals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Opposing factions in the Orientalist-Anglicist controversy in the 19th century shared a common understanding of Indian religion and society. Europeans from diverse ideological and religious backgrounds identified the brahmins as priests and brahmanism as a &amp;lsquo;religion of the priests&amp;rsquo;. This common understanding derived its consistency from a Christian understanding of religion. Even the writings of Rammohun Roy and Babasaheb Ambedkar, this article suggests, reveal an unconditional acceptance of Europe&amp;rsquo;s conceptualisation in a debate over religion that continued into the 20th century&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Indian reformers understood Protestant Reformation?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-indian-intellectuals-understood-protestant-reformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2011 03:42:18 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:58012/hipkapi/posts/how-indian-intellectuals-understood-protestant-reformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the second half of the nineteenth century, some western-educated, Bombay intellectuals came together in the Prarthana Samaj (inspired by Keshub Sunder Sen of the Brahmo Samaj). Perhaps the best known members of the Prarthana Samaj were Mahadev Govind Ranada and Narayan Chandavarkar (the Vice-Chancellor of Bombay University). Both reformers advocated what they literally called &lt;em&gt;Hindu Protestantism&lt;/em&gt;. Below, I will present what I believe to be illustrations of the distortion that occurs when these intellectuals talk about reform.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
